hello and welcome everyone welcome back
this is the second interval of the third
applied active inference Symposium at
the Active inference Institute on August
22nd 2023
this is going to be another pact and
exciting interval and we're kicking it
off with Jean Francois katir a
collective of theorizers First Steps so
JF thank you for joining and to you for
this presentation and if anybody has
questions for this presentation or any
of the others please just put it in the
live chat and I'll do it I can so thanks
JF to you
well uh thank you Daniel
um I'm a software engineer a company
called smart rent where I write software
for smart home systems and I also work
on a research project at the Active
inference Institute called the Robotics
and embodied project
my current focus is on supervised
learning in active inference agents
in my presentation today which is titled
a collective of theorizers First Steps
um I'll first start with a brief recap
of the project
then dive into recent progress and then
I'll conclude with what I see as the
next steps of the project
well since 2017 I've been experimenting
with Lego robots and models of cognition
I do this for my own education
because like I think most of us I
understand something better when I build
it
what you see here is the my latest robot
model it's a Rover
it has a whole bunch of sensors and a
number of effectors actuators as a
matter of fact Those sensors and
actuators can be understood as forming
the marker of blanket of my robot
last year I presented at the Symposium
about the history of the project it's uh
then status and it's ambitions
I presented a cognitive model that
implemented predictive processing from
an active inference perspective so they
were uh genetic models there was
predictions there was prediction errors
and
um the these generative models animated
the robots so that they would roam avoid
obstacles uh observe their uh companion
and also in a very simplistic way build
a theory of Mind of the other robot they
could uh from observations
infer that uh the other robot had
detective food food being presented here
as a sheet of paper on the floor and
then would uh kind of try to track the
other robot to also get to the food
and and fun stuff like this the
implementation uh combined uh
multi-processing and functional
Computing there was nothing
probabilistic in the implementation
I thought maybe you would uh see them in
action that's what's presented last year
but just to get a sense of what they do
I have two robots here
um one named Carl and Andy I named them
before I knew I was going to present at
the conference
um so uh they benefited from a number of
training sessions they uh learned how to
um uh find which policies would achieve
their goals better than others and uh
one here on the left found the food
rather right away but got closer to the
pedestal uh where the beacon is that
simulates the scent of food
um
fear was getting into a collision and
then backs off in a hurry as we'll see
the other robot observes all this sees
the other the the the robot backing off
as being in a panic and uh decides to
share in in this emotion and backs up as
well so you know uh fun stuff
the um since from the beginning I've
implemented different cognition models
but they all have in common the fact
that they Implement a Society of Mind
um so what is a Society of Mind a
Society of Mind is a concept by which
um the uh the mind is not a monolithic
uh structure but a composition of simple
actors
independent actors that interact with
each other in simple ways
that uh view of the Mind was put forth
by by Marvin Minsky
um 50 years ago so this is not recent
again what I presented last year was a
Society of Mind containing a hierarchy
of I call them cognition actors each
cognition actor is an independent
process
each one has a scope
um
a level of abstraction as well so for
example you would have a commission
actor that's concerned with the location
of food
and it would have beliefs and
perceptions about food location and
these would feed into a higher level
cognition actor let's say food approach
which is concerned about getting closer
to the food and so forth and so on these
connection actors communicate again in
simple ways this is the Society of Mind
and and they communicate by emitting
predictions predictions about the
beliefs of other cognizant actors and
they communicate by emitting prediction
errors when predictions made about their
beliefs by others uh are inaccurate
that leads to uh coaching actors
processing these uh prediction errors
and combining them with their own
predictions to create a an updated set
of perceptions that are synthesized into
beliefs and these beliefs lead to
um actions in order to eliminate
negative beliefs and Val or validate
positive beliefs
now it's from the interactions of all
these connection actors that seemingly
purposeful behaviors emerge
so that was successful but learning was
very limited this um this hierarchy of
congression and actors uh was given was
pre-defined and the only learning that a
robot would would do was to discover
which action policies tended to be more
effective
so clearly my robots are not monolithic
um active inference agents
um so the question is why would I
use a Society of Mind architecture well
because I I subscribe uh to the uh
notion that all intelligence is
collective intelligence
and and this paper makes uh the argument
uh quite cogently and I'm gonna I'm
gonna cite a number of papers which were
important to the evolution of my
thinking this is one of them
this paper sees intelligence as a
process
and not a property it's a process
enacted by the interacting parts
as opposed to again a property of
individuals
so a Society of Mind is basically that
it's a it's actually a um a number of
interacting processes
um that together from which emerge
apparently intelligent behaviors now my
my own personal current definition of
intelligence is uh self-sustaining and
active sense making since making is
really important by autonomous agent
system
in a dissipative and dynamic environment
and this guides
um all the work I do in this project
now if you want a um description a
detailed description of uh
where my project stood at the a year ago
there's a paper that was published that
I published on xenodone which you can
look up
now over the last year I wanted to move
away from a
pre-built a given Society of Mind and
toward a learned Society of Mind I
wanted to see if
um I could program an autonomous robot
to evolve in Society of Mind through its
interactions with its environment
now one might think that programming
autonomy is an oxymoron
um it's it's it's it's it would be a
good point but I don't think it is
um if if the program I write and and
install my robots uh imparts uh
constitutive autonomy which is uh enable
the robot to constitute its own identity
and if it imparts adaptivity which uh
enable the robot to uh modify itself
from its interactions with the
environment then I think that
um uh the the robot uh will be truly
autonomous
now for autonomy to um
to exist inherently in the robot
something in the robot must be at stake
and in it's different it's in this case
it's the survival of the robots Society
of mind now
the physical structure of the robot is
not uh at stake it's survival is not at
stake unless of course it falls off a
shelf
but as I intend to
um have my robot develop its Society of
Mind from experiences I also expect that
if it fails that the Society of mine
will perish in its attempt to to grow
and sustain itself
so that's what's at stake in in this
current and going forward in this
project is the robots survive the
survival of the robot Society of mine
and and this survival would be an
expression of being by doing uh the
robot need will need to act an interact
in its environment in order to uh
survive
now whatever sense it's going to make of
its environment will then be grounded in
this survival imperative in essence the
robot Society of mine will have skin in
the game
if this weren't the case then sense
making would actually reside somewhere
else it would reside in in in in the
mind of the of the programmer in my mind
as I observe uh the robots but I would
like the sense making to be grounded
in the survival of the robot's mind
itself
so that's key
now what do I mean by an evolving and
growing uh Society of Mind so instead of
the given Society of Mind which I I
showed uh earlier I want
um I want the cognition actors to uh be
created to connect with each other
dynamically through interactions with
the environment
um so I want an active uh
self-organizing
self-optimizing Collective of cognition
actors now is this feasible well that's
a big question
um in order to and in trying to answer
this question uh I'll be
um also answering uh questions like what
must be given a priori and what can be
discovered well I already have elements
of an answer I know that the um the
sensors and the uh effectors and the um
the cognition the Primitive cognition
actors that wrap them will be given this
this will be like what you're born with
basically and there might be a um a meta
cognition actor which uh role will be to
uh oversee and guide the evolution of uh
all other cognition actors but that's
that's my hypothesis
I can imagine a test environment for my
robot that will test its ability to
survive I can imagine for example that
um as the the robot uh moves around or
computes it it uses a Limited store of
energy it's simulated
and that store of energy is replenished
when the robot consumes food that would
be by being on top of
pieces of paper colored pieces of paper
on the floor
um and I'm going to make sure that it
needs two sources of food in order to
survive right that would be represented
by a yellow paper and a green paper for
example so that to prevent the the robot
from just simply finding one one source
of food and just stationing itself over
it so the environment will also contain
obstacles so the robot will need to
learn how to navigate avoid obstacles
locate different sources of food get to
them and make sure that it it alternate
between various sources of food in order
to survive and the um Society of Mind
that will evolve will uh hopefully
evolve to successfully do this
else if it doesn't then it will
um shrink as resources uh disappear and
uh essentially uh die so that's when
it's at stake uh for uh this robot
now this effort employs a a number of
Frameworks
um
and by framework I mean a useful system
of concept and constraints that that
guide uh the implementation
well there's obviously the the free
energy principle and the active
inference framework
um
however I see this the IC active
inference as and as if framework it
describes the what what must be achieved
in this case uh reduction of the agent's
uh variational free energy but it
doesn't guide me as to the
implementation how to build the robot
for this
um I need as is Frameworks and um I'll
be using uh two Frameworks one which
I've been using since uh the beginning
of the project which is uh the actor
model
uh the actor model uh views computation
as
um uh diversity of processes processes
that are independent have their own
private internal State and who
communicate with one another strictly
through messages
um yesterday in uh interval one uh Keith
Duggar uh presented on the actor model
and made the case that we should use the
actor model to implement active
inference agents well I wholeheartedly
agree with them
the other uh framework that I'm going to
be using is a special case of symbolic
AI called the app reception engine and
much of the presentation will be about
the opposition engine and its
implementation
so here's where we are uh is the project
is located at the intersection of active
inference as a domain the what and
Society of Mind as a architecture and
symbolic AI as a form of computing
um so that's where the project is at
this intersection
no so where to begin so I I want to
um uh dive into
um
a more extensive form of learning and
the first step uh logically is to learn
how to predict so
um I want to enable a single uh
cognition actor we'll start with a
single cognition actor to
um learn how to make sense of its local
environment it's so-called unvelt and
making sense implies
at a minimum to be able to predict
incoming Sensations so it needs to learn
to predict
so
what will be given to a cognition actor
well a uh there will be a history of uh
Sensations uh broken into discrete uh
units of time
so time n minus 3 and N minus two n
minus 1 time n which is the the present
moment
so these would be remembered
observations
and then what we want to get out of this
is the ability to predict the next
incoming set of Sensations at time uh T
equals n plus 1 and plus two
and for this
to be able to predict uh future
observations we need some kind of
predictor function
that is learned from the remembered
observation
now this predictive capability can be
built in two very general ways one is
from statistics uh so doing pattern
analysis and and being able to predict
what's most probable which is the
standard Uh current machine learning
approach or we could predict from an
understanding of uh the observations by
developing a causal model
uh of these of what uh produce these
Sensations
and from this understanding uh predict
what rationally should be observed next
so this is all about
sense making
and now what is sense making how do I
understand sense making
um
well to rationally predict incoming
sensory inputs uh one must make sense of
them that's what making sense means to
me
um and to make sense of sensory inputs
means to derive meaningful experiences
from them it's not just data it's not
just pieces of data it's a there must be
meaningful experiences and by experience
uh I mean a conceptualization of the
sensations
and a unification of them in time in
space so making sense of these inputs
will mean to
produce meaningful experiences that are
conceptualizations and unifications of
the sensations now an experience is
Meaningful
if it is underwritten by a causal model
so the expense is uh is uh
is perceived as the consequences of a
latent generative model
a generative process that we have
modeled
and I want meaning to be inherent to the
agent and that only happens if the agent
is truly autonomous and if this meaning
is grounded in the survival imperative
as uh discussed earlier
so how does expansing work
how can that be put into computer code
surprisingly for this we refer to the
philosophy of Emmanuel Kant
a reverse engineering approach
um asking himself what must entities do
to achieve experience
this is akin to the free energy
principles high road which can be
paraphrased as what most organisms do to
maintain their existence so in manual
con uh we've tried to reverse engineer
um uh cognition
um asking himself what's the minimal
cognitive apparatus needed by an entity
to have experiences
and and that he he documented in his
critique of pure reason just a little
parenthesis
um the the meaning of of the title
critic of pure reason is not what I
thought it was it's actually translates
more closely to the case for a period
recognition
a critique is is a legal term is where
you make your case and pure reason uh we
translate nowadays is a priori cognition
so
um
his work wanted to establish what must
happen to create an experience that's
coherent that is Unified in time and
space
um and to reverse engineering cognition
as a system that is both complete and
essential that is minimal
okay so let's let's
um I'm gonna try to give you the uh
posted uh postage stamp uh version of uh
Emmanuel Theory uh focusing on the
synthetic Unity of Apperception
well first of all there's the real world
which is outside of our direct
experience uh it's the numina it's
forever hidden from us
um as an as is uh
reality but we do uh it it impinges on
our sensorium and then so we have a
number of intuitions site sound touch
smell
um that are initially uh separate and
and then we need to uh Network them
connect them both in time and in space
in space
um uh is is sound and and and and the
site uh describing a single thing
um uh is one thing uh behind or uh
inside another
um and in time is this happening before
after uh something else and and then at
a higher level uh meaning is given to
these uh networked intuitions Sensations
uh via Concepts and and judgments rules
uh which are generalizations as to what
can and cannot be
um and this is what we experience
now it it turns out that a con synthetic
Unity of that perception is
um
a blueprint for automating a sense
making
um
and it's kind of uh interesting I think
that 18th century philosophy would be uh
relevant to uh 21st century uh
technology development
and this is what happened and and and
was published uh by Richard Evans and
and all in the paper making sense of
sensory input where um they developed
the app reception engine
they took um synthetic Unity of our
perception as software requirements and
successfully implemented uh them into a
piece of software the app reception
engine and applied it to a number of uh
exercises
um and where they got a very good result
so the opposition engine is in um an
instance of machine learning it's
unsupervised machine learning and it
operates on very small data sets
um and generates uh human readable uh
generative models
and when I read the paper I realized
well that's exactly uh what my robots
needed
so what doesn't that perception engine
do well given a a sequence of observed
States
it uh finds a generative model
that can recreate past States but most
importantly predict uh future uh States
and the state is defined as a set of
simultaneous uh observations Sensations
intuitions
so
an app reception engine
searches for a causal theory that can
recreate observations I say searches
because this causal theory is not
determined by the observations
it has to be found it has to be
discovered but
once
it is found
then it can be validated against the
observations and see and see if it can
recreate them and augment them
into the future
as well as into the past
so what what is a causal Theory
a causal theory is is a logic program
that has a number of components
um they're in the causal Theory there
will be
um the objects and the predicates from
The observed uh relation so from the
observations we can extract what objects
were observed and what properties of
these objects were observed and maybe
what relationships and these these
objects were observed
that's the start then we have latent
object types objects and predicates so
we may want to imagine causal Theory
imagines a hidden objects maybe in types
of objects and maybe hidden uh
properties and relationships between uh
objects uh latent meaning unobserved and
given both The observed and unobserved
um uh
objects and and and and
predicates it
derives rules
first of all constraints on those
predicates what's permissible so for
example being in front of cannot uh a
cannot be in front of B N at the same
time B and at the same time behind B so
an object cannot be in front of another
and behind it so they're constrained
some predicates
And Then There are rules that apply to
any simultaneous sets of observations
what what uh they must conform to Then
There are rules that given a state will
infer the next state and then maybe some
initial state from which we can uh uh uh
run the causal Theory
so
what makes a causal Theory Unified
well first of all it needs to be unified
in order to make sense of the
observation
there are various Dimensions so if a
causal Theory involves a number of
objects all these objects must be
directly or indirectly related there's
no object that just floats in space
totally independent of the other objects
so they must all be related
um so they're they're spatially Unified
all predicates that make up the uh
causal Theory like
on off the hind in front they must be uh
constrained so that
um for example in front cannot be at the
same time as behind or that a light
cannot be both turned on and turned off
so there's there's some restrictions on
uh the predicates and that creates
conceptual Unity
and in the aesthetic Unity where all
simultaneous relations must satisfy the
static rules and temporal Unity where
all the states must be sequenced by
causal rules
we'll see examples
so
let's
start with a an example here
of a set of observations what we are
observing are two lights
uh and the lights can either be at any
discrete Moment In Time
either on or off so here we have a
sequence of uh observations uh and One
Moment In Time
the first light was off and the second
night was on then
the first light was on the certain light
was off
then both were on Etc
and I put the grape bars there
um to show that maybe the observations
aren't complete so on one stage we can
only see the second light or there may
be other lights or other objects that we
do not see but that's what we observe
so
you feed these observations
um in discrete time
into the art perception engine
and the opposite perception engine
searches for a causal Theory that when
applied to an initial
condition let's say that the light A is
often light B is on it will create a a
trace of uh recreated observations
that um
cover is a superset matches the initial
observations and if this happens then
our causal theory is a good one
now the causal Theory May infer uh the
existence of hidden objects hidden
relations and whatnot it may actually
need to
okay so here's a an example of a causal
theory that is generated by my own
implementation of the perception engine
because I I re-implemented the the
perception engine as described in the
paper by Richard Evans and all
and um
I ran it on this the set of observations
about lights on uh two lights uh one on
one off at any point in time
and it came up with it found a result it
found the result in uh 64 seconds
it was a perfect match
and it
um it actually invented a relationship
which is called thread one
um which we can that's that's imagine
that it's actually means connects to
and it found a static Rule and a causal
rule uh it said that a light is on
at any moment in time a light is on if a
light that connects to it is off
and it found a causal rule that said
um a light turns off if it uh connects
to another light that was also off
so that's how the the lights change over
time the status of on and off and it
came up with initial conditions that
said that well
a connects to first of all that there's
an object one a light called object one
that we don't see but is there we
imagine is there that a connects to it
uh the light object one connects to B
and the light B connects to object one
so that's the causal rule that it
discovered
now if we uh run uh this causal rule
produce a Trace
and as you can see the trace matches the
observation it adds an a new object so
the coverage being uh excellent the
perfect in this case and our causal
theory is a good one it's actually a
perfect one
it's no it's not necessarily the only
one though
so is this causal Theory Unified
so going back to uh Dr Khan's
requirement of synthetic Unity of that
perception not every causal Theory will
do though it may
predict correctly it may not be
meaningful unless it is Unified
well is it we've saw the fourth
dimension there's four dimensions of
unification is it specially spatially
unified well all our objects are
connected
directly or indirectly to each other
that's good
so we have spatial unification
do we have conceptual unification so we
have this new predicate we have two
predicates right uh Fred one which we uh
translate to connects to and then the
predicate that says uh whether the light
is on or off
well we have a constraint that says that
um
a a light can only be connected to one
other light so Fred one has a constraint
on it that says it uh
uh it it's it's
exclusive so an object cannot have read
one to two objects you cannot connect to
two objects that's a constraint of us
discovered and part of the causal Theory
and also uh implicitly
um a uh the uh on uh relation of the
predicate as the value on or off and it
cannot be both at the same time so
it's conceptually Unified
is it statically unified or are the
rules of static rules obeyed well uh for
example the static rule would say that
uh given that b uh connects uh to a if B
is off then a must be on so if you look
at any uh place where B is off a is
going to be on and you could do that for
uh every uh other uh light and
relationships between lights so they
they all obey the static Rule and the
causal rule says in for example here
that if B connects to a then if a was
off then B must turn off so if you look
at uh B let's say e or B was off
um
yeah if I'm sorry if uh B connects to a
and yes
and if a was off
B must be off so if a was off b b
becomes off the next step so that's
correct as well
so statically uh we are true and
temporarily we are true
we are unified and of course that uh we
get a thumbs up from uh Dr Kant
our causal theory is Unified thus makes
it makes sense of the observations of
the sensory inputs
now it's no accident uh that um
uh can't would be with figure in an
active inference project there is a link
uh between active inference and Kant and
it runs through the the celebrated 19th
century uh German engineer Herman Von
ham Holtz
he was a disciple of Kant and he
developed the theory of uh visual
perception that operationalized Khan's
epistemology and in fact it anticipates
predictive processing uh in 1995 uh
Peter dahin and Jeff Hinton uh developed
the helmholz machine name is in his
Hunter
um and it is a type of artificial neural
network that's trained to create a
generic model uh from an original set of
data and it can account for the hidden
structure of the data
so there's a as you see there's a
there's a link which is uh discussed and
elaborated in this paper which is very
very interesting paper
all right so
close parentheses so we've looked at the
perception engine uh from the
perspective of philosophy
so uh
now let's look at it through the lens of
machine learning
um
we the observations that constitute a
training set it's a very small one
and the opposition engine is uh the
learning algorithm and what is learned
the output is a causal Theory
um so the the learning process is uh is
unsupervised logical inferencing
and the um the output is a human
readable logic program so we see here
that there's there's some profound
differences with uh the more popular
form of machine learning in that the
training set is really small
um that uh the uh the product of uh the
the learning the uh is actually a human
readable artifact in this case a logic
program
so this is the training set
um uh as as inputted lights
led a
turned off
at time one B turned on at time one a
term on at time two be turned off at
time two etc etc
so that's the training set
and you feed this into the um uh
Obsession perception engines algorithm
and out comes a uh causal uh Theory so
in in a little bit more details uh what
the algorithm is and does first it
extracts
um the uh
observed object extend objects the
object types and predicates from the
observations so we have on we have
object a object B we have led as an
object type so that's all part of the
observations and that becomes part of
the extent vocabulary
then the opposition engine
imagines
uh unobserved objects types and and
predicates uh for the relationships and
properties and that becomes a latent
vocabulary so there's a a step of
imagination then using the combined
vocabulary you know the both the extent
and and latent vocabulary combined it
looks for a unified causal Theory a set
of constraints rules and initial
conditions that uh obey the um the rules
of um the constraints of uh synthetic uh
Unity of our perception
um once it has this causal Theory and
with initial conditions it applies the
causal Theory to these conditions and
produces a Trace
uh it recreates observations if you want
and and augments them and and extends
them into the future
uh now it looks at this trace and
Compares it with the initial
observations for coverage and decides if
this is a good causal Theory or not then
it also looks at the causal Theory
complexity how many rules how complex
are the rules
Etc and um measures for complexity so if
we have a choice between two uh causal
theories of equivalent coverage
um the app perception engine will uh
select the least complex one using
Occam's razor
now if you look at this algorithm you'll
see that the the the boxes in green are
um not uh deterministic that's this is
where search happens we can posit
different kinds of objects we can find
different kinds of rules so this this
was this is where search happens
now
app reception is implemented using logic
inference actually it uses uh three
forms of logic inference there's the one
that we're more familiar with which is
uh deduction where given rules and
causes we we infer the effects then
there's uh induction we're given causes
and effect we look for the rules this is
what science does right looking for
rules that would account for uh effects
given the causes
then there's abduction where given the
rules and given what we observe the
effects we're looking for the causes in
this case we're looking for the latent
objects the latent or relationships
between these objects
and then you can combine both abduction
and induction where you're given effects
essentially observations and you're
looking for both causes and rules which
is what the app reception engine does
and this is where in the um in the
algorithm uh these kinds of inferences
uh are at Play
so positing latent objects that's that's
a form of abduction
uh imagining causes finding the rules
well that's clearly a a form of
induction
and then applying the rules to uh uh of
a causal Theory to
um some initial conditions to create a
trace well that's that's deduction we
have the causes the initial conditions
we have the rules causal Theory and then
we produce a trace the effects so that's
that's deduction so the app reception
engine uses all forms of logical
inference
and and now just a reminder that um the
output of the perception engine that is
what is learned is actually human
readable uh you may want to compare that
to a a large
array of floating points uh
produced by a traditional the more uh
popular form of machine learning
nowadays so here this is what's actually
produced by the app reception engine as
it runs on a set of observations it
produces
um a logic program that is human
readable the only when you look at it
the only thing you need to to kind of
guess is what does the what what is
meant by pred one and if you think well
maybe it means connects to maybe the
lights are connected underneath uh a
board out of sight of um
of the Observer
but finding a unified causal theory is
hard so we have to guess what the latent
objects and predicates are what what are
the hidden uh lights what are the hidden
relationships between lights and we have
to discover what constraints might apply
on the predicates
um and what are the initial conditions
from which we want to recreate a trace
uh what are the static rules that apply
to a simultaneous observations and then
what are the causal rules that given uh
observations at time T will predict
observations at time t plus one this
this is hard
as a matter of fact it's a non-polar
polynomially hard uh the search space
grows exponentially with the size of the
input which is the the the the the size
of the uh accident extent and latent
vocabularies and
so just like in chess you can't uh
predict to the end the consequence of a
move because of Contour explosion with
the app perception engine you cannot
systematically Traverse the entire space
of possible causal theories to find a
good one because it's impossibly large
so the job of the app reception engine
is to find a causal theory in a
ridiculously large haystack
how to do this
in my implementation I follow the uh the
the the recommendations in in uh and and
I follow also the implementation in
Richard Evans paper by breaking the
search space into uh chunks
first I there's a region and the region
says
um so how many latent object types
objects and predicates will we allow so
what is the limit of imagination of the
cognition actors that is trying to uh
perceive a causal Theory what are the
limits of its imagination and within
that region
um of bounded imagination
um we
carve it into templates where we say
okay we're going to use these latent
objects types these latent objects and
uh so basically what vocabulary specific
vocabulary we're going to be using we're
going to use object one we're going to
use object uh thread one on top of the
uh observed on uh predicate and observed
A and B lights and we're going to set
the maximum complexity on the rules and
see if within uh we can find causal
theories that fit this template so this
is a carving up of the search space
and having broken the search space into
regions and templates
uh
we have Scopes in which to apply
heuristics now why heuristics because
the systematic traversal in it cannot be
done in reasonable time there's just too
many uh candidate causal theories to to
look at to find a good one so we use
heuristics we find
we we find ways of maybe getting to a
good solution faster at the risk of
missing it but at least uh we'll have an
answer or no answer in a reasonable
amount of time and there's a number of
of heuristics that I have implemented in
my implementation of the perceptron
engine
well there's time boxing at some point
you'd spend no more than this amount of
time looking into a region or into a
template
uh there's multitasking well the problem
is actually as they say embarrassingly
parallel you can explore multiple
regions and multiple templates in
parallel and so make good use of a
multi-core uh computer
uh you want to make sure you don't
repeat yourself so you don't want to uh
Traverse the same region uh twice or
look at the same puzzle Theory twice
you want to satisfy you may be a good
enough theory is just fine we don't want
to look for the perfect one necessarily
we may not have time
um you want to fail early if you're in a
region where nothing good is found you
may want to leave it uh quite quickly at
the risk of maybe not finding the a good
one that is just over the horizon but
you want to be impatient you want to
throw the dice you may want to kind of
mix it up so that every time you run the
Apple session engine on the same problem
uh you may find a solution a a different
solution first
um you want to uh go for The Simple
Solution first you may not want to try
everything to sample sum we want to
start with the the easiest uh part of
the the search base first be judicious
and so forth and so on and most
importantly be selective so reject any
uh causal theory that would fail the the
the constraints of unity of our
perception with all these in place
on the running my implementation of the
app reception engine gives pretty good
results so here I I did a run this is
not Cherry Picked I said decided to do
one a series of seven runs uh and
collect the data and show it and in this
run I set up the app position engine to
only accept a perfect causal Theory one
that would uh produce a trace that
totally covers the observation so and I
did seven runs uh the first one
succeeded found it in four seconds
uh the second one it took 102 seconds so
there's there's some randomization in in
the order in which things have searched
is luck is involved as I said
um the third one one second that was
that was pretty cool the the the fourth
one well took 204 seconds
uh then 96 12.99 so uh what a a good
distribution here
now I said okay I'm gonna I'm gonna run
the perception engine again on the same
uh training set that I showed earlier
those two lights
but this time I said um I'm gonna be uh
I'm going to accept the theory that has
at least that has at least 80 that has
85 or more coverage so it it predicts it
it it recreates the the the observations
well enough but not perfectly and I uh
time boxed it to 30 seconds so you have
30 seconds to find It Go
um the first run it signed a a causal
Theory with 75 percent uh accuracy uh
immediately then the same accuracy same
coverage 10 seconds 11 seconds it hit 80
29 seconds it found a perfect one
then 11 it found 87 coverage and stopped
right there that's good enough 75 again
100 is the first one it found above 85
in 18 seconds and 75 zero seconds so a
good distribution again so we're getting
into uh reasonable times we're not
talking about hours here we're talking
about seconds and I'm I'm hoping to um
do further optimizations and bring it
down to something even smaller so that a
cognition actor can say uh uh I want to
make sense of these observations
uh
query the app reception engine and get
an answer a causal Theory within uh
maybe a couple of seconds That's My Hope
now something interesting sir it so
happens that what makes it hard for the
app perception engine to find a good
causal theory is formally equivalent to
what makes cognitive science as a whole
hard and that's this paper here makes
the case uh and proves the case uh quite
quotiently
um so um
the cognitive science wants to find
models functions or algorithms that
explain account for
um situated behaviors so you you feed in
uh you feed into this this the cognitive
science machine
um pairs of situations and behaviors and
you want to come out of it a a model an
explanation a a function or an algorithm
that accounts for it
well the the paper makes the case that
if if if the explanation is is to be
bounded in size then the the the the
problem is computable
but it's not tractable in the same
meaning that it's combinatorially
explosive but once you have a solution
it is uh computable and tractable to
verify that the solution is good that it
accounts for the um the uh the data that
you're trying to understand well this is
this is equivalent formerly equivalent
to what the app reception engine is
doing
um
my implementation was done in prologue
uh I will not go into the details it's
about a thousand lines of prologue I'll
just say that prologue is a programming
language uh that use deductive inference
as its model of computation with
backtracking
um so essentially it searches it
searches for a solution and will
backtrack if it took the wrong
um Branch if you want it and and and
we'll look for a different way of
satisfying a a line of the program
um so let's just say that it it makes
traversing a search space uh it gives we
get traversing a search points for free
when we program in prologue I won't go
into any more details but you can see
some prologue code here and it's uh the
fun thing is that um a a prologue
program is akin to a logical description
of the problems trying to solve
I think it's very cool
and the
prologue environment was augmented by
something called constraint handling
rules which is an extension to prologue
that adds abductive reasoning so
basically in the program you can say
assume this is true until proven
otherwise and the um the uh the rules
the CHR rules
um are there to uh verify if it can be
proven otherwise
so um again I'm not asking you to
understand this quote at all but I want
you to realize that this code is the
code that actually executes a causal
Theory
um both the static and causal rules to
build traces it is that small it's it's
very powerful so combining prologue in
CHR
um I found extraordinarily uh powerful
and very excited about it I'm a
programmer
next steps
well next steps now that we've solved uh
individual learning by cognitive uh
actors
well I want to move to uh beliefs from
uh
from the sensations and to policies to
validate or eliminate beliefs
um a lot of these beliefs actually fall
out of our perception latent objects and
latent relationships and properties are
can be considered by as beliefs then
there are other kinds of beliefs that
can be uh obtained from uh what's been
not perceived
um they'll be introspective beliefs uh
that uh
uh communicate
um how the cognitive cognition actor is
doing in terms of competence
predictionary rates
um how well uh it's um its our
perception is doing is and whether it is
uh engaging with other cognition actors
is it relevant
I will have feelings which will provide
normativity to these beliefs so if uh
feelings are signals of uh risk to
homeostasis uh loss of resources
physical damage uh too many prediction
errors so that's hunger pain and fear uh
and feelings will take beliefs over time
and
tainted beliefs and Norm
good beliefs bad beliefs will want to be
eliminated or validated through policies
um that will be synthesized by the
cognition actor
and each cognition actor Will emit uh
make available to others
um its API what what predictions can be
made about the beliefs of this cognition
actor what actions uh are available to
others to be uh uh asked of the
connection connection actor
and then as cognition actors uh uh
connect to one another
uh as the uh Junction actors formed the
um belt of other cognition actors
then uh the a construction actor will be
able to predict the beliefs of others
will be able to uh compose policies made
out of actions that are implemented by
other cognition actors
and eventually
um we'll have a Society of Mind which is
a bunch of intersecting uh boom belts
so um that's uh it
um so I I see what uh the Society of
mine is a complex system uh of
collective theorizers
and I'm gonna try going further with
this project to answer the question if
uh Collective of theorizers can
self-organize to actively sustain itself
so thank you uh to the active reference
Institute for inviting me to present and
for providing a home for this project
and for the constant support and
encouragement
I'll see you later on Discord thank you
awesome thank you JF just to conclude
the session I'll I'll read two questions
and let's maybe address them in an
upcoming Robotics and embodied meeting
so if you're excited about this project
certainly we all are and about symbolic
active inference join the Discord and
participate in the Robotics and embody
it but I'll drop these two questions
from David Williams in the chat who
wrote One how important is conducting
this work in Real World versus
simulation and two what tools or
components are missing in the robotics
toolkit to make this research easier and
better I know those are things you have
a lot of thoughts on so I'll look
forward to uh discussing with you more
thank you JF
thank you peace
all right
see you
and it's a great
Segway from
Collective behavior in Surprise
minimizing agents two Collective
behavior in Surprise minimizing agents I
guess welcome Connor
hey sorry I just turned on my audio so I
just heard the last thing you said yeah
okay both can hear you yes thanks
um
we're looking forward to your
presentation multi-agents active
inference and multi-scale Alignment
current developments and challenges so
feel free to share your screen or
proceed however you prefer
great thanks and before I start can I
just um because I've had issues with my
my voice like saturating like my
microphone saturating how's my audio is
it clipping at all or does this sound
okay this this is good and I'm watching
it
okay perfect thank you
um I will share my screen
I'm going to share this one and then the
one thing I'll note oh yes okay it's
just JF symbolic implementation does not
use statistical distributions it uses
the
um symbolic and The Logical inference
and now we're gonna move back into the
distributional space and it'll be
awesome to see similarities and
differences so thank you Connor to you
for the presentation
and thank you um Daniel for the
introduction and for inviting me as well
as big thank you to the other organizers
of the third applied active reference
Symposium
um yeah I'm really happy to be here to
present so my name is Connor Hines I'm a
PhD student at Don much Park Institute
of animal behavior and I'm also a
researcher at the versus AI research lab
rmd Lab
um so I'm gonna do something a little
bit I guess unconventional for
people in my position like I'm a junior
researcher coming to the end of my PhD
so usually when I give a talk I would
present on my own research
um like what I've been up to for the
last 10 years working on but instead of
that I'm actually going to talk about
given the motivation of the Symposium
I'm going to talk about something that's
more of an overview or perspective on
the current state of the field in
multi-scale active inference or
multi-agent active inference
and what in my opinion we need to do to
move forward as a field I think that's
very um resonant with the kind of
motivations and the title indeed of this
Symposium so I'm going to give a general
analysis of what multi-scale activations
is why it's import important I'm going
to provide a brief analysis of its
formal basis as it currently stands and
then what we need to develop in this
kind of sub-discipline of active
inference multi-scale active inference
to really make it rigorous and really to
actually reap the benefits of what it
promises
um so generally active inference has
been used a lot to design agents that
can solve problems plan and just
generally emulate behavior that we deem
intelligent which includes things like
Risk sensory decision making intrinsic
motivations to resolve uncertainty and
finally from a more scientific
standpoint the ability to firm a process
theory about how biological brains
actually might work
um but in a lot of the theoretical work
on active inference from the last 10
years is or 10 plus years really there's
also alongside all the kind of practical
building adaptive agents there's a claim
that active inference is inherently or
intrinsically multi-scale
from the very get-go it is a multi-scale
framework it's not just about building
single agents
um so it's really whenever we write down
a single active inference agent what
we're implicitly implying is also a
nested hierarchy of active inference
agents both below and above so
colloquially you'll often see this in
papers as the idea that there's Markov
blankets all the way down markup blanket
is a statistical structure that's very
kind of
um intrinsic the definition of Agents as
they are defined in under active
inference so I'm not going to get into
defining that I'm kind of assuming that
there's a more disciplinary audience
there but I'm sure other touch feelings
Symposium can provide better Clarity so
yeah Mark Hawk blankets active in
difference all the way down all the way
up
and at any given scale crochet the free
energy minimizing Dynamics or the active
inference Dynamics are kind of claimed
to be aligned with or parallel to the
free energy minimizing gradients at the
level below and above so what what the
claim is that as agents are doing their
thing and doing active Infamous at one
level it both entails and is constrained
by active inference processes of the
macro agent that they're participating
in so I'm a cell that's part of a tissue
as well as the microagents that comprise
them I am a free energy minimizing
cellular agent comprised of organelles
that are also minimizing free energy
so this this kind of constrained neat um
nested gradient descent on free energy
is part of the story of multi-scale
active inference and it also crucially
assumes that these Dynamics are aligned
correlated Cooperative across these
different scales so I should mention
that there is a formal argument made
more recently I would say in the last
five years about how this is possible
and it relies on an apparatus from
statistical physics called the
regionalization group this basically
allows you to analytically identify
shared symmetries energy and
conservation laws at different scales in
a given system that's comprised of
subsystems and subsystems so on at
infernium so there's a formal argument
specifically made in the a free energy
principle for a particular physics
monograph from 2019 that applies the
renormalization group apparatus to
multivariates stochastic differential
equations that are kind of the
equivalent point of Ages so you can
apply that that framework to certain
sorts of coupled stochastic differential
equations that exhibit Markov blanketage
Swatch coupling structure and you can
kind of prove analytically that there
are going to be nested systems of Markov
blankets and that they're all of some
sense of minimizing three energies at
their own scales so I'll get more into
that argument later but I just want to
mention that as I Define multi-scale
active inference that
um that there is a formal argument that
that's related to it
so this slide I just put together to
demonstrate the idea of nested free
energy minimizing processes visually so
at a given scale we can think of an
agent as occupying some point in its
free energy landscape indicated by this
Red Orb
um which represents say its
configuration its beliefs and its
actions and it performs active inference
and in doing so minimizes its free
energy so it changes the position of
that ball on that landscape and that is
all we mean when we say active inference
that that corresponds to the agent doing
inferencing doing action and kind of
getting to the fixed point of its local
free energy landscape
the multi-agent case is simply when we
add more of these processes so there's
other agents usually assumed to be
similar agents and the word similarity
let's put the asterisks on that and
they're all sitting at different ports
in their own free energy Landscapes
they're all the the position of their
local Red Ball is maybe in a different
place
so the claim of multi-scale active
influence is that as we link these
multiple active inference agents
together so they can actually exchange
information like observations and
actions with each other what we
automatically get is some kind of super
agent that is also minimizing variation
of free energy and is in some sense an
emergent or supervenient active
inference agent and I say the word we
automatically get a super agent with an
asterisk because there may be some
conditions on that mapping from local to
Global that have to be elucidated
um so we'll come back to that in a bit
but in short I think the the definition
of multi-scale active entrance is very
eloquently put in this paper by
um Raphael uh Kaufman pranav Gupta and
Jacob Taylor I think Rafael Kaufman is
actually going to be on the panel later
um and this line from their paper is a
really nice uh I think just summary of
what it is
so I'll just redo that right the upshot
is that in theory any active inference
agent at one spatio temporal scale could
be simultaneously composed of nested
active inference agents at the scale
below and constituent of a larger active
infantation at the scale above it in
effect active inference allows you to
pick a composite system or agent a that
you want to understand and it will be
generally true that both that that agent
a is an approximate Global minimizer of
free energy at the scale at which that
agent reliably persists and that agent a
is composed of subsystems a sub I that
are approximate local minimizers with
free energy so that is the claim as I'm
going to like continue continue
evaluating in this talk and I think it's
just a great reference point to make
so okay that that that's what
multi-scale active inference is why is
it important why do we actually care
about that that sounds philosophically
nice and beautiful visually but why is
that important so there's a ton of
actually really important implications
of this both for the engineering and the
Natural Sciences
um first of all the namesake of the
Symposium I assume inspired by this
recent paper by Carl ferson at all about
enacting ecosystems of
you know parenthetically shared
intelligence so this is the third
applied active Symposium so to to really
make this resonate with the applied
aspect let's make this very concrete if
we can figure out this multi-scale
endeavor then we can actually engineer
distributed systems of multi-aging
intelligence where local agents and
doing their own little local active
inference processes are also
cooperatively instantiating a global
agent that's also performing active
interest this has huge computational
potential of course compared to kind of
the state of VR predominant methods for
artificial intelligence which are deep
learning which really is about
propagating Global Information through
an entire computation graph so although
you could argue back propagation is
local in some sense it's really not
local in the way that multi-scale active
inference promises to be local so if we
can figure out how to actually engineer
multi-scale active inference it will
have really tremendous implications for
the study of artificial intelligence
just from that pure engineering
standpoint
it'll be cheaper in one where it will be
computationally energetically Memory
wise cheaper a lot cheaper
um secondly
from a kind of more Natural Sciences
motivation which is kind of where I'm
coming from I get a piece I'm doing a
PhD in biology so I'm interested in
questions about actual real systems in
nature just the idea of being able to
get super specific and rigorous about
phrases like emergence intelligence
emergent computation collective
intelligence super organism that's often
thrown around we're talking about social
insects right these are terms that you
hear thrown around in many different
scientific disciplines that deal with
multi-agent systems um Network systems
but none of these terms to my knowledge
have really rigorous or precise
conditions multi-scale active inference
is a kind of framework that's in the
position to provide those rigorous
definitions and conditions so from a
scientific standpoint it could really
lend a lot of potential and usefulness
for other scientific disciplines and
finally another pragmatic motivation
there's loads of fields that are
obsessed with designing and Engineering
Systems where local selfish individual
Behavior can lead
when networks appropriately to some
desired Collective outcome and these
disciplines you really want to figure
out how to engineer that properly so
this goes from the design of financial
markets and trading systems all the way
down to how do you design a multiplayer
video game
so that that's kind of just motivating
why is multi-scale active inference even
interesting
so then the question of course becomes
is the multi-scale active influence
clean actually true are all multi-agent
active influence systems comprised of
and themselves comprise nested hierarchy
of free energy minimizing agents a
glance at a smattering of other
scientific disciplines that specifically
deal with multiple agents multiple
interests Collective phenomena like
coordination group Behavior collective
intelligence
I'll go answer all those disciplines
would naively suggest that the answer is
no so there's things like frustration in
thermodynamic systems Game Theory the
very existence of zero-sum games and
Nash equilibrium bandwagon effects when
we're talking about social networks and
and um opinion Dynamics
um sacrifices for the common good which
we see in different contexts in biology
like in the context of kin selection but
also in the context of arguably cell
cell death in a tissue
um these are all basically plenty of
systems where local constraints and
Global constraints or desires or free
energy gradients whatever you want to
call them coming to direct conflict so
the obvious example that I I have listed
at the top of these on bullets is the
idea of geometrics frustration that we
see in ising systems with very low
temperature so these izing models
basically describe lattices of
ferromagnets that are happy when they're
pointing in the same direction as their
neighboring Fair amendments and they can
be in an up or down state so basically
the magnet can be pointing up or
pointing down and these Global Systems
are defined by a global energy function
and the whole system is in some sense
trying to minimize that Global energy
function but sometimes you'll find cases
in these Collective systems where this
little spangle in the middle cannot be
happy because they're getting
conflicting information from two
neighbors I want to be pointing up in
blue like the agent on the left but I
also want to be pointing down like the
Asia on the right so this is a system
that's collectively finding some fixed
point of its Global free energy but it's
actually leading to a local conflict
where this agent is not at a point where
it can do anything to make itself happy
or minimize its free energy further so
just from even the basic glance at a
fair magnetic lattices we already see
instances where local and Global
gradients or local and Global Optima are
not aligned in the right way
so given all this the burden of proof
for multi-scale active infantry skill on
us so we need to show that Collective
active income systems generically do
align again across scales and maybe if
we can put an X across the word
generically and it's not some automatic
condition if they don't then at least we
have to establish exactly the conditions
in which they do
so anecdotally we do actually have some
conditions
there's some seem to be some kind of
basic ingredients to get Collective
Collective active inference to work so
one is that we basically need agents to
exchange actions and Sensations across
some kind of Markov blanket this is not
really a conditioning this is almost
more part of what it means to be an
agent so having more comfortable and get
separation between agents is just
another way of saying we have multiple
agents in our system rather than a
single agent if you're violated a Markov
blanket property so internal states of
One agent are not allowed to see the
internal States or external states of
another agent then you're kind of
cheating because you're kind of saying
it's actually One agent and what you're
doing is information sharing within the
brain of the similar region the second
condition which is something that's
often hallucinated more anecdotally and
not really formally is this idea that
agents need to have some kind of shared
narrative or shared hidden States or
censor space in their generative model
so I've worked a lot on Collective
active inference systems just simulating
agents and trying to get them to do
interesting things together and my
intuitions and experience do agree with
this basic fact if the agents don't have
any similarity in what they're
representing or trying to achieve then
it's kind of like trying to fit a square
peg into a circular hole so this is
really nicely elucidated in the one the
earliest cases in this paper a duet for
one by first and first from 2015 where
they show that for two agents to really
align they kind of have to have a shared
generative model and then you can get
kind of this nice synchronized Behavior
again though these things like what does
similarity mean what does a shared
narrative actually made formally
mathematically those things have not
been initiated yet so right now a lot of
the building of these Collective systems
is based on our intuitions and kind of
engineering things in using some vague
guidelines like oh they should have a
shared sensor space but there's no
mathematical conditions or guarantees
about what degree of similarity is
needed between two agents models to get
the intended Dynamics
and finally we have to have at least
some agreement between the generative
model of each agent and the generative
process which is really the behavior of
the other agents generating their data
so this is kind of related to the the
previous point about having shared
generated models but just to be very
specific
the physics of the space that transfers
your actions to my observations that
physics can't be dramatically crazily
different than how our generative models
represent those physics so if we took
two fish with the same generative model
of each other and they normally would
school together in a fish tank but we
throw them in a volcano or shoot them
out into outer space they won't school
together because then the generative
process is so dramatically deviating
from the way they're representing that
physics the the way they're generated
model is constructed so these are again
just ingredients kind of guidelines or
anecdotes but there's nothing really
rigorous Behind These conditions they're
more like a list of best practices
so now let's get on to actual rigorous
stuff so the first real rigorous attempt
to show that multi-scale active
inference generally works is in one
section of this free energy principle
for a particular physics monograph from
2019 so it leverages this apparatus I
mentioned earlier the renormalization
group operator to basically show how one
can successively course screen
multi-variate stochastic differential
equations that admit sparse coupling
between their state variables so the
main result in my mind that connects
these remobilization group results to
multi-scale acts of inference is the
fact that the lagrangian of the system
at one scale can be expressed as a
function of the lagrangian at other
scales and that applies in a scale
invariant fashion that is the main like
uh kind of output or the main benefit of
using a renalization group apparatus so
you can kind of think of LaGrange like
the generative model it's a it's a
physics term but it's related to the
generative model of the agents that
comprise the system and therefore also
their free energy so in terms of active
inference it means that this reasoning
of the renormalization group can be used
to smoothly move between the models of
individual agents at one scale and the
model of a collective or larger agent at
a different scale or a smaller scale for
that matter and the nice thing about it
is general for all kinds of Dynamics and
thus generic models it doesn't depend
heavily on the form of the stochastic
differential equations that form your
system
um the issues with it is that there's
not a Global Link to basic mechanics and
active inference it's still all done in
the traditional physics formalism so we
don't actually have an explicit link to
local inference and Global inference
although if you know the connection
between the lagrangian and the
generative model and the free energy
then you can make that connection but
it's not actually made explicitly for us
in this part of the monograph it also
requires the assumption that the
generative model and the generative
process are identical at the local level
that's where we need to have lagrangian
is defined that's also a restrictive
assumption that's probably not realistic
in my opinion and then finally there's
something about uh kind of spatio
temporal segregation of scales so we
need to make assumptions about how fast
random fluctuations are at one scale
relative to another scale in order to
justify kind of core streaming or
forgetting about certain States As you
move between scales and that's also
something that you could argue current
Research into Collective Dynamics
challenges that assumption about how how
fast noise is at one scale relatively to
the max
so now I'm going to discuss quickly
another small contingent of active
inference research that is attempted to
address this mapping between local and
Global Insurance processes so what I
want to kind of just generally say with
this presentation and to our community
is that the kind of approach taken in
these two papers first of all active
inference model of collective
intelligence and speaker glass systems
there's Collective active influence this
is one of the types of research I think
we really need to move active inference
multi-scale active inference forward so
I'm not trying to be too biased because
I am the first author on the second of
those papers but I'll also be the first
one to point out the limitation but
benefits wise I think these approaches
are really important because they
formally relate a local generative model
at one scale to a global generative
model at a different scale so really Ty
how did the parameters of one model
relate to a course grade model and these
are really good um steps in the
direction of a formal theory of
collective intelligence that goes from
local intelligences to Global
intelligence
however there's still issues with these
one of them is that they only deal with
the issue with inference at the global
level not active inference so these both
these papers concerned with a bunch of
local active inference agents that
cooperate to form a global inference
agent like a passive-basing agent rather
than an active inflation and it's also
unclear whether the system studying
newspapers are actually very generic
like the results are generic to study
collective intelligence in general or
their nice formal arguments but they're
only applicable to these specific
systems so we still don't have something
that's even more kind of zoomed out and
Abstract than these which tend to be a
little bit of case specific and finally
the actual
um scale Transcendence that we're doing
in these papers is still relegated to
really one step we're not doing the full
multi-scale infinite scale regression
that's something like renalization group
promises
so that's kind of the current overview
of what I think are the most promising
directions in multi-scale active infants
and I'm aware on time sorry five minutes
so I'm going to quickly try to go
through what I think are really
promising directions to push in terms of
multi-scale active infants and kind of
intuition products that I think will
help us
study these systems in a way that's
different and also actually better
informed by other research disciplines
so the the general idea that I'd like to
put forward is that misaligned gradients
can actually be a good thing so it's
actually sometimes good when local free
energy gradients are misaligned with
global grains so sometimes the global
system will actually do better if the
local systems are performing worse so
this is something you could call
multi-scale conflict with a free energy
minimizing process at one scale are
actually doing bad quote unquote but
it's because they're being driven by
some higher scale process that is doing
well so rather than trying to always
avoid constructing processes like this I
think this kind of frustration to use
the analogy from statistical physics can
actually be an inspiration for what we
should investigate further because it
actually might be key to facilitating
optimality at different scales
um the reason I put this forward is
because there's loads of research just
Recent research in the last several
years that are suggesting that actually
making local agents more frustrated or
more unhappy might coincidentally or not
coincidentally lead to better Collective
or Global outcomes so this is expressing
various forms in various bodies of work
but one of the biggest patterns I've
noticed is the study of collective
Behavioral Systems over the last several
decades is the idea that local noise and
local dysregulation can often facilitate
Global coherence or the global
coordination and where multi-scale
active inference has something to say in
my opinion is in framing this benefit of
local frustration in terms of a
misalignment of free energy gradients so
maybe that actually temporary
misaligning local free energy energy
gradients from Global ones may
facilitate the dissent to fixed points
in the global free energy landscape that
satisfy everyone at all scales so I'm
basically expressing an idea that's been
known in various communities like
stochastic optimization and stochastic
resonance theory for decades but I think
we as active influence practitioners
have a new and potentially useful
perspective to shed on that using the
language of active inference and free
energy and minimization and Bayesian
inference in general so instead of
thinking of accelerating optimization by
just adding noise to the system we can
think of exactly how to design local
generative models such that there's an
optimal misalignment of local and Global
gradients or local and Global generative
models in a way that facilitates
everyone in the long run actually
facilitating or minimizing your free
energy
um so yeah that's just kind of like a
something I'm putting out there I'm
investing in it now in my own work but I
have no real results on that but I just
want to put that out there in this venue
because I think it maybe will inspire
other people to think in a similar way
so just to conclude now multi-scale
active inference I would say is still
largely based in theoretical or
philosophical descriptions and
illustrative simulations but we're still
lacking a formal Theory
um there's some theory in terms of the
renormalization group arguments of the
monograph but they're still in my
opinion a bit underdeveloped a little
under demonstrated and relying some
restrictive restrictive assumptions like
the fast and slow fluctuations the
identity between generative monogenic
process
there's a few more recent papers those
two by um Kaufman at all and then by
myself on spin glass
um systems that have attempted
particular proofs of multi-scale
Bayesian infant systems in particular
situations but their generality is still
not known and not proven so we why I'm
kind of trying to conclude with is by
saying we need to incorporate findings
from other disciplines related to the
role of noise conflict and frustration
in facilitating not subverting
collective intelligence or Collective
coordination and I think we can really
benefit by looking at these other
disciplines to help us build a really
powerful formal creative multi-scale
active inference and finally I think we
need to set the goal post for what
counts as a formal proof of multi-scale
active inference and once we get there
once we say okay this council's proof
this is satisfying how could we use that
to actually do the the hardest part in
my opinion which is engineering actual
multi-scale active inference systems
that are intelligent and minimizing free
energy at multiple scales
um yeah so with that I'm going to
conclude it looks like I'm just on time
so yeah thank you again for the
invitation to present and I'd like to
thank a bunch of people who are listed
here and Beyond who have influenced my
thinking and kind of my opinions
um yeah if there's time to take any
questions of course
awesome great
talk I'll just give a few seconds if
anybody wants to type in a question also
it's really cool like aswin in the
previous session was highlighting pi mdp
and just the way in which
we enact the collective intelligence
different people seeing a paper where an
analytical formalization is introduced
and then there's still so much work to
get it to the package and then so much
more work to take it to the Last Mile
and I think your presentation really
checked a lot of those boxes
um I'll just read a question and then um
that will just be an appetizer for our
continued discussion so Marco Lynn asked
do you expect the inferentially
connected Dynamics to exhibit Behavior
akin to theories of multi-body systems
and to what extent can we transfer
insights from that multi-body of work
and then second question just
for our thinking and learning from Marco
have you explored integrating work with
uh integrating work on self-organized
criticality with multi-scale active
inference or other Frameworks who can
provide more flexible Frameworks or
assumptions for a generic notion of
multi-scale Dynamics great questions
I hope that we can continue
um have you back anytime or just
continue to collaborate in the ecosystem
so thank you for the Epic talk Connor
and good luck finishing your PhD thanks
a lot Daniel yeah I'll talk to you soon
talk to you soon
so thank you for that
all right
greetings all right well our next
session hey hey Bert greetings
great how are you doing good good very
well
um our next session is with Bert device
Dimitri bagayev and Bart van Erp it's
going to be called towards user-friendly
design of synthetic active inference
agents and I know a lot of people are
super excited to see this really
practical and Cutting Edge work so to
you Bert and just let us know how we can
support
okay great uh well is my audio good yep
sounds good okay then I'm gonna share my
screen uh
I hope I picked the right one I don't
work it's Zoom quite often looks good it
looks good yep all right super
um well thanks a lot Daniel for for
hosting this uh simple stream I've been
watching some talks it's really amazing
and uh we really we feel privileged to
get the chance to present ourselves so
we also just like a few others before is
interested in developing a toolbox for
active inference
and so this picture or she kind of shows
what we're
um what we're about or what we're
interested in so here's a lady on the
left hand side and
um I'm gonna
try to get a laser pointer and she has
this idea about a rewarding behavior for
a vacuum cleaning robot right so she's
writing down she has a textual
expression move around the apartment
apply suction until the floor is clean
do not touch objects and when don't
return to the dog so that that's not so
hard I'm gonna rate that with one star
out of three stars in terms of difficult
difficulty level to specify that
um but that's not enough to program
these robots right because what she
really needs to do now is to specify a
generative model and uh that you know
the there's effectors and actuators
right the robot has to move around to
apply suction uh until the floor is
clean so the sensors probably a camera
uh do not touch objects so maybe there
has to be object recognition this is a
really difficult task to come up with
this generative model here and on top of
that
she has to specify this kind of
rewarding behavior in terms now of
probability distributions of this
generative model so very difficult I'm
going to rate that with two stars
because
the next thing she has to do for this
model is to specify the inference
procedure to do actually active
inference and freelance minimization in
real time
or this complex model and really that's
almost impossible right only a few
Specialists can really write a procedure
for for variational free energy
minimization in some very difficult
model so what we are about what we've
been working on is to try to automate
the inference task so get rid of the
three stars and yes she will still have
to specify her model but in the long
term we try to get away from that so in
the long term we hope we will get a
toolbox and now we're talking five ten
years right
um where a textual description would be
enough to specify some initial model
with an initial prior and everything
else is just automated inference
learning of States parameters
structural adaptation of the model even
maybe based on her feedback updating uh
the the prior so that's long term for
now we would be very happy if we could
just automate the inference task
so
um why why is it so difficult to specify
inference for an active inference agents
well we have so many competing
kpis right we we uh we want to do this
for large model Scopes not just for ABCD
models but maybe there's also a
continuous variables and
our electrical models right it must be
very user friendly you really don't want
her to worry about robustness of her
code
um we don't want her to worry about
whether
um two variables are have conjugated
relationships right
um adaptivity we want to update States
parameters maybe even the model the
model structure has to be low power
because these angels often run on edge
devices all right so they run on their
battery powered has to be in real time
because you can't learn how to ride a
bike if if there's no real-time
reasoning and on top of that you
actually want to minimize variation of
reality right you want to do it at least
as good or at least in a neighborhood of
if people do a manual derivation and
some of these the ciderata bite each
other right if you uh you want to
minimize variation free energy but you
have to do it in real time and on low
power yeah that kind of bites each other
right so these are
difficult kpis that we we want to yeah
we are we they're all important you
can't just take one out
um because then the whole system
wouldn't work
um so
um when you read papers on active
inference you often also read and now we
Implement variations of range
minimization and that can be done
by message passing on a graph and I want
to clarify first why it has to be done
by message passing on the graph
um I'll do that by giving a very short
answer
and then do an example the short answer
is that Bayesian inference involves
um Computing very large sum of products
like what you see here on the left hand
side here's a product AC
adbc and then we send them in AC plus 80
and so forth this is a sum of products
now we know by the distributive law that
this here on the left hand side can also
be computed as on the right hand side If
I multiply this out I get a times C plus
a times D and so forth this is a product
of sums and there exactly the same thing
the only difference is that to compute
the left hand side takes four additions
sorry four multiplications and three
additions to compute the right hand side
takes two additions and one only one
multiplication so on the right hand side
is much cheaper to compute in the left
hand side normally when we write down
marginalization and Beijing inference we
we write things down in the as in the
left hand side what message passing does
on a graph it will automatically convert
that into much cheaper to evaluate
product of sums and I'll give an example
of that
um
so here is an uh an example Model F of
seven variables X1 X2 through X7 and
this model happens to be factorized F A
of X1 fbx2 and so forth now we can draw
this factorization in a as a graph
and what we do and this is called a
Forney style Factor graph what we do is
for each factor F A we allocate a node
so FB gets a note and FC gets a note and
we associate the variables in our system
with the edge and an edge is connected
to a node if that variable is an
argument of that function so FC is a
function of F of X1 X2 X 3 and that
means that FC connects to the edges X1
X2 X3 and FD is only a function of X4 so
if D only connects to the edge X4 so
what you can see in this graph is this
graph is nothing but
a visualization of the factorization
assumptions that we have for this model
now if I'm interested in a big
marginalization a task integrate out
overall variables but X3 so X One X2 X4
and so forth through X7 I'm interested
in this
um then
making taking advantage of this
factorization I can rewrite this sum
this basically this sum of product into
a product of sums as as below here what
you will see here below this computes
exactly the same thing but I've made use
of this distributive law for instance
FC contains no X4 no X5 so I moved it
over the summation sign to the left and
FB also doesn't contain X4 X5 x67 so I
moved it all the way to the left
and when you do that you are left here
with an expression
where I only some some over two two
variables and here I have to sum over
six variables and here over two and here
over two so you can imagine if each
variable would say so X1 X2 if each
variable has 10 interesting values that
you need to sum over
then I have here
the original marginalization problem I
have 10 to the power 6 so a million
terms and here
in red I have 100 terms and here I have
100 and here I have 100 so here I have
300 terms and here I have 1 million
terms so is it it's an enormous
reduction in computational
complexity
when we make use of this distributive
law now it turns out that if you write
this out you can associate these these
intermediate factors with messages on
the graph it's just an interpretation a
visual interpretation it's as if
FC
receives a message from fa and FB
receive or FC receives a message from X
from FB and computes an outgoing message
mu X3 and the same thing for Fe so Fe
receives a message from a neighboring
factors FD and FF and computes an
outgoing message
or X3 so what you see here is that the
entire marginalization process can be
represented as basically Computing a few
messages on a graph
and multiplying some of these messages
with each other and and and and that's
how you can do Beijing inference and
also how you can do variational free
energy minimization so this works in
um in factorized models but I would say
even stronger if your model is not
factorized and you have a lot of
variables uh there is just no way you
can do proper inference so any serious
model is factorized like the brain is
almost sparse is is almost empty we have
well is it about 10 billion neurons and
each neuron connects to a few thousand
other neurons so if I would draw the
graph that graph is almost empty it is
hugely sparse and so there is no other
way to do inference in the brain than by
message passing
um so that's why message passing just
because it's more effective than
anything else
now then the issue is which message do
you compute how do you compute messages
um because there are different ways of
doing it right and we also read in
active inference papers you can do this
by variational message passing or
expectation maximization or belief
propagation and
variational LaPlace and all these terms
it turns out that there is a an umbrella
framework for all these message passing
Frameworks and that umbrella framework
is called constraint better
free energy minimization and I try I
will try to
illustrate that by uh well by this slide
so here I have this graph this is just
an example graph
where my generative model is basically
factorized in f a f b f c of d and f e
and I've also written that here so this
now is the variation of free energy
now I haven't made any assumption on Q
of X so Q of X is still Q of X1 X2 X3 is
just a joint overall variables and it
doesn't have any factorization
assumption
it makes sense to also assume that the
posterior kind of follows the
factorization Assumption of the prior
namely of the generative model so
if we make that assumption
and that means we're going to make the
assumption that Q X is also now a
product of qas
of X of a where qas of X of a stands for
beliefs over notes what I mean by that
is that Q of B is a is a posterior
belief over this node meaning it's a
posterior belief over the edges that
connect to this nodes just like FB is a
function of X1 X2 X
4 that's if you will the prior or the
generative model then Q of B the
variational posterior for this node will
also depend on X1 X2 X4 and on no other
factors if you just do that then you
will count some of the variables double
because X1 is part of the belief over F
A but also part of the belief over FB so
we just have to Discount that by
dividing by beliefs over edges that
means that I make now an assumption
that my posterior believes is
is is divided into local beliefs over
notes and local beliefs over edges over
variables
this will make things a lot simpler in
fact if my graph is a tree and it is a
tree here and I would do message passing
on that tree and I could suppose I could
do that perfectly everything is linear
gaussian then I get perfect Bayesian
inference there is no approximation so
this is a good assumption
sometimes it's still very hard to
compute a message because
even the the the the the single message
that come out of these nodes the still
integrals or summations and in
particular the integrals may be a
problem we may not have an analytical
answer so what we sometimes do is add
additional
um assumptions we'll say well the
posterior belief over FD I can't compute
it in general but
but I'm gonna just assume now that it's
a Garrison that makes it easier or we
can make an extra factorization
assumption
and say the posterior belief over FB
which is really I believe over the joint
X1 X2 X4 is going to be broken into
uh um independent belief over X1 and in
the belief over
um X2 and X4
um
these additional assumptions if I impose
them as well this is what I recall now
if I if I if I all substituted here in Q
of X I get what's called a constrained
beta-free energy this is the same death
as in the Oppenheimer movie this is Hans
Bethel where it's named after and
um so
we have a graph now
that that is highly factorized and we
have
local beliefs over notes and over
um over edges and they're indicated with
with red and we have additional
constraints in green there could be
gaussians or I mean field constraints or
other constraints and now we will assume
constraint that make it possible to
compute all the messages and now we can
just automate this by making different
assumptions we can turn this into
expectation maximization or belief
propagation or
um hybrid forms thereof we can turn it
into any relevant message passing
algorithm that you've heard of so this
is a very nice umbrella framework that
basically encompasses everything and and
there is a we've written a pretty large
paper
on this
um in entropy Journal where you can read
all the math on how this works
so we've talked about why message
passing namely because it's the most
effective way of doing it inference and
we've talked about which messages to
compute namely
we turn our
variational free energy into something
called a constrained better free energy
and then we can compute messages the
only thing that's left is well when do
we pass these messages right what is the
sequence of messages which one comes
first
and
um this is where we see a lot of papers
right
um
you have the right control flow what's
called control flow you have to say okay
here is my algorithm for active
inference first I specify a model then
let's do inference for every time step
collect a new observation update the
state update the desired future
right and so forth compute expected free
energy select the policy Etc
um this kind of program the problem with
active inferences is that there is
nested for Loops in here here's a for
Loop and here's another for Loop and for
each of these policies I'm going to have
to go into uh the future so I'm going to
have another time Loop so it is for
Loops in four Loops in for Loops this
will completely explode in terms of
computational
complexity so as a result uh some very
clever people have written very clever
algorithms of doing this much faster
sophisticated inference branching time
active influence dynamic programming efe
I recent proposals for doing this very
clever
in the end all of these proposals come
down to a particular just a message
passing schedule
um once we commit to message passing on
the graph as our inference procedure
it's the only thing that's going on and
all of this
or sophisticated inference and granting
time active inference all it does is it
schedules the messages it says first
this message then this message then this
message I don't mean that as a slide to
these algorithms they're very clever and
as we've seen in the presentation by
asvine Paul you get huge improvements if
you go from regular inference to
sophisticated inference but it's good to
realize that
these algorithms just specify in the
graph which message comes after which
message
um so here's an example
here's an example of a graph and a
message
um
sequence here's a message one then
message H2 and message three goes up and
then we go from FC to f f and here's
message five and then we go to Fe and
this could correspond the sequence to
Dynamic time programming efe or
sophisticated inference
um there are a couple of problems with
this approach which we could basically
with with having the user to specify a
clever algorithm first of all
you have to be a specialist to do it
right only these are very clever people
so so that means that um if we let it
leave it to
um let's say to an engineer in a company
it's it's well it's the higher
probability is not going to get it right
that's very unfortunate
um but there is another issue and that
is that in it in a sense it's a global
variable
um in the message passing schedule all
nodes are visited because if a node
would not be visited then we shouldn't
have it in the graph and that means if
one note crashes basically the message
passing schedule is invalid I have to
reset my system
and if you fly a drone if it's deployed
and it's out in the field and a node
crashes a transistor burns out and I
have to totally reset now my system I
have to compute a new message passing
schedule
um then you're not doing inference and
you know and your drone flies into the
wall
so this is not robust and it also for
very this the same reason we may
actually want to take out a node we may
want to prune you know we might want to
do structural adaptation and
we can't do structural adaptation
because we have to reset the system
recompute a message passing schedule so
this procedural style where an engineer
app purely specifies which message comes
after this message has some
disadvantages it's not very robust and
it's uh if you want to do it very clever
you have to be really a specialist so a
better system is what we call a reactive
message passing
and it's very related to what was in the
first session uh called the the actor
model Keith Duggar had a nice
presentation on the actor model
so what we will do is we will say we
will not have a global message passing
schedule the engineer will not space
specify anything anymore the inference
code that an engineer will have to write
is just say react to any free energy
minimization opportunity in other words
there is no inference code it's
completely automated and
um we will replace This Global message
passing schedule by local triggering
inside the node so each node is now just
an autonomous autonomous system that's
interested in minimizing its free energy
it can do so by sending out messages and
when will it do so well it receives
messages I mean it feels when it looks
at these messages and it feels like oh
there is an opportunity for me to
minimize free energy
buy or expect the frequency by sending
out the message then will send out a
message and each node will do so by
itself asynchronously so you get
parallel distributed processing or
concurrent processing as Keys call it
um in principle you could play this game
on many computers at the same time
and so you get tremendous advantages
first of all you don't have to write
difficult code second of all you can do
multi-threading or you can you can run
it on multiple computers at the same
time
and so do and there's also
um robustness
um
um uh advantages because even though it
crashes then there's nothing that stops
the system from just finding another
path right if if this node crashes this
path from here's message three this path
Now doesn't work so I cannot send
anything to Fe anymore from uh no from X
well then I just sent a new message here
why not it's like when water
falls down a mountain and it zigzags its
way down into the value and you have
where you put up an obstruction it just
finds another path
um not the preferred path this has to
find well the the second the second best
path because the first path has been
obstructed right and that's good that's
what's going to happen in this system as
well right that's just how nature works
it tries to find the best path the
easiest path and if that's not available
then we do the second best pass and
that's also what you can do with
reactive message passing so you can
throw notes you can do structural
adaptation
um and it's far more robust and you can
also get uh let's do a chance encounters
with other drones right drones that get
close can start communicating with each
other and when they are far away they
stop communicating with each other and
this is no problem because she can
basically change
who changed
um
notes can change on the Fly who they
communicate to and who they want to
listen to and uh so that's that's the
way data works and also how it works
when we do a reactive programming and
react with message passing so in summary
we're interested in automating inference
in um
active influence agents right because
it's an operation that's basically only
for for experts and this
active influence technology is not going
to be successful unless we get more
people uh let's democratize it and we
get competent Engineers being able to
develop good agents right you shouldn't
have to be a top specialist in the world
to go to develop an active inference
agent now in order to automate
inference you must do message passing
and I've talked about that for
efficiency I've also talked about which
messages to pass
not necessarily do you have to follow
this framework but constrained better
free energy framework is very convenient
it's an umbrella framework that
basically
um
goes over
all the interesting other uh messages
passing computations when Nas is passing
a reactiveness is passing it's fully
automated so you don't have to write any
code anymore
in principle it's con it's you can do
parallel distributed processing it's
robust to structural changes you can
learn new inference Pathways so lots of
lots of advantages here
now
how do we do it
um I'd like to introduce a toolbox that
we've been working on uh called RX infer
and we do that with my lab here at the
University I'm here in Eindhoven in the
south of the Netherlands and we have a
lab the lab is called buy slab here are
postdocs and assisted professors and PhD
students and we've been working on this
for many years and some of these
okay like Albert and Ismail and dice
um have written dissertations
um and our best work we have
Consolidated that in a toolbox
and the toolbox is called RX infer and
you can if you want to have a look you
can go to the website action4.ml
and asking for
our confer Works uh in the way that I've
just discussed it does message passing
it tries to minimize constrained better
free energy that means it it can come up
with all kinds of message passing
algorithms
um it will do it in a reactive way and
it will try to do it in real time and
low power and all the kpis that we're
talking about now it's of course not
done but um it's functional and I'd like
to show some demos and I will
leave it to Dimitri and Bart who are two
Advanced PC students in my lab to show
the demos
so I'm gonna stop
sharing
awesome thank you great talk sure
uh can you hear me yeah yeah
okay I will try to share my screen okay
so you should see it now
looks good
okay so yeah hello uh to everyone uh I'm
uh Dimitri Vegas so I'm a PG student in
bioslap and I'm from University of
Technology uh and yes I have a small
presentation about the actual software
developments in bias lab and yeah so
over the past few years we have
significantly improved our tools and
basically my entire PhD was dedicated to
implement the this idea which bird was
talking about uh like implementing the
variational reactive message possible
and in this presentation I just want to
show you what you can actually do uh
using this Theory under the hood
okay so basically in order to automate
active inference right we need to
automate Bayesian inference and we have
uh we have already a lot of solutions
for that as such as Stan pyron numpyre
which is funded by Google internet is
funded by Microsoft Turing is in
Jewelery by MC and many many many so uh
and basically these Solutions are really
really good so uh and they're really
good at prototyping as well but our goal
is eventually to be able to deploy this
kind of systems not just prototype and
we are really focusing on this
particular properties for this ultimate
Vision inference uh so it must be low
power adaptive real-time scalable it
also must be user friendly at the end
and it must support a large scope of
models if you want it to be useful
so and in biaslab we want to build such
a software uh in such nice properties
and it's always about Traders right so
we do something better in one particular
domain and maybe other software
libraries they might be better in a
different domain so but we are really
focusing on this particular properties
uh and so yes I will reiterate a little
bit there's presentation so how do we
achieve this so we have imagine we have
an environment and we have an agent uh
and the agent log takes some actions and
the agent basically what he needs is to
come up with some sort of good enough
probabilistic model of its environment
in order to do patient inference
uh and in our framework we encode the
model as a factor graph which not only
models the observations but also actions
and desired future
uh and this this approach allows us to
decompose the these complex
relationships between variables and
hidden States into some kind of
structure and local blocks uh and it's
not a block it's not a black box anymore
so
um and the model itself may have some
sort of background motivation
interpretation it may encode your prior
knowledge about some particular physical
system
uh and the locality of these blocks
basically allows you to scale to
millions of variables and hidden States
it allows you to pre-optimize it maybe
or maybe use like some sort of different
approximation strategies in different
places
so it allows a lot of very nice
properties as well
and we use reactive message passing to
run uh actual variational version
inference it uses reactive programming
under the hood to minimize the
approximation to the variation of energy
and yes as berdos mentioned it's it's
very much related to actor model
and basically indirect transfer you can
think of different nodes as actors
themselves
uh so and they have basically one single
purpose is to send the variational
message that minimizes the energy
this is a very short and very high level
description but it is essentially what
is happening so we are not reaching
different agents which interact with
each other as actors but we also treat
the the actual components of the
underlying model as actors themselves
it's like a very hierarchical structure
so this is the main central idea of of
this inference
uh so here for example first example we
can do an inference in a dynamical
system and this example which is quite
old already I think it's like two years
ago so we we track a position of the
object given some noisy measurements
which are indicated by Green Dots uh the
actual uh real signal we cannot observe
it but we just can plot it uh it's shown
as blue and the invert signal is shown
as red and the data set is infinite the
inference engine just reacts on it and
does not assume any particular data size
simply reacts in your observation as
soon as possible
uh yeah I'm actually not sure how
smoothly Zoom shares my screen uh maybe
you can see it's a bit lagging in the
animations I'm not sure because maybe
Zoom does not share it on a full frame
rate
um and also on the right hand side you
can see how we Define models uh in our
framework we use Jeweler as a
programming language
and so basically this is everything that
you need to Define this particular model
and run inference on a data set and
actually I like really spend more days
to plot it instead of in France right so
inference was was an easy easiest part
from approaching was way much harder
relate to user friendliness
so and we actually have plans to improve
our model specification language make it
even easier so now for technical reasons
we have some auxiliary statements and
model specification language but we are
working to improve
that and make it even easier
uh
this is another example which is similar
to the previous one that uses much more
complex and linear dynamical system of
the double pendulum and the system is
chaotic and we can observe on this small
part of it a lot of noise also indicated
as a green dots
uh and nonetheless given
given good enough model uh you can infer
the other hidden states with pretty much
High precision and the code needed for
that is also relatively short uh and
yeah
we also have uh examples with active
inference agents that interact with
their environment
uh so the left uh
left up shows uh yeah Mountain curve
problem very famous problem the left
bottom side shows an active entrance
agent which tries to control the
inverted pendulum from falling in the
windy conditions it reacts and wind
we also have a demo of an agent that
controls a pendulum in an ever-changing
environment so on the right side you see
a pendulum with an engine and Legend has
engine has limited power
and the agent itself needs to reach the
goal and the goal is indicated as a red
circle so and
basically in this demo we can change the
environment in real time and see how the
agent reacts so you can change the mass
of the pendulum on its laying for the
amount of noise in the measurements or
we can change the goal we can change
maximum engine power Etc right so the
agent will still try to infer the best
possible course of actions in order to
reach its goal and it just never stops
reacting
um it's it's also actually possible to
restrict ancient power such that it will
not longer possible to reach the goal
right but the agent would still try
uh we have other cool demos with smart
navigation and collision avoidance uh
which are still under active research
and the code for them is not available
publicly it will be soon available but
for example in this example we can
define a set of Agents with their
boundaries and a set of their
destinations so and we can see how they
try to resolve their Roots all together
um and we can have some static obstacles
in the map we can see how agents can
find their most optimal path
in order to reach their goals and avoid
any possible Collision
and it's also not necessary to have
static obstacles uh the obstacles
themselves may move so in this demo we
have hundreds of agents that navigate
through a map of obstacles that move
from bottom to top to the circles or
obstacles and agents are depicted as
small dots and they need to go from left
to right basically avoid any sort of
pollution
uh and as I also mentioned we want to
perform efficient and real-time
inference but we also have to do it like
low power low performance uh on low
performance devices such as Raspberry Pi
or coolpy as an example and we have some
results of successful in running uh the
Bayesian audio Source separation for
example on cool Pi so it is actually
possible we also run active we try to
run active inference agents also on
coolpy so as the aforementioned in word
pendulum
and
as I mentioned we also need to have a
large model scope and basically RX infer
has not been designed to solve any of
the aforementioned problems specifically
we have a large set of different
examples in our repository uh different
models different data different
influence constraints
uh we have examples for linear
regressions hidden Markov Model Auto
risk model hierarch models mixture
models gaussian process and so on so
right so this approach is very versatile
and for example if you
um if you compare it with sort of a
conventional software libraries where
you let's say have a library that solves
a common filter might be a very great
Library maybe super fast have top
performance works great and very
reliable
uh super good but then you are
constrained by by this particular model
common filtering right and you can't
really change it much
we we are free to Define our own models
uh which we can pretty much easily
Define a model that essentially would
act equivalently to Common filtering
equation and so basically in the demo
that I showed before about object
tracking it was essentially a common
filter
that was written in a in a probabilistic
model
uh so yeah that was my small addition to
the best presentation so our software is
free so MIT license and it's open source
available on GitHub
uh yeah and we would be happy thanks to
be able to present where we would be
happy to answer any questions thanks
awesome
awesome all right I'll just ask a quick
question in the chat
Marco asks
sorry if I missed it are the collision
avoidance demos real time adapting to
other agents Behavior or is it a
collectively pre-computed path
um so basically they are not uh super
real time they're kind of fast to
compute this path like maybe five
seconds or so but it's very basically
working to make it real time so we know
what is the problem we know where to
improve and we will make it fill that
yes
almost almost like
next question do you have some
comparative data with other methods and
just more generally what kinds of
benchmarks or what when you're talking
with industry in different settings what
are people like looking for that killer
app of active inference or what are they
looking for their key measures
uh so I personally have a big paper
about the comparison with sampling based
methods like HMC and also in my PhD
thesis cell there will be a comparison
if not also other sampling based methods
uh so long story short sampling based
methods cannot really run uh this kind
of sophisticated inference in real time
uh they're very time consuming they do
not really scale well to large problems
which is really needed for active
inference agents because if you have
like a large environment very
complicated you will have you will have
a lot of unknown variables in your model
uh so yeah so there is a paper that
compares and basically we show that yeah
our approach scales much much better so
I personally run on just a just a
regular MacBook laptop I run the model
with 2 million uh unknown variables plus
and it was like quite quite fast and
then and if sampling based methods you
may you may find yourself in the model
with like 100 variables and then you
wait like two hours or something and
then it turns out that your chain did
not converge so uh or something like
that
cool yeah it's um people commenting in
the chat like how far message passing
and Factor graphs have come and so to to
bias lab and to Bert at all we
definitely
appreciate this exciting line of
research I mean there's so much to learn
there and sometimes looking at the
equations it can seem like it's like
written in stone and just sort of the
beginning and the end is you know
variational free energy but then in your
presentations you're really showing like
no we we are Hands-On that's where we
get the interpretability the modularity
that's where it really is implemented
and it's like an information Logistics
challenge it's not like an esoteric
philosophy question at that point
no no in indeed I mean I
I should say it's uh it's taken us I
mean we're no Geniuses right so our lab
exists more than eight years and and you
see all the people in the lab it's taken
us many many many years with lots of
wrong directions to get this to work to
where it's now so it's a very long path
but the the at this moment I'm pretty
confident that at some point in the
future and I don't want to put a uh I
don't want to say in three months or one
year but we will be able to write a
toolbox that will allow people to design
a generative model and just press a
button and and forget about the
inference you don't have to worry about
influence anymore it will be fast and
automated and that will happen and it
will happen within a few years and uh
and maybe somebody else will write an
even better toolbox but I'm pretty
confident that even our Toolbox will be
able to do that so
um and I think that yeah you know people
talk about uh so why don't we have the
success of deep learning and generative
AI right well if they have the success
because of a big data availability of
Big Data big computers and toolboxes
tensorflow and all the successes we
don't need big data because agents
collect their own data on or in the
filter we don't need big computers
active input agents
you know they they manage their power
resources but we need a really good
toolbox because
programming and active inference agent
programming the influence by hand is
just not doable
so we need a really good toolbox that
really automates this
we hope uh
RX inferior will be one of the first two
boxes to do that I am sure that other
people will also be working on it and
and better toolboxes will come about
um but I think the the optimistic
message is that it will happen right uh
and and once we have a toolbox like that
then we can actually a large community
can start building agents and we can
actually show
uh
Deployable agents in the fields right
that they work and they work better than
the reinforcement learning agent or
whatever is out there right
um so that's I think that's the very
positive and hopeful message
it's what we expect it's what we prefer
yeah yeah
any last comments from either of you
um comments from us no no we just I'm
just very happy to uh well to get the
opportunity and uh yeah I want to uh
so
yeah
um everybody can download this toolbox
um I think you at this moment you still
should be a programmer to work with the
toolbox
and I hope you're friendly because you
know it's not uh totally polished
in the way that we want but it's coming
right it's coming in the next years
there will be a good toolbox for for
almost everybody to use but people that
are interested
uh even people that are interested to
work here at biceland we have open
position uh for PhD students so we're
happy to uh yeah to receive
emails from people that are interested
to have to work with us
thank you Dimitri anything in closing
no just thank you yeah again for
possibility to present super nice to be
here
cool yeah well later in the year we will
be discussing your two-part recent work
and so we're going to be getting a lot
into the details and I I hope that
people in The Institute in the ecosystem
will be as excited
as we all are so thank you thank you
bye-bye
all right
for the next interval
we are in the section hosted by the
active inference Institute on our recent
paper active inference Institute and the
active inference ecosystem so two short
messages first if you're in the live
chat I'll post the link right now to the
paper and this can be more of like a
conversational interval so if you have
any questions about the um the ecosystem
or The Institute or
um any of the stuff that we're talking
about let's make it a conversation uh
and then second message if there are any
co-authors on this paper who are
listening to this stream then
message me on Discord or post in the
YouTube live chat or just check your
calendar and I expect some others to
join in
as we go
um
welcome Pablo
we'll be hearing in a little bit from
you as a presenter is there anything
that you wanna just bring up or reflect
on before I share the screen with the
paper let me just walk through it
explore it and hear questions
foreign
I'll bring in the paper and again anyone
watching live please just feel free to
write any questions and uh
I'm just going to bring it so that Pablo
you're not going to see the paper
uh but it's it's on the live stream
cool
well here we go
this is a paper that had an awesome
co-authorship and even broader circles
beyond the listed co-authors of
collaboration and contribution so just
like everything that has happened and
will happen
in our work
it was massively participatory and a
real learning by doing and a real
enactment moment
the first version was released three
days ago on Saturday August 19th and
I'll briefly just list all the authors
first we had the Institute as the
first author so that the citation can
always remain like Institute at all
Institute comma active inference
Institute and we also had Enrique John
boyick Libra Burien Matthew Brown RJ
corday Scott David David S Douglas Pablo
Fernandez macquieta Daniel Friedman
Holly Grimm Avalon kalu Raya Louisa
Annika Virginia blue Knight Alexandra
mccaleva Ali ramju Adil razi Jacob renan
tamari Dean tickles and Alex vyatkin so
this includes
everyone from Founders and officers and
board of directors and formal
participants on different projects and
different roles as volunteers or
facilitators or interns and also people
who are continuing to join the fun and
show up and makes
The Institute in our field what it is
and what it can be what what we want it
to be
there's a table of contents for those
who like to click through and just
broadly there's going to be a preamble
on active inference but outside of the
Preamble this paper is not conceptual it
is not technical it is not philosophical
although perhaps it can be read in all
of those ways but it's quite a
logistical
historical
and vision oriented position document
after getting some of the active
inferences out of the way in the
Preamble we're going to turn to The
Institute itself in terms of our Vision
Values principles and how we see moving
through the challenges that we're facing
right now
onto the specific history of the
Institute our current organization model
in terms of our governance and
Leadership structure as well as the
Institute units the organizational units
that support all the work we do
we then turn out to the community and
ecosystem growth and development
and go through some details of
different roles
that are stakeholders and participants
in our space and some of the tools that
we use today for managing information
and message passing
we talk a little bit about our
Communications plan internal and
external both sides of the blanket
and point towards some of the types of
support infrastructure and
administration that we do and that we
will offer for the active inference
ecosystem
we frame that in terms of continual
deployment continual development and
quality performance and growth
evaluations across multiple scales close
with some discussion and then provide an
appendix that overviews
a variety of the open source services
that the Institute has provided over the
past so
let's just jump in I'm actually going to
jump into the open source Services first
and overview them before we jump back up
to the top and look at the big picture
because this is really to appreciate the
work of so many contributors who stepped
up in The Uncanny Valley in the gray
Zone in the ecosystem as it's forming as
it's always forming and really made it
happen and so many people we know are
out there scribbling or taking notes or
printing out papers by friston at all or
struggling and asking questions are
there applications of this how would
this matter why would this matter is
there a code version of this how do you
connect the dots between these equations
like those are what we ask every day and
so when people can combine their regimes
of attention into a synthetic
intelligence outcome then we go so far
so
the first category of works that the
Institute has developed are educational
we've done video live streams since the
end of 2020 till now more than 370 live
streams
all live streams are
curated in terms of their transcript
and we increasingly are developing
automated and semi-automated methods for
transcription translation sub captioning
language modeling and so on
we've had textbook groups actually now
as of now we have three completed
cohorts of the active inference textbook
group The 2022 textbook
we have two courses that are being
offered that are produced by external
content developers and both of these
have only started in the last three four
months first is Chris fields's physics
is information processing and second is
the work spearheaded by avell and
co-organized with Kairos research active
inference in the social sciences both of
these are like awesome and great
learning experiences
as we heard from earlier in the
Symposium we're working with Sanjeev
namjoshi on his incredible textbook
although almost to call it a textbook is
to either think more broadly about
textbooks than one has or constrain what
it really is that he's doing because
it's such a unique
real research development full spectrum
effort so I'm really looking forward to
seeing how this plays out in 2024.
until then for those who want to get
involved with the testing that we do
and we've developed the active inference
ontology which is a critical resource
for the ecosystem it enables us to
Center accessibility rigor and
applicability across languages and
settings by knowing what it is that
we're talking about when we talk about
active inference
on the research side we've also
developed the ontology in a research
Direction in terms of research on and
about and with active inference itself
as far as software goes our primary
developments first off has been the
documentation and connecting the dots
around some of these other incredible
packages that others are developing for
example just in this Symposium we've
heard from some of the core developers
and
open source contributors to Pi mdp the
python package for generative modeling
as well as just a couple of minutes ago
from bertofries and Dimitri bagayev
coming from the Julia language RX and
fur side and both of those are some of
the leading packages for applying active
inference so we do a lot of work to
connect those dots and make it more
accessible not everybody is going to
jump in with all six feet to a
programming language
and what we've done with active block
prints with the work of Jacob smeckel
and others is to wrap generative models
from active inference inside of the
complex systems modeling framework
CatCat
we've developed notation
interoperability systems that actually
let us pull back one layer from the
implementational details themselves for
example of RX infer or of Pi mdp so that
we can bring it halfway to where the
ontology and the visualization and the
natural language exists and then use
language models and other techniques to
deploy it in an implementation fashion
we've developed a host of research
Publications
we support people in all of their
different stages of their career
different seasons of life and some
really creative work has been directly
produced through an Institute project or
somebody who knows may have gotten good
ideas or good feedback just by hanging
out being in the game and we've
performed literature meta-analyzes to
help grapple with the scope and the
quantity and the quality of what is
unfolding before our eyes or before our
antenna again even as we only so
partially sample this ocean of
information
we're active in standard setting and
continue to develop our qualification
standards for active inference that
could be the basis of Education research
and professional development
we provide a variety of mentorship and
facilitation service type activities
including volunteer program internship
program
distributed facilitation and applied
active inference symposia
these activities just as all others that
we're describing above are open source
and they're also open to your
participation so if you
can follow some of those Suggestions by
JF time boxing and prioritize and pay
attention and be active all those fun
things that he said and you're looking
to do it in a semi-structured way with a
volunteer program
or in a more structured way with the
internship then I heartily encourage
people to get involved act now
and in terms of governance activity
we have a scientific Advisory Board as
well as a board of directors and
together with the officers those groups
constitute the formal governance
structure of the Institute but there's
also so much more to it and we look
forward to understanding what ecosystem
governance can look like in the coming
years
so welcome Dean I just summarized the
the work itself that was the pre pre
Preamble and now if you'd like to say hi
you are Pablo before we jump into more
sections of paper or look at more
questions that people have asked how
goes it or what was your experience of
working with the paper or what brings
you on to this strange stream at this
opportune time
uh basically why I'm here is because I
for the first time even as as a acting
board member with
with the Institute I was able to get a
better sense of the kind of depth that
we aspire to
and I'm not sure whether or not we
are going to be I I really don't know
what directions we're going to be going
in the next
coming months weeks years Etc but I have
a better sense now as a result of
participating in this development
exercise of what the potential is that I
probably had at any time and I've been
with the active infant Institute for a
couple of years so that's
saying something I think we had to get
to this point to be able to write this
document and now it's it's acting as a
bit of a springboard now which way we go
and how we land I'm not still certain
about what that looks like but I think
that's part of what the really
interesting thing is
um we seem to have moved away from the
dock and now the real Journey Begins so
that's my take on it so far
moving away from the dock d-o-c-k
pushing off
using it as a springboard continuing the
adventure leaving the pre-print behind
continuing to version it as a living
document and also way finding outside of
the dock Pablo
oh wait I don't hear you yet Pablo
sorry oh I was mute hello
um it was a great experience to go
through the document and review it and
reread it and thinking about it actually
it's a living document which is super
exciting and I keep taking notes and and
hopefully uh
act on it on the future
and uh and it's been a super uh
experience to
to find
so many people with the same
um
some interest same interest
um some values that I really think
are going to be the basis of
organizations on the future
so I think we are doing something very
cool here
cool all right well let's just walk
through some of the
sections in the 25 minutes that we have
um again the paper is being shown on the
stream but but Dean and probably don't
see it so
we
kicked off with a preamble
we wanted to introduce active inferences
briefly as we could
and point towards the fundamental first
principles and physics-based nature of
active inference
and initially Point towards its
integrative capacity in principle and
then in the second paragraph there's
about 104 citations in this paragraph
and that's where it's really only a
sampling
of the domains 21 domains here so it's a
place where we can point to where is
active inference being applied or How is
active inference being applied or how is
it different or better than another
approach in a given setting which isn't
to say that it does everything in all
settings for all people at all times and
all of that but this is to say that
here's where one can look to find out
more and even just building this and
bringing it all together we we see so
many opportunities for epistemic
resources in the ecosystem and having
real-time literature analyzes and all
these kinds of services that we want to
provide
starting on page five we turn to The
Institute
itself
and we write as of August 2023 the
active inference Institute is a
registered non-profit organization
tasked with identifying establishing and
managing the sustainable implementation
of
administrative and governance functions
to give components of the active
inference ecosystem coherent forms and
reliable channels of communication two
publishing and Licensing protocols that
establish open and fair use and
effective dissemination of community
products within and Beyond the ecosystem
three services at the scale of
individual humans and the community at
large so that stability is protected
while risk and uncertainty are minimized
within the ecosystem and
four organization and operation of cyber
and cognitive security systems that
ensure productivity inclusivity
accessibility and safety in discourse in
collaboration
figure one gives a graphical
representation just one
of how we are now and for those who want
to dig more check out the 2022 active
inference textbook where you'll also
find a golden ring and we kind of took
that graphical Motif and
ran with it had a lot of fun and a lot
of interpretations there
so just here looking at figure one
Dean or probably just want to add
anything
yeah Dean
so one thing about the building of this
document
um with a whole bunch of authors
uh
it's often not made explicit but there
are two aspects to learning about
yourself one is to actually throw some
stuff down on paper
because you believe certain things need
to be included and then the second part
is the consolidation process and I think
one of the most interesting
consolidation processes was this graphic
because I think what what it does is it
tries to condense as as much as possible
and yet still remain coherent around
what the relational aspects that we are
trying to make available are as opposed
to this is what we've captured now look
look what our graphic designer came up
with
so if you've had a chance to kind of
look at this and really analyze it and
think about the layers and think about
okay so what's the background here
what's the foreground does this
representation allow for a swapping can
we have things that appear to be
background or you know fundamental basis
stuff that could actually be things that
we are addressing in the moment versus
those things which we look at as
particulars that in fact are
generalities so again it's one of those
things I I don't know Daniel probably
knows whether it's a where's Waldo's
thing or you know some sort of
artist that they came up with some
strange Twist on things but but the
bottom line is spend a few minutes have
a look because you'll want to go through
your own building of what these
relationships are and you'll also want
to be able to consolidate if you I
wasn't there when this representation
was built but I do know that I want to
be able to both look at it do a
comparative analysis to what I think the
Institute should be and then be able to
consolidate
awesome yeah just a few notes on this
and to give a visual overview since it
may be clearer to see this then go
through the pros that essentially
describes it as much later on
the Golden Ring represents the active
inference ecosystem and I think we could
talk about golden rings for a long time
to come but coming in from the ecosystem
on the bottom
bottom for the reader not from the other
side of the table
are the projects and all the projects
are participatory Endeavors they're
happening behind on and in front of the
golden ring depending on how you look at
it and that is the appendix and all of
those different projects that we talked
about and all of the iterations and new
threads that I know that we're going to
see in an hour and I know that we're
going to see in a month and in a year in
a century
and those projects are being supported
through to
units kind of like a department but an
organizational unit one centered on
education and one centered on research
the education unit is called eduactive
and the Research Unit is called
re-inference so right there you kind of
have active inference in case that
wasn't clear
coming from The Institute scale
supporting the unit scale
are a variety of functions such as
funding and Partnerships Communications
and hierarchical processes such as the
construction of enabling systems and at
The Institute scale other than
administrative functions we have the
officers the day-to-day operators of the
work the board of directors which is the
formal governing body and the scientific
Advisory Board where
we really want to call out broadly and
have people who may have or may have not
thought that they would find themselves
in a scientific Advisory board for
example in 2024
this is your invitation and we really
want to have a vibrant scientific
Advisory Board who serves liaison type
roles with different sectors and just
gives periodic super valuable High
leverage insight and then I guess
depending on how you think about it as
all things we have just a few terms
they don't just represent bricks in the
wall
but it's more of like the
the fibers we weave and some of these
are already things that we do every day
courses educational groups events live
streams ontology research others of
these are things that we know will be
coming into place in the coming years
and we know that the tapestry is just
going to continue to expand so it's
really exciting
on page six we have another figure
and this is just another way to
represent some of the functions that we
serve in the ecosystem this isn't the
only final or a fixed representation of
the functions that we have or the only
way to slice and dice or any of that but
just to connect some of the dots between
the functions that we do and want to
serve for the ecosystem
so starting from the broadest let's just
say where the listener is where you are
right now is in the space of awareness
and that happens through communication
some people who become aware through a
search or language model or a video
suggestion or a friend or happenstance
or synchronicity or however some
fraction of the aware
will pursue education
and about education we have and will
continue to produce the materials
documentation ontology courses live
streams and so on
education is produced and rests upon a
comments it's an epistemic comments it's
a verified information environment and
that is really the space the wildlife
preserve as I know Dean likes to refer
to it
not jokingly at all and underneath the
commons is the support that does
sit between a participatory Commons and
a formal governing kernel
that support in the coming years may go
many directions but we know it's going
to involve
all of our favorite things like Hardware
software information
Behavior or narrative and more and then
we have the
regular Institute scale governance
partnership sponsor and donor
relationships such that we can first
find a type of stability or
sustainability and then more actively
play a regenerative role in our
ecosystem we want to dispense micro
grants to people and we want to explore
paid internships and be able to meet
people where they are in their active
inference Journey
and
things have been happening to that end
and through many means since 2021
on page six Pablo or Dean want to add
any thoughts
I'm super excited about the governance
the education and the game and tools
in an hour we're gonna see
the first active inference game this is
very fun
um
on seven
we describe our vision
our values and our principles and just
to read the top level on the values and
principles they are active inference and
exploration
integrity and inclusivity
Dynamic internal modeling
anticipatory Behavior
and continuous development
on page a we talk about some priorities
and challenge areas these are challenges
across multiple scales they're
challenges that individual people face
in their journey to learn and apply in
so many different backgrounds these are
challenges of national interest these
are challenges of global emergency as
well
these challenges are educational in
nature for example related to scientific
literacy and Workforce Development and
just general professionalization and
Changing Times
on the research side there are some
priorities and challenge areas related
to the fundamentals
of cognitive science and grounding the
cognitive science in physics getting
that integrative first principles
framework that we expect and prefer
about information science and diverse
intelligences
things are faster and different than
they have been and active inference is
perfectly poised for sense making a
decision making in that space
user experience accessibility and
socio-technical Design
this is a major open question across
different settings so it's not uniquely
held to The Institute however we really
do believe and really will commit to
exploring new kinds of ergonomics and
onboardings and experience
so that we can
come through
and be how we want to be from the first
time somebody enters the game where we
can highlight accessibility meeting
people in the language that they prefer
to listen to and speak at the language
in computer language or at the math
level that reflects somebody's
preference in that moment
as well as being able to use augmented
and synthetic intelligence systems to
ramp up and even push the frontier of
what augmented people and other kinds of
collective intelligence systems can do
cyber and cognitive security
these also are broader topics
we've worked on these topics from an
active inference perspective many have
and we think that this is going to
become increasingly relevant as things
do
become more and more challenging and
uncertain in certain ways out there
scaling the active inference ecosystem
we've heard about this from the narrow
and technical side we had estimates of
the computational complexity of
sophisticated inference about how many
computer operations have to happen for a
given calculation to play out and that's
sometimes called scaling active
inference like okay it took one minute
on one gigabyte of data so how many
minutes is it going to take on this
computer with this much data
scaling the active inference ecosystem
though is a broader question and that's
where we come to more of the social
Fabric and the real sense of belonging
that we all want to have and co-create
and provide for others in the ecosystem
and so this kind of scaling is really
transdisciplinary it's really skin in
the game it's as real as it gets and
applying active inference
some applications we've heard from today
some applications are cited in the early
pages of this paper and more and more
come through every day and we support at
The Institute various applications of
active inference Dean what can you add
in there
why okay my beauty is off good so here's
here's a
here's something that never came up in
the writing of the document but I think
it's kind of interesting and I'm curious
what you guys have to think about this
175 years ago an institution came and
formed together it's called the
Smithsonian Institute now I don't know
if 175 years from this conversation
today they'll be the equivalent of
whatever the active inference Institute
is
175 years forward but I think it's okay
to start thinking in those terms it
doesn't mean that we follow in their
footsteps necessarily but I think it
means that we have a long-term view of
that the things that we write about
ourselves now have some shelf life
have some real sense of
what we can't there are things that we
can and we cannot change but if you look
at this if you look at the front page
the landing page of the Smithsonian
Institute the first thing that they say
is welcome which is what we say about
the active difference Institute and then
they say the Smithsonian institution is
the world's largest museum Education and
Research complex we are a community of
learning and an opener of doors
join us on a voyage of discovery
so in three sentences they kind of sum
themselves up what's the formula for not
just existing for 175 years but being a
force
and I think again
um
Daniel whatever you decide to highlight
in the document today but I think we're
really trying to do is say do the words
that we put out now
will they continue to resonate with
people
for decades to come and again I don't
want to sound all hand wavy but I want
to hold up an example of a place that
really did set itself up to be something
that people could return to again and
again and again
and I don't think there's anything wrong
with aspiring to having that kind of
place that kind of respect and I think
that the things that you're pointing to
right now hopefully
set the set the the you know the we're
preparing properly
so that's what I'm that's what I'm
taking away at this point
we know about that preparation
measurement cycle from Chris Fields
don't we
we go on let's talk a little oh yeah
please Pablo go ahead no no definitely I
completely agree I've been thinking
about that uh for a long time
you you want to build an act
uh for the best of the future and I
think to reflect that on the paper
it's super important so
yeah definitely up to do that
yeah
way ahead we describe some paths that we
want to take but and and the history of
the Institute we describe our Origins
but I actually wanted to come to to
figure three and four on page 11 to
speak to a building
one of the most amazing and encouraging
things has been the all ages all time
zone active build contribute mindset
and earlier
version of myself I might have thought
like hmm people who do variational
Bayesian methods and machine learning
they're going to have no issue
onboarding to active inference it's just
going to be like as simple as saying
yeah it's a variational Bayesian model
with action so just signal processing on
the inbound that's just control theory
on the outbound but if you're familiar
with variational bays and variational
free energy this isn't changing it that
much oh yeah we use a particular
partition and it's related to the free
energy principle but don't worry too
much you'll get there
I thought that that would be the
path for so so many
and
future analyzes will reveal what they do
or don't reveal
but what we found
in our
enacted work as it really played out
that there was inclusion and unique
contributions to conversations ranging
from philosophy of science
to fundamentals of statistics and meta
science and the role of quantitative
studies and social systems all these
amazing topics and people who just
scampered so rapidly through
the prerequisite what could be seen as
prerequisite from a disciplinary
perspective
was be was facilitated by the
recognition that one was already
in the space and in the way that they
needed to be to be an act of inference
and that was not
written out before and even now the
traces are barely recorded but it will
become to be understood more fully
and to your point Daniel
I think especially what the pie chart
shows is the actual
Spectrum aspect of this so I know that
right now that that maybe the
neuroscience and the psychology piece
take up a bigger portion
but I think one of the things that we're
trying to promote is the idea that um
you can come from just about any
background
as opposed to Oh all all paths lead to
like as you said an earlier version of
you said oh okay well I can see where
everything is gonna where the Confluence
is going to
no I think what this District this
demonstrates is that it's actually
becoming more distributed
the longer we
we continue to to exist
yeah this figure
of course I'm super happy with
everything that we were able to do but
this figure is like almost a little bit
like a um
like a a paper Target that we're just
going to blow out later because it was a
fraction of only people who had formal
affiliations listed which means only
people for whom we had done full
literature based polling up their
information so it doesn't even represent
the actual participation profile
this is more like the invitation list
for live streams
so
we are going to see another long a long
tail that
covers the part that's not the long tail
I believe
um
the rest of the paper continues along
possibilities challenges next steps
more about the Institute organization
various other pieces of information that
potentially eager stakeholders or
participants or donors or
Liaisons or other
people would like to learn more about
it's there to engage with we want people
to hop into our Discord and continue the
conversation or email us
or otherwise get involved
it's why we called this Symposium
enacting ecosystems of shared
intelligence at the of course relevant
suggestion of Carl friston
because we really do want to enact it so
if you feel like you're on the sideline
waiting to jump in or you're on the
beach and people are out there surfing
the 100 foot wave then maybe it's time
to get more involved so I will leave the
closing word first to Dean then Pablo
and then we'll go to raf's presentation
well just real quick again if you have
if you want to Consolidated document
that speaks to the now but also points
to a direction that we none of us really
know is is certain but is also really
exciting have a look at the doc
Pablo
um yeah I'm here uh
to make sure that I act as one of those
people of all backgrounds and
perspectives that has taken advantage
through one year of learning and acting
on this institute and hopefully see you
in one hour so thank you and have fun
thanks awesome thank you thank you Dean
thank you Pablo welcome RAF also
author on the paper so
how are you doing
uh I'm good what about you
pretty good other than this brief
interval of white light I'm just hanging
out
hahaha
fantastic so I'm trying to figure out
here how I can uh I'm using a different
uh slide software setting to make sure
that I can pull this up in the right way
so give me just a quick second yeah
great
cool so just just to
um read off what's coming while you
figure that
um out so right now we have Ralph
Kaufman and this presentation is going
to be Gaia an active powered Network for
planetary scale sense making
following this 30 minute presentation
we'll have available on embedded
normativity that looks perfect that's
perfect
awesome all right thanks Ralph to you
thank you all right I was going to try
to see if I could blow this up to full
screen but I I can't I got it I got it
on the Stream
oh it looks good on the stream go for it
cool so I'm just pulling up my notes
Here
all right
so uh let me just test that this moves
did I just move the slide
great cool all right so uh as I said uh
hi everyone it's a huge pleasure to be
here and thank you so much to Daniel and
everybody else at The Institute for
organizing this I'm going to talk about
what I think is the single most
important application of active entrance
not of in as a detriment to the others
but it's sort of Upstream of everything
else and that is how do the 8 billion of
us humans make sense of what's going on
in our planet and all scales and how do
we use that understanding to survive as
a species
so this presentation here is a bit of a
technical presentation and it has a lot
of content it's going to move pretty
fast and assume that you're familiar
with some Concepts but I'm going to try
to leave time for a q a at the end so
first of all I'm going to talk about the
motivation behind what we're doing uh in
particular the concepts of the medic
crisis and the third attractor then I'll
give an overview of our Network
architecture and the application so far
and cover the many remaining challenges
and last but not least I plan to
convince you that this is the single
most important thing you could ever be
working on and I'm doing this because we
need your help so that's a taster of
what we have and uh so as I said let's
jump right into it with the motivation
and uh what greater motivation could
there be
um if you haven't heard of The Meta
crisis uh it's a term that it's
originally from Doctor Who but it was
Borrowed by a thinker called Daniel
schmeckenberger to talk about the total
risk for Humanity and the biosphere that
is posed by the combination of three
factors the first being the increasing
interconnectedness of everything from
climate to food security to National
Security to biodiversity and everything
in between the second being the the risk
associated with self-evolving technology
including runaway artificial
intelligence and the third being the
increasing uh omnipresence of
coordination failures personified as the
the god of coordination failures
and so the combination of these three
factors as hypothesized by
schmuckenberger who lead to either one
of two attractors one of them being
chaotic breakdown of uh all structure
and the second being a reversal to
oppressive authoritarian control and
obviously both of those qualify as bad
in my book I assume in yours as well
so the question of course is can we
actually find a third attractor that is
positive Sun as opposed to negative sum
and rather the question is can we design
it so what I claim and what we as the
the guy Consortium claim is that yes we
can uh and we can design this attractor
and it's
the design goal is basically to build
resilience and the stabilization into
our biosocial economic system and to do
this subject to multi-level system
constraints like the applianetary
boundaries
desirability meaning it has to be
something that people actually want so
they will help it happen so it needs to
preserve standards of living and so on
and it needs to be feasible it needs to
be achievable from our current initial
conditions and of course there's a lot
of design complicators in the mix uh
some of which uh partial observation
there's lots of information asymmetry
going on uh there's a lot of uncertainty
about how the pieces of the world system
work from a scientific perspective
there's obvious computability
constraints Associated to this and last
but not least uh you can't really
control what happens in most cases we
can only create consensus
recommendations and nudges
so
uh easy right
of course it's not easy but we think we
can do it if we apply the the sum of the
principles from cybernetics that you
already know and apply them in a
decentralized uh positive sum composable
way so uh what we're talking about here
is uh decentralized Network this implies
hybrid AI human Network for planetary
scale decision support and automation uh
it features uh it recognizes that we
will have human and artificial agents
interacting by the billions in an open
network
it its goal is to facilitate both
consilience or model alignment and
coherence or goal alignment at multiple
levels or scales up to the global scale
meaning the survival of the system as a
whole
it will need to feature built-in in
incentives and governance and it will
need to be private privacy preserving
intrinsically so uh the below list
participants are participants founders
of the of the Consortium I'm going to
talk about it later
but so this is the framing this is the
motivation for what we're doing and uh
and I'm gonna give a whirlwind tour of
the architecture so far and I'm going to
cover mostly what we've built uh the the
version of this architecture that we've
built so far uh thinking about this
explicitly and then I'm going to talk
about how this connects to other
architectures that already exist in the
world just very briefly
so we've been uh framing this as uh an
architecture for building decentralized
digital twins uh which are local models
of real world systems that run in
network
and the road that such a digital Twins
play is that they help us understand the
costs and benefits of strategies and
projects that happen in the real world
and we in in our organization digital
Gaia we started out caring primarily
about agroecology so how do you actually
make better decisions uh meaning better
recommendations negotiations valuations
investments into a form into a forest
into uh uh bio light landscape to make
it uh better to make it more likely to
to survive and thrive
so uh as a practical implementation uh
it needs to tackle several real world
challenges first of all uh it needs to
handle distributed non-iid data uh data
sparse it's heterogeneous it's private
it's potentially unreliable
uh it needs to enable localized
collaborative forecasting and planning
personalized planning and privacy
preserving it needs to uh accept the
fact that it won't be able to directly
control but only recommend it nudge as
we discussed
and the the outline of what we came up
with is this concept of the guy Network
which is a mesh of AI agents called
natural entities or ants for short that
act as proxies for Real World Systems
um each and runs on an engine called
penguorn which it uses to inquire learn
plan and allocate resources and ants
communicate in a language called the guy
protocol
they they use this language to
independently interact with their
environments and each other and if we do
this right I'll show a bit more of this
later but if we do this right the guy
networks Behavior approximates a single
composite agent that handles uh that
interacts with and couples with its
global environment
foreign
just to give you an overview of how this
works behind under the hood the fatron
engine is really the heart of our
architecture and the core Loop uh that
is mentioned here is a typical active
inference Loop but uh to make this work
in very heterogeneous and distributed
contexts there's lots of work involved
so just some highlights that I think are
going to be particularly interesting for
this crowd uh first of all so as I said
this first the same core engine needs to
be able to work for very heterogeneous
contexts so each agent has access to a
library of generative models and these
models are specified using a python
based program probabilistic programming
DSL and they declare what context they
are appropriate for using a shared
ontology uh using that ontology fangorn
can then select the most appropriate
model to use online given the
configurations like project
configurations and the kinds of
observational data available so using
the model using model that's appropriate
for uh for a form or for a horse what
kind of form what kind of forest what
kind of ecosystem what kind of of
you know their context energy projects
um I'm gonna get into the examples right
now because there's more more on the
applications later on
so uh we end up with a network of
heterogeneous agents but that's okay
they actually form a single model in a
formal sense because they're all
connected hierarchically uh by a system
of of hyper priors and uh this means
that Bangor needs to support inference
of generic hierarchical generative
models and we actually do this
automatically using approximate
posteriors with structural constraints
um and so we have this Global model that
connects all the nodes and describes
General facts that apply over multiple
contexts and this means the whole
network needs to jointly perform
inference over this Global model using a
peer-to-peer or Federated algorithm so
initially the way this works initially
uh the network sets the global posterior
to be the same as the global prior each
node then independently performs local
optimization of the variation of free
energy and then passes the parameters of
the new Global solution to the peers in
the network where they use it as a hyper
prior and this works over a broad range
of topologies and under pretty General
constraints and by the way I'd love to
I'd like to mention that uh there's a
lot of overlap and interaction between
the stuff that I'm talking about here
and some of the other presentations that
you're seeing today and I I wasn't able
to reference them explicitly in this
talk but I I'm sure you guys are going
to see the connections
cool so
um what it turns out is that the shared
parameters that represent our Global
model are effectively stored by the
network stored in a Federated parameter
store meaning that each node stores
their own local parameters their private
stuff about their own local context and
multiple nodes store copies of the
global parameters
and this architecture because it
supports heterogeneous uh local models
it actually allows us to introduce
another kind of nodes which we call ant
mood nodes uh these are notes that
aggregate scientific and empirical
information using a meta-analysis model
and uh we actually uh are able to use
that meta-analysis model to constraint
or constrain our project level models or
ants using quote-unquote imported
knowledge that wasn't directly observed
by them which is left to right in this
picture but this actually also goes two
ways so empirical findings from the
projects uh what actually works on the
ground for this particular project also
informs the end moves but serious which
is the right to the left and so we
actually have a complete uh type of
Science and empirics all implemented
using hierarchical active entrance
so finally uh just uh among the global
parameters that Network learns by
Federated inference are the precisions
associated with data coming from the
different data providers and this gives
each node a way to consume data without
rustic ground truth and basically to
learn together which sources they can
rely on for what
uh this is just uh some of more core
features we're working on integrating
many other capabilities into this
architecture not going to go through all
of this uh but basically what what we're
finding is that we have all the building
blocks to turn this into a full feature
decision Network and complete with its
own internal knowledge economy meaning
that contributors uh contributions get
attributed and rewarded in proportion to
the to the free energy reduction that
they afford
cool so uh jumping into applications uh
as I mentioned our main focus as as an
organization organization has been on
modeling agroecological projects like
regenerative agriculture and
agroforestry and this exercise is all
the constraints that we've talked about
so far
so uh again I'm not going to go into
full detail but just to give an overview
of what is the anatomy of uh generic
model for a form of forest so we start
at the bottom right with observables
that are things that we can measure
about that ecosystem about that that
local context like the plant counts and
size vegetation indices from satellite
data and so on these are are linked to
latent states which form a non-linear
dynamical system that's parameterized by
uh the policy the the the things that
modulate the the latent States uh like
agricultural interventions and practices
we can think of the timing of plant
planting and harvesting what kinds of
crops or trees get planted what products
like pesticides get applied or not and
more uh as well as covariates so
external events like weather physical
risks Wildfire drought and so on
um and so there's uh some scientific and
measurement parameters uh that that go
into this as well things like uh the
effect sizes of the various actions and
covariates and these local parameters
are conditionally dependent on a set of
global global parameters which as we
discussed they they link information
between different ants and different
sources of knowledge
um uh and uh so these same Global
parameters are used in the meta-analysis
model and they actually established the
link between what happened what is found
to happen on the ground and what is
reported in the literature
um and uh so I'm not going to go into
this because I I think I'm gonna uh run
a bit long but basically the concept is
is that we have these project nodes that
correspond to to many forms and they're
each on Independent nodes in the network
they're also connected to this common
meta-analysis model and uh together all
these uh together these nodes they
incorporate academic studies expert
knowledge and uh locally relevant
context they did so privately so only
processing the local data locally and uh
through this parameter sharing they
actually jointly uh and iteratively
estimate the the global posterior uh in
a cycle forever for as long as there is
new data about the project as long as
there's new studies and new expert
knowledges so so all this is happening
basically in an online way and again the
topology can vary but the principles
remain the same so just to see you show
a little bit about how uh this works
this is just two epochs of the the
posterior the global posters and this is
just location and scale four four two
uh parameters uh the slope and intercept
of the relationship between uh uh
vegetation index and the tree biomass in
a one given Hector or forest and as you
can see this this converges pretty
pretty quickly it's comparable to to
local local lowly methods
um and just to highlight how this can be
used to to uh also the limits of how
this can be used to estimate uh Source
reliability uh here's a really
successful example at the left is pretty
pretty straightforward to use this to
estimate reliability of uh of uh
satellite data and for other cases like
very local very uh context specific data
you actually need more data or more data
from more independent sources that we
had in this demo here
um uh another
very useful use case of this is as we
discussed we don't have direct control
over what happens at a form we can only
recommend and nudge often we also like
we get there's a node gets suit up and
that gets stood up for an existing
project that has already happened and we
want to find out uh what actions were
taken in the past and the same uh the
same generative model can be used to
estimate uh what happened in the past in
the example it infers uh when planting
started and when harvests started for
for different fields
um so uh bringing all together one of
the applications that we've been using
we're really working on it actually uses
all those Machinery together to validate
claims about projects performance and to
estimate future performance we've
deployed this uh in real world projects
uh this one this is the examples here
and seeing this photo are by uh are
relevant to acroforest reforms in
Colombia and uh we found that this
actually helps the project developers
and their funders to come to a shared
understanding of how successful the
project is how much it's worth in terms
of its impact and its fundability
whether it should be scaled up or or
needs to change course uh what is the
quality of the strategy versus other
potential strategies for natural
regeneration and so on so uh it's
actually useful on the ground for
decision making in this context cool
so finally uh I want to talk about the
end State and uh going back to our
original motivation of solving
everything I forgive you for your
thinking this is nice but hey we're
we've been kind of in this uh downward
spiral towards the meta crisis for a
long time and what you're telling me
doesn't even come close to solving
everything and you're right uh there's a
lot of movie pieces that need to be
built and connected but here's the good
news
um we can do this there's no mystery
here and we don't need Perfection I love
this quote from Edward Fullbrook that
says that to define a policy we don't
need an exact empirical measures
or optimality if one jumps from an
airplane it may be nice to have an
altimeter but what one really needs is a
parachute so there is uh only so much
that we can get in terms of diminishing
returns what we should be really
focusing on is creating and refining
Solutions everywhere and connecting them
everywhere
um and you might be thinking about how
this is actually scale to Global goals
and how does this actually get used uh
for uh scalably uh in building into the
the fabric of decisions in our in our
society uh so about scaling to Global
goals uh I will again won't be able to
get into the details but maybe Conor
mentioned this in his presentation
earlier uh we have actually some proof
of Concepts that we can actually build
active agents that that are made of
active and active agents so we've shown
in this paper here that a collective of
interacting acting phasions uh is able
to perform approximate inference at The
Ensemble level and that this further
that this happens through a specific
mechanisms that are mediated by uh by
capabilities like theory of mind and
goal alignment they they work together
to improve Collective performance by
eliminating ambiguity and through
actively exploiting diversity
um so that's one and the other question
is uh how do we actually uh build this
kind of stuff into not just these uh ad
hoc decisions but into really the fabric
of decision making and that that gives
our global economic system so uh talking
about here uh work that I did with
Casper has
this is a game that highlights the
ability of ants just like the ones that
we just described to infer true System
state and use it to credibly incentivize
long-term positive outcomes in uh an
externality happy scenario uh this team
uh we were able to show that it works
even with adversarial bot strategies uh
and even with high uncertainty and
intentional misinformation so you can
actually get these ends to to
work with budgets and incentives to
drive decision making that internalized
sexualities and uh and compensates for
occlusion and uh uh generates long-term
positive outcomes
that's not all there are other Solutions
uh uh that have been around for hundred
and hours
that apply similar principles to Global
decision making problems in the real
world at scale this is one case study
from our partners at cognizant that they
developed for the cool epidemic and this
is uh not using active influence
formalism this is a combination of
traditional recurrent neural networks
for prediction and evolutionary
optimization for prescription and it's
actually able to achieve some pretty
amazing uh stuff it discovers a Pareto
front between uh prevention of cases and
uh economic cost
it's uh it's also a showcase for hybrid
human AI intelligence they did an
initial version of this model then they
launched the next prize they got a bunch
of contributions for other models and
then they did a meta model uh that
discovered a better burrito front and uh
even better even better this tool has
actually been used to advise policy in
the real world so it's actually very
exciting that uh we're working with them
and connecting the dots because we need
to connect the dots we need to bring it
all together this uh this illustration
here is just uh I think a subset of the
uh effects of the of the climate change
crisis which is just one aspect of the
meta crisis on on humans on our society
and the economy and uh so we actually
need to be able to deploy solutions that
work across many different domains and
to connect these dots uh this means two
things uh the first is interoperability
aligning decisions across context so
that we don't get unintended
consequences and second is reusability
so being able to to transport and
transfer uh learning and structure
across context so for instance using
that evolutionary approach from the from
the coveted example in in our
agricultural context or in many other
possible contexts and this takes a form
of libraries of components apis and so
forth
so that's what we're working on so we're
launching this Consortium we just put up
the website a few minutes ago and we
have the goal of having a minimal but
functionally complete implementation by
the end of next year
uh and this is an open project we are
working on this at our organization
called digital guy but we're also
launching this open Consortium that
welcomes uh contributors from anywhere
both active entrance experts and
non-experts and uh we need a lot of
contributors we need all of you because
this is uh the most important thing that
we could ever be working on together and
we need your help to tackle the many
remaining challenges so if you want to
help us build the planetary brain please
go to Gaia consortium.org and or reach
out to me you know where to find me uh
and together we can design build and
learn what it takes to achieve
planetarium generation thank you
thanks for the great presentation
I'll uh post the link to Gaia Consortium
into the YouTube live chat but let me
get a few quick questions in so
um
here we go first uh question this is
from
uh Marco Lynn
um
I agree with the critical importance of
such a project how will you deal with
the challenges of scaling given the
dependence on real world entities like
humans
um
for dependence on real world entities
like humans for major meta crisis
domains such as geopolitics
socio-cultural fragmentation and other
particularly hard sense making domains
uh first of all hi Marco yeah thanks for
the question and uh I 100 agreed that uh
I'm not claiming that this is sufficient
I'm just claiming that it's necessary uh
we do have a lot of energy that that a
lot of ideas and a lot of energy that we
want to put into exactly what to
describe how to uh change the uh how to
weave what we're doing into the existing
incentive Landscapes whether they're
Market incentives or policy incentives
But ultimately this needs to be uh an
enabler this needs to meet people where
they are and we need to be cognizant
that change is not going to happen
overnight at least not right now right
typically these things take uh take a
while to mature and then they they snap
into place and we're already finding
some of this happening in some of the
domains that we're working on where uh
nothing happened for a very long time
and then bam hockey stick and we believe
that the same uh can happen in and
pretty much anywhere so we're very
optimistic
great what are currently the greatest
challenges for Gaia as an organization I
love that kind of ambiguous question
like is that the guy a Consortium as an
organization or is it but let's let's
hear both what are the greatest
challenges or frictions for the
Consortium and for the bigger picture
too
also uh I I'm gonna I'm not gonna talk
about the the technical stuff for a
change I'm gonna talk about uh the the
more Mana stuff it's actually very
related to what uh your uh previous
presentation Daniel about that paper uh
about the Institute talked about and
it's really related to to uh building
out this common what we were calling the
common cognitive kernel for for sense
making and decision making and uh
relatedly uh breaking through this
um
uh this uh culture of sort of Suspicion
and uh surfboards and getting
um you know State people State trying to
stake their their claim to something so
we are and always have been uh extremely
open but it's it's kind of hard anyway
to build trust so we are
were aware that it's going to take a
while to build to build this trust with
everybody and
uh and I think the only answer to that
is really to be as participatory and uh
and transparent as possible also uh
being humble and knowing where where we
haven't we don't have the answer and uh
asking people to help us
awesome any closing words or thoughts
well if there are no further questions I
uh again I I thank you all for for
paying attention and I'm going to
be reaching out a lot more you're going
to hear a lot more about this Consortium
as I said it was just formed you just
put up a website in time for this
presentation and by the way uh thanks so
much to to Mahi and uh and of course
Steve and everybody else who's been uh
part of forming and uh and getting this
to getting this ball to start rolling
um we are
um you know very early stage very
formative and still uh very quiet so we
definitely are we lost I I just gave you
like my perspective on on a bunch of
these things the the shape of it that
that has come from from or work on this
so far and even not all of it just piece
that we could cover in 20 minutes or so
uh but we are we're very plural we want
to uh engage with you on uh on different
paths forward different opportunities to
to
build things experiments to connect the
dots to learn together and yeah
ultimately like we we really just want
to uh provide a platform a convening
space a protocol uh uh in the classic
sense of New World the word of a you
know a shared language a shared means of
communication a shared means of
understanding to find together what we
need to do to to actually build this
third attractor
awesome
call Gaia trim tab
thank you exactly
thanks so much Daniel and see you guys
soon bye
bye
all right
what a cool presentation
next up welcome avail
we have available with embedded
normativity so thanks aval to you
hello can you hear me yep
we'll do
and can you see the slides
um I only see the top left of the slide
you only see this the top left yeah just
yeah try again thank you
okay
Yep looks great thank you
okay good
so I am uh
I'm interested in a multi-scale
collective organization this is why I
came talk to in France to begin with
and the core question I've been asking
is um basically when we look at human's
organization there is great Evolution
there is a challenge through time of the
specific patterns that are enacted and
this is very hard to account for and I
have been trying to pin down more and
more specifically what exactly is going
on and how to model it so this specific
work is a work I wrote in the context of
what my PhD of course which is funded by
The Escape project a project in a
cognitive archeology that's interesting
interested sorry in how the culture the
archaeological landscape shape cognition
and vice versa the title of it is
onomatic normativity an active inference
of urgency
an active influence account of agency
being flesh because you will see very
quickly why
so first we will go through the existing
work on ankle recognition in the context
of acting in France then we'll try to
expose the concept of embedded motivity
which we introduce here and what it
means and then we'll look at the more
semiotic question around the
externalization and utilization of
normal activity in
cultural landscapes
so first encrypted cognition inactive
inference
so we interact in France I will go
quickly over it I still need to do it
because there are Lookers that are not
familiar
so active in front say that uh agent
continuously predicts the specific queue
sensory cues they will see and they
predict the action or policy they will
not take and they basically enact an
ongoing stream of expectation that they
reconstruct given you know a coming
signal
so this is best accounting for in this
schema which shows the agent as the
miracle system which engage through
environments through action and
cessations and all of this
um specific
domains they minimize a specific
function that is called free energy and
whose minimization basically means there
is a prerogative process going on
and a core property effective in France
is that it dissolves agency as we
typically understand it we don't have
agents that have like internal monologue
that drives them to take decision we
have a constitution dissipation of
what's going on and whatever an agent
anticipate itself to do it will do
and so this goes for
computationally satisfying but very
definitionary notion of what is going on
with agency
so the question then comes uh what is
the relation between an agent and the
cognitive landscape in which it evolves
uh I will present very rapidly again the
framework of skill and functionality
appear nearby Bruno's
and which says that skill agents which
we understand as agents that understand
what is going on around them they will
basically experience the world as the
landscape of affordances which is
opportunities for actions
and they will the recognition pretty
much reduces to the experience of the
Sunscape and adaptive engagement with it
which basically maximize the grip the
agent as on the system
and essentially for reasons we will not
go over because it's math
the very uh existence experience of this
landscape it is equivalent to the
existence of constraints of our
attention the attention that the agent
gives to thing which uh translates the
emerald expectation that are at least
two times about it but the more
expectation that the agent enacts
and so this becomes very interesting
when we you know cross it with the
existence of encaturation in humans
because the basic experience we have of
affordances of what we can do it is uh
shapes culturalities shaped by social
interaction when we learn uh with other
humans about what we do what we can do
and what we can do and this means that
the basic human experience it's
thoroughly encultured it's embedded in
what ROM said called a control landscape
landscape of cultural fondensis
and it is embedded in cultural and
material
[Music]
regimes of attention so ways to pay
attention to things
and this is a figure that comes I
believe from this year on
thinking throughout the minds where it
shows basically and how the actual
installation cycle when we have the
Civil agent they build a common
environment that has epistemic cues on
how the world is like and when we are
incarcerated to pay attention to things
in a certain manner that makes it so we
perceive and enact this this landscape
and so the uncultured constraint of all
the flow of attention because of the
what we saw just before the deflationary
account of agency it means that the very
expensive landscape cultural landscape
that is collectively enacted it
effectively integrates intentionality
and it effectively uh integrates normal
activity in a way that Clash is strongly
with classical account of both
so given this state of the art let us
look at what I mean specifically about
embedding normativity so a marine
motivity is a kind of alternativity I
think you have you have got it
so normal activity it means basically
the criterions by which we judge things
to be good and bad
in the context of biological system they
will look for specific I don't know
chemical concentration and I will avoid
other this is the phenomenon of
chemotaxis this is pretty basic and this
is a form of normativity
but for humans we will typically think
of you know laws cultural norms
um there's really shared way to judge
Behavior
and again at least in the context of
flow and choice Theory
which because you think there is an
agent he has access to information and
we'll think Hmm what should I do and He
will judge uh rationally about what is
good and what is bad based on a
collection of values which are internal
to the agent this is not how it works
um
what I call embodied motivity is by
contrast regimes of normal activity
where it is the uh the norms and value
that guide the agent's Behavior it is
embedded in the material and cultural
environment so basically the agent
projects a specific set of norms and
value in his very experienced princess
environment
and it will perceive the locus of
normativity as the environment and not
as a form of internal judgment
um
let us look at what can exactly how
amazing motivity work it will be more
concrete
so first we can materially constrain
people to do things so for example there
are roads you can go off-roads but it's
harder and you can't really do that if
you're a chariots so when you have a
specific pattern of roads which is
constructed by cities
uh you were pretty much constrained to
follow the roads materially and for this
we will talk of structural embedding
and there is another regimes
interactivity where we build on
environment that will basically queue
you suggest you into uh adopting
specific norms and specific values for
example Escape
things that vertical patterns in
archaeological culture
they are somehow embedded within uh what
we call vertical Norms so hierarchy and
certification in Social relationship
and for this specific form of mudding we
control curve semantic compelling I'm
what is must be very clear is that we
don't have structural embedding on one
side and cementing embedding you know
there are basically two mechanism
complementary mechanisms in which uh
nominative sorry embedded multivity
occurs if we look at the city so this is
a
impression of Sumerian culture city
states
we have much organization that prompts
specific kind of behavior so for example
we have a bridge and this bridge allow
you constrain you to go through the
river in a specific way if you are on
foot
but this particular constraints it is
perceivable so by using the bridge you
will also see that you can navigate the
world in this specific way
so you don't have aspiration between
semantic and structural embedding we
just have two ways in which
um constraints of our behavior that are
embedded in the environment work
and
something that is a core to the account
of a medical activity is again that it
is not internal but we need to go into
more detail about what we mean by not
being internal because of course we're
talking about agency agents constrain
what engines do it's not outside
uh what it is is
um
and Marine motivity is the origin of the
motivity where the norms and value they
stem from the experience of foreigns for
example if I see a fire I will not think
about
hey could I put my hand in it and get my
hand burn
I think pretty painful I won't do that
if I even think about putting my hand in
the fire I will immediately feel bad the
normativity it's embedded in my
experience of the world
I feel like the fire or more
specifically the possibility of putting
my hand in the fire is intrinsically bad
I do not feel there is a possibility
that is neutral and then I judge it to
be bad
but uh of course this uh this judgment
does not occur outside even if I feel
like it's about my affordances it
emerges from the arrangement I have with
the material and cultural niche in which
I find myself
and if we want to
um
to untangle what this mean precisely we
will have to go into more detail into
the what I call the externalization
andalization of anonymity
so let us look at something very simple
how normativity work for embodied agents
so I'm read agents they do things with
hopefully in an Niche that is material
and this Niche will be marked by the
activity of my agent and these marks
they can then act as constraints either
through structural augmentating
embedding in the age environment because
like basically signify that in the past
I wanted to do that maybe doing that is
you know good
for example uh we have Centuries with I
don't know if century is a English word
but we have path if uh animals that have
legs this is actually important work uh
sorry work on a specific path they will
compact the Earth and it will become
improper to grow anything even grass and
you will have a path that will emerge
that are pretty it's pretty visible and
I tell you hey not only this Earth is
Compact and allow you to walk on its
like without effort but also this has
been widely judged to be um
to be a Goods uh
Outlook outline for navigation in this
specific environment
so the very experience of a path
basically invites you it affords you
perceive the affordance of walking
through the path
and this is something that again can
result from your own activity that can
be written into development by your own
activity
and solve this uh that's the question of
how okay there exists embedded
normativity but how do we embed
normativity what is the activity of
embedding motivity like
and the word I will use for that is
externalization we perceive the world
because we externalize uh specific
causes of sensation into an imagine uh
objective external world
so when we see the path
we see a path we do not see compact
Earth that we then compute to mean that
other things have worked on it we just
see hey there is a path
and this is because we have externalized
a specific cognitive kind which is the
path
and this is a argument that several
people named here are Lennon steinler
which if I remember well
um worked on the um
the production of devices that help
blind people see things through
I believe an array of Repertory device
on their shoulder so the core
argument they make is that if you give
people that they will start seeing
things they will start pursuing things
as being before them rather than having
Liberation on the shoulder and then
thinking about oh what does it mean and
so the basic argument is that perception
is just
um picture of what cause we infer what
is the structure we infer of environment
given the existence of a specific
coupling device that relates action to
sensation and vice versa
and this critically relies on the
internalization of specific we could say
a lot of things but I will say priors
specific prior is not an interception
so missing the path as a path relies on
me having the prior knowledge that there
is such a thing as past and I should be
expecting to see them around
and so you have um duality of
externalization and internalization in
the production of a marine motivity I
can only see Norms out there if I've
internalized integrated or specific
operators of perception that entails
that they are indeed those specific
Norms that are embedded in those
specific references
and so this uh produce a marginal
question of symmetics basically of
information Theory
how do reading and writing motivity
works
uh so my next 10 lies I treat the world
as having specific natural categories
that I pretty much imagine
and I can use them because I can adjust
them as an extended memory that allow me
to read and write normative cues uh this
can be um you know letters uh pure signs
but as far as I'm concern here all signs
are at least implicitly Innovative there
about how you should interpret the
design
and this means that we can experience a
specific landscape or valencies and we
can
we can write things out there we can
write normative cues biobehavioral that
will then constrain for the behavior but
nothing tells us that we can
that we can
communicate through this the
communication it works because of the
internalization of prayers if a given
community of agents are vitalized a
specific set of prayers that is a set of
pairs that enable externalization of the
narrative cues then only it can use the
environment as a way to
two rights and reads normative cues as a
embedding normativity thing
and this communication it can be read in
terms of information theory of course it
can be read in terms of sematics but
what is uh critical to analyze that the
process of internalization it is there
there is no um trust system there is no
private key that allows you to be sure
that the way you internalize Norms is
very specifically uh the way in which
the amylene motivity was encouraged to
begin with there is a loss or there is
ambiguity or there is I'd rather say it
like this an active the march of
reconstruction of given prayers by the
agents and so this gap between the
intent of other Communications and my
intents my understanding of what I meant
by their acting active engagement with
the world it builds a tiny Gap in
information that is somehow enough to
drive the opinion evolution of cultural
landscape and this is something that I
do not think is a marriage inactive in
France and I think is of major interest
to research to the research at least in
the evolution of opponent evolution of
crucial landscape
so uh to sum up things
uh I just presented the paper that is
called animate motivity and that speaks
and surprisingly enough of embedded
normativity
uh first major point is that effective
inference is correct then
um our notion of agencies dissolved
essentially in the notion that we can
perceive and enact cognitive landscape
if you want
and given that this is the case
we will experience the norms and value
that guide our Behavior as a property of
you know the cognitive landscape
experience the affordance that we can
perceive
and this specific regime of normativity
I call embedded normativity
and the third thing is that you have a
critical thing going on any other
symmetically constraining thing going on
in the externalization and utilization
of regimes of embelline motivity
because those two things they
respectively enable nomadin activity to
exist to have causal power
and the enable also the operating
Devolution of the Norms that are
embedded in a given landscape in a given
measure landscape and therefore the
operating evolution of the assaded
cultural or cognitive landscape
so thank you I will enroll my references
slides in case someone has the really
needs to know what the reference season
is ready to move around the video for
this
and do you have questions
awesome thank you avail
while people are typing any questions
could you maybe just give a little
introduction to the active inference for
the social sciences course like what
brought you to want to
facilitate this effort and where are we
at and where do you want it to go what
do you want it to be for people
and then continue
good point thank you uh the active info
Institute organizes uh and keros
research organize a course on the on
active inference in the social science
that is essentially in explaining the um
basic the March the basic hypothesis and
the consequences of the cultural
landscape formalism that I
hinted at slightly in this presentation
the goal of the course is to give a
basic ontology that is on the interface
between complexity sense let us say
physics written large cognitive Science
Central science to afford
interdisciplinary collaboration in the
in the social science and in the study
of the evolution of human societies
and I think it is cool
but then I asked because I have a nice
date some maybe you should ask Daniel
which is absolutely embiased whether the
course is cool
I I've been enjoying it a lot uh we just
finished last week with my section on
Collective Behavior
first we had the introduction lecture
from you then Ben why on the basics of
being an active agent and we have Lorena
and mouse sections upcoming as well as
your more dedicated session yeah it's
been a really
fun uh
uh experience and it's going to provide
a really useful
missing piece
in the ecosystem I guess just one
question I have how do we take some of
these
topics you're bringing in about the
embedded normativities and think about
them digitally like are we talking about
conceptual embeddedness in information
environments and or are we talking about
the ergonomics of sitting at our desk or
how do we bring that kind of pleasure
path
stigmergy on the grounds
into the digital are we talking about
something that's
embodied and embedded
in the information space or are we still
talking about bodies
so if we talk about humans we talk about
bodies with the brain needs that do
things in a material environments but
your question is uh I'm not sure on the
studies how can we bring these specific
Concepts in the study of digital
filamental I like Twitter internets yeah
is that it yeah okay so Europe basically
is the whole study on the uh affordances
you have a
so the recipient of design has
incorporated a while ago the National
Conference in its structure and most of
the study in the digital design center
learn what uh platforms are for or do
not afford
and we have a richer stance when you
take into account not what you can do
with a specific interface but what the
specific interface invites you to do
given a set of cultural
it can be self learning but given a set
of power that you share with
with the um
platform in a way that is a
formal but indirect and
um
so yes I would look at it in terms of in
user interface design I think this
concept specifically is useful for
um
for interface design
then you will have implicitly the
question of
um the floor that platforms such as I
don't know uh Twitter Facebook
um how specific structural environments
bring specific Collective dynamics that
might be a bit
um richer
not richer specifically but that might
go in a direction that the user
interface question do not go into
and that can still be modeled in terms
of constraints and therefore in terms of
environmentivity is that on point we'll
go to a question
um
yeah that's interesting about
what the interface does and then what it
invites it might invite things
in order for that invitation to be
fulfilled it has to actually provide
that possibility
but it might invite things that that
aren't relationally possible like there
might be a wall which invites climbing
to a given Observer yet they cannot
climb it and then on the other side
is
a capacity that isn't invited and
that is the
the adjacent possible of tool use
where something that was being used for
this purpose it's like all of a sudden
it just fell out of someone's hand they
grasped it a different way it invited a
different engagement and then that can
become re-entrenched and that points to
that sequential like making and breaking
of new spaces that your work has
featured over the last few years
exactly this work has been developed
with uh while thinking about tool use
while thinking about the cognitive
archeology we're thinking about the
experience of cities the way urbanism
from specific behavior
uh but
um if I can get back on the internet
thing I'd like to make it more specific
so the interface design as far as I know
is focused on interface let's see this
that is not surprising
but in doing so it is focused on
specific foreign what you can do you
have another layer in uh ecological
psychology with his the layer of
solicitation so for example Twitter
there's something very specific which is
when you log in it shows you it shows
you the number of notification you have
then it removes it and you have to wait
to know which were those certification
and you have to wait no
once again not one minute but a random
amount of time so this is uh what they
call dark patterns they are patterns in
design that are explicitly designed to
create addiction so this is a layer you
can't afford in a France because uh
yeah
from a foreign
motivation in the way uh specific
structural environment is perceived the
simulatics semantics Maybe
the meaning that given landscape has for
an agent and even if you look at this
you are still still looking at the
platform in a way that is um
is embedded from these specific patterns
that specific patterns of things that
people do on the platform if you have
Twitter without the aggressive qualities
and the um way to aggressively signal
that you are in whatever it is is going
on you don't have Twitter much of
Mastodon maybe that has very similar
affolensism very very dissimilar
solicitation
so this is this is why you have to to
take a multi-scale account of things and
when you take them kind of things you
have to look at the semiotics basically
Behavior how specific coordination occur
at specific scales around specific uh
communication specific message passing
and once you look at how specific
message become meaningful to specific
agents you are
you you have a problem basically because
this is subjective this is constructed
through the activity of the agent and
this is uh whatever is the
range of time you're looking at you will
have the construction of new
possibilities of adjacent possibles as
you put it
and yeah this is the this is the uh big
question that I think we are missing at
the moment in active in France
awesome well thank you for this
presentation thanks for the social
sciences work and we're all looking
forward to
seeing how the projects play out
thank you goodbye
farewell level
all right
the
next presentation
is with Pablo Fernandez machiara so
welcome back Pablo
hello
akir okay I did take us on an adventure
of curiosity
yes I'm gonna start sharing my screen
let me know if everything is all right
um
should be
perfect
yep cool
so this is one of my favorite memes and
um
and
probably most of you know it
this reference
is
um
the cave of platon
and uh
to me it was kind of a fine intuitive
truth
that now with active inference
seems like we are closer to
demonstrate that that how it is
though
the first time that I start uh act in
and surf at The Institute uh I just
this was my kind of my feeling or my
face uh was uh looking into something
that it was complex scary
and look interesting so I went and why I
decided to to go through it
um
ambition a world where people is driving
by stronger incentives that motivate
them to reduce uncertainty in the
systems they are part of and my Approach
is through games which are gonna go
later but I really on this talk want to
encourage uh all kinds of
persons or people that are curious and I
want them to
act and get involved in the community
because you may find that uh for now
most of the actors are scientists and
very well on reputed people and you
might think that you are not
a part of of it but uh very far away
from that uh The Institute encouraged uh
the opposite so I'm super glad to have
been through this journey and I wanted
to share a little bit of my background
and then we go to the game
um
here is the second and last meme uh the
world you were raised uh to survive is
no longer exist we are on a digital
Revolution and with this digital
Revolution uh it comes bunch of
different
[Music]
um
things that are evolving and hopefully
uh bring us to a better world
um okay who I am I'm Pablo my name is
Pablo but I'm more defined or well
what best defined me is my action and my
experiences
um
I think uh role game plays
um Sports and movies are super important
and asakida was uh uh dyslexic and the
system didn't feel my Necessities so I
really hated it's cool but I love
learning and it's something that I've
been doing all my life and it's curious
how a system that is designed to
give you knowledge and to
help you with the learning in my case it
didn't work at all
and and just that's a little uh
starting point uh I believe in in the
copy transformation and combine of
things and on my uh adulthood uh
everything
sifted and I became a successful
professional and I love
it teams
um
what they do for living is
a product manager and what I do on my
pet projects side projects call it as
you want uh is related to uh gaming and
gamifying
um
uh organizations and experiences
um uh nowadays I trust more my intuition
which is something that it really was
broken during my childhood and you will
see a little bit
more about that here are some things of
my interest licenses uh like open
science which is the case of the
Institute philosophy and that's the
first meme education governance family
art
um law of communication technology
and nature and a bunch of other things
that I will be happy to share any other
time
on one of the questions that Daniel
asked me for this talk is it was what
was exciting for me uh uh about all this
what right and for me I always when when
I I give talks I I like to Sir or a view
of the last hundred years and and the
Industrial Revolution and how uh the the
ones that were on this world uh before
us did something right I'm sure that we
all know uh big
mistakes or big things that have uh fail
or that could be uh better through
iterations but on data it's it's very uh
promising and and very good I I think is
um inspiring to have uh these the basic
education how it grows uh the
vaccination what it did did for us uh
democracy uh and how uh poverty drop
drastically
how literacy it it grew and because all
these uh things uh child mortality uh
just went very low
uh so basically the future of education
is what makes me be excited
um
how I ended on this ecosystem uh it's
super random and I'm gonna explain it in
hopefully two to five minutes I as a
product manager I'm very interested on
technology I heard about blockchains
back in
2015 and I didn't understood anything at
all and then back in 2017 I heard about
a stos I didn't understand them I did
not play that game but it was a racing a
fun thing
to consider which is digital assets and
ownership of those digital assets uh for
now we we did we didn't had uh a
technology that could scale and that was
good enough to ensure that the digital
assets that you own uh were you yours
and you had the freedom of transaction
uh on them I I did understand that very
fast and because I'm a game player and
as a game player you always have your
different assets and and do things with
them and as well I I I have been
collecting music
and all kind of uh digital
assets uh I bought uh this very famous
collection of uh punks and sold them
very fast before uh I Could Be A
Millionaire
but during 2021 I decided that I wanted
to build something and then back then I
went through this uh beautiful project
that was the first art show on ethereum
which one of the artists it was Daniel
uh Friedman so I as a curious person and
a person that has been working with
artists I always like to know what is
the driver of those artists uh what they
do and and try to get in their walls to
understand better and to get as much
information as as I can before I decide
to uh encourage or collect or or or just
deep deep always uh deeper on on music
or art for me is
um very nice nice thing to do so I
discovered uh these cards and education
um
was one of them and I went through uh
Flickr which is where it was the first
at least what that I found a place where
it was and the license it was a Creative
Commons license uh of not commercial use
but uh it it was an open license which I
been uh a part of uh Creative Commons
Community for a really very very long
time since I was uh uh working with
musicians and I think it's one of the
best things that happened to the
internet
um this is these are some of the
pragmatic uh uh things that uh the
audience cares about hopefully we will
have some of these on our games uh
uh AI for sure is going to be there
um
free energy principle is going to be one
of the things that hopefully we
help to minimize and to make it funnier
games or happier games or on games that
help organizations to be better
uh the human factor uh it's super
important for me an implementation an
action I learned by doing and it's one
of the values that the Institute
encouraged more so uh I just jump on
things and try to understand them
through doing and sharing as I'm doing
now
uh here are the epistemics and
um Collective uh is one of them that um
as well uh super interested
um agents of course
practical and curiosity which is the
adventure that um uh I have the feeling
that I'm being involved all my my life
and that I encourage always my
my two girls to to be curious and to
open things and look behind the doors
and just be an active here are some
values that I like to point with our
exploration uh the culture of curiosity
that I did mention a lot
um
uh continuous learning uh
because that experience on the school I
think I I just keep going and keep going
and it's something that sometimes
um bad experiences could turn out in
good habits uh learning by doing as I
already told
um
integrity and inclusivity honesty
I couldn't tell you accountability a big
one
um trying to be professional on
everything that you do
um for me I started as a human being
curious
um people of all backgrounds and
perspectives are welcome to them
to The Institute
um I could I could be very happy to be
the link and to speak with uh
someone that has doubts or if I can help
I think I could help on the very early
stage and and if you're not very
technical person I think I could help
there and and yeah
and NASA we are learning by doing I
would love to everyone that's uh that's
on the stream uh I'm gonna share this
link which is uh
a new a new game that we are testing and
I'm excited to to share it with with you
uh it's the adventure of curiosity
um here Daniel I'm gonna
be and paste the link
uh it would be awesome okay there's a
tiny typo on your slides it just ends
with a curiosity
thank you but I'm gonna I'm gonna paste
I'm gonna paste it into the YouTube live
chat
okay thank you uh yeah I told you um
dyslexic I have all kind of titles
throughout my life sorry about for that
I always try to improve it uh let's
um
okay so you sir the yeah I put it in the
YouTube chat so people can head over
there all right yeah could you tell us
about this platform and this is the
first active game
yes
[Music]
um we uh started thinking on how to do a
game a while ago and we decided to go
with this
um
uh picture that explains how it works
actually
it's simple and you have uh for pieces
the internal States external estate and
in the middle you have the sensory State
and the active state
so
here is the mission you have some
instructions that you can read and would
be fun if you go through them and you
can go either way
and here we are gonna go to the sensory
state where you're gonna listen to a
music
um
where some notes
you can
sensor that are
not in the famous song of
for release
so
you have to take notes
and
you can go
and you can see that we are on the
Markov blanket which is so everything
very
delinian
but painted
and here is your active uh part of the
game where you have to do something
which is
add the different notes that your
professor music
Professor is telling you
don't miss because you probably on the
uh
external state are
trying to play the music so you have to
infer that you are missing some notes
and
go
to
the active state
and start uh walking through the right
node
if I miss the note
I just follow the form into the nothing
and come back it into my internal state
so I probably would have to go back and
censor again
and once I take the right
actions and the right nodes I can go
and solve the
fossil and
the idea here is to have a tool
a gaming tool to explain or so you can
experience
how
this active inference on free energy
works and once you
go to the end of
that Adventure which I'm not gonna
finish because it's something that
players should do you're gonna have a
door where you have to put the sequence
in low case
of uh of what were the missing notes and
it's gonna allow you to come inside
the treasure room
where you
will have uh feedback
uh
feedback that you can send us and we
will be very happy to have it and then
if you have a wallet
you will be able to have a digital asset
if not we will add information to help
people to go from web 2 to web 3 and to
get those digital assets
and
here to be developed would be future
Adventures that I would be very happy to
do
so this was pretty much the presentation
and
hopefully
we have play new players
in the coming days
hope you have fun and I really really
encourage anyone to discover
and play with all these ideas and
thoughts and experiments and
things that I have that gut feeling that
are gonna revolutionize how we
understand
uh the world
and how we can improving it by reducing
uncertainty
so thank you
and I don't know Daniel if you have any
comments or something in this last 10
minutes oh yeah let's we can definitely
talk for a few minutes I'm I'm seeing
many fun comments and questions in the
chat so people can can post it yeah the
gameplay is smoother on even a normal
computer it just like it may look choppy
on the live stream but it's quite a nice
um playing experience like maybe just a
little context like how did you get into
building these worlds or what kind of
tools are these and we obviously don't
see them in today's mainstream
educational and research offerings but
like what could that even be to bring
together this kind of immersion and role
playing with education research
yes
um I uh uh
um we I I I I I've been playing role
games on Roll games uh you have uh very
uh diverse kind of players so I I was
playing with uh guys like me like uh
have
um
had a struggle through the school and
guys that uh end up being uh researchers
like yourself because they were very
good and and in those environments and
and and for me it it was like we are
sharing a lot of cognitive uh
um
um values and information and they are
really having fun with me so uh that
what what the Academia is telling me is
not isn't is not what I'm I'm feeling in
in the real in in outside of Academia
so that that through the years
uh it became more and more clear that
was one of the drivers to have a very
diverse kind of friends and and
and that one of the most important
things for me to learn it was having fun
and to be a good professional I have to
be enjoying what I'm doing and to enjoy
what I do it has to have that gamified
feeling of it and so in 2021 uh I I just
went to
try to explore that road
uh because blockchains what what can do
is have a persistent sea of of objects
and attribute attributions to those
objects and to those wallets that you
can add and build on top of them is like
having a huge uh database for a game
purpose and and then you figure out that
a game is uh kind of our organization so
you need rules you need to serve values
you need to uh have like uh what we are
building now which is the session
which you agree with the players what's
going to be about and how it's going to
work and and we are uh building this
um fantastic uh storytelling of how
uh kind of world where it was in the
uh early 20s
compared to what's happening now in this
imaginary world
that's
complementary to what's happening in
real life and we are just exploring
those areas for three years and once I
got into the
and to The Institute we started sharing
these ideas you
send us to do
um system thinking course that it was
super uh cool with we we explore and
learn and these uh document that I can
share it was very uh important for us to
understand and we find out the necessity
to be able to computerize what we are
doing so we'll start focusing more on
ontology on on
on all the the Brick breaks that you
need to to understand uh to build
um the skeleton of uh something that
could last
for
decades which is uh the idea and we are
trying to build it so everyone can copy
paste Fork it and do whatever they want
with the game adapted to their own
organizations and use it uh on their
favor and and we are just exploring and
having fun
that's that's awesome and there's so
many
um
the so many pieces there it's true about
the fun and the Curiosity those
intrinsic motivations
like being six hours deep into counting
ants in the desert or 5 000 pipette
pushes deep or whatever it is in the
trenches and in The Last Mile and um
it it can be easy to lose sight
but when we lose sight and when we put
out the fire and the spark
it's a cold dark night
and no career or status or
extrinsic valuation is gonna provide
like
simply the joy
and the the deeper meaning of like
two people going on a little Adventure
running around this space being inside
active inference rather than active
inference being like this high-speed
train that's leaving anyone behind or
you're on the outside and it's taking
these twists and turns and you're
getting thrown off it's like it is cool
and air-conditioned
in this space
and people
play and watch a lot of games where they
wield
violent arms and not even like saying
whether that's good or bad it just it is
a genre to want to have a camera either
in a character's head first person
perspective or a camera in a second or a
third person perspective which you can
switch between here and like those kinds
of topics about like egocentric versus
allocentric navigation and our ability
to have a a perspective swap on ourself
and be able to take that kind of like
out of body
um situational awareness in real spatial
settings
and just to be able to cruise through
this space and it's like yeah there's no
there's no right way to Boomerang from
extra you can go from external to
sensory you could go here or there
it's it's a um it's an appetizer
and uh a fertilization that like we've
really just never seen
okay yeah thank you very much Daniel
well for this
any last thoughts or comments
no just enjoy while we are here which is
I think our mission
all right thank you Pablo I'm sure
everyone's gonna really enjoy this and
let's also of course
continue to um develop these games and
continue to offer these on-rams and have
times where we're meeting up in these
spaces and playing around
thank you bye farewell
all right
welcome Mao this will be the final of
the
uh presentation sessions in the
symposium
this is Mal aberration with the
presentation shared pretensions in
active inference so thank you Mao to you
and you're the first you're the first to
join with an AI Steward slash Guardian
awesome
awesome shall I share my screen yes
Let's do let's do let's do
Advanced just a second I'm looking for a
window
I think this will do
okay so can you see the screen
Yep looks good thank you
awesome so unfortunately
I imagine that you are seeing the entire
screen and not just the presentation I
apologize about that but I got it it's
it's cropped I got it okay wonderful
thank you
all right so
welcome to the presentation on shared
Pro tension under active inference we're
going to cover a lot of topics
um should I introduce myself a little
bit
um
or have you already done that
awesome so my name is I'm a PhD student
in cognitive Computing I work in active
inference in the interaction between uh
social sciences uh philosophy
Consciousness science and artificial
intelligence
um we're going to start a presentation
on potential protection and active
inference so I'm going to define a lot
of terms it's going to deal into
um
philosophy terms that are very deep
um and so let's get started if you will
just give me one small second
and we're back
so shared retention is a term derived
from phenomenology and it refers to the
shared anticipation of future events
among a group of individuals
this philosophical study of experience
and Consciousness becomes particularly
interesting when we consider it in the
context of active inference
when we combine these two concepts we
get a powerful tool for understanding
how groups of individuals can coordinate
their actions and work towards a common
goal this is the main focus of the
discussion today so imagine
a group of people
planning a trip
they all share a common goal to have a
successful and enjoyable trip
the shared goal forms the basis of their
shared protection they all anticipate
future events related to the trip such
as booking tickets packing their bags
and visiting various attractions
as they start to take actions towards
their goal they're also engaging in
active inference they're making
predictions about what will happen next
and then adjusting these predictions
based on what actually happens so for
example they might predict at a certain
flight will be the cheapest based on
their past experiences but when they
actually check the prices they find that
another flight is cheaper
so they adjust their prediction and book
the other flight
this constant cycle of prediction and
adjustment Guided by their shared
protection helps the group coordinate
their actions and make their trip a
success
so we're going to delve deeper into the
concepts and explore the role of past
experiences known as retentions in
shaping our current knowledge and future
predictions
explain let's explain first the concept
of retentions retention is a key
component of time Consciousness that
retains the past trajectory of a
temporal object
it's the preservation of the content of
a now passed High letic datum in our
present consciousness
a high letic datum refers to the raw
uninterpreted Sensations that arise in
our consciousness
when we retain these data
we are essentially keeping a record of
past Sensations and experiences that can
inform our present and our future
actions
inactive inference we can formalize
retention by thinking of moments as
binning of states which are bounds to a
hierarchical state
this way retention is seen as the
bidding which becomes the current state
informing the next expected state
to further connect retention with active
inference we can consider the way in
which retention plays a role in updating
an agent's belief and generative model
the past experiences influence the
current expectations and actions thus
shaping the agent's understanding of the
world and the future
so let's consider a practical example to
illustrate this concept if you had a
good experience at a particular
restaurant you might choose to go there
again in the future
your past experience influences your
future decision in hustling temporal
phenomenology we would think about much
shorter time scale but if we extend this
concept we can see a much larger
structure whereing the retention is
simply the past state
it's like having a mental note that says
this place is good and this is how an
example of retention works in your
everyday life
they're not merely representation or
memories but presentations of a
temporally extended present
which distinguishes them from
Recollections this involves the
presentation of some already constituted
content in conscious experience
retentions also play a crucial role in
mapping past knowledge onto current
beliefs contributing contributing to the
development of shared narratives or
goals that we will delve into in the
rest of the presentation
they can be former now points and the
current awareness of the past and far
sedimented retentions can be engraved in
scripts or deep temporal priors or more
fluid deontic cues
this phenomenon corresponds to a
specific application of message passing
between agents in the present moment and
in the sensorium
retentions and protections may also
emerge jointly within a group
forming a collective understanding that
transcends individual perspectives
protentions as we saw
refer to the anticipation of future
events based on past experiences and
current knowledge
it's thus forward look it's the
forward-looking counterpart to retention
which is backward looking
protection is the anticipation of future
trajectories of a temporal object
it's the process of looking ahead
predicting what's to come based on what
has been and what currently is
so in active inference it could be
formalized by considering the future
states that are expected based on the
current state and past States
pretension is thus the anticipation
guiding the next action
you can consider the way in which
protention plays a role in updating an
agent's beliefs and generative models
influencing the actions and thus shaping
the agent's understanding of the world
ends the future
so for instance if you see dark clouds
in the sky you might anticipate that
it's going to rain and decide to carry
an umbrella this anticipation of future
events is protention it's also going to
determine whether or not you're wet when
you go outside and therefore whether or
not you expect to be wet
your brain is constantly making
predictions about what's going to happen
next
so let's put this in the context of
temporal flow
which ties together those concepts of
Primal Impressions that we will see
retention and retention
together
temporal flow is the structure that
represents the continuous progression of
time from the past through the present
and into the future
agents are constantly revising their
generative models and they do this by
integrating the observations which we
could refer to here as Primal
impressions
this updating process is a balancing act
between maintaining the predictive
density of the agent's current beliefs
and adapting to new information
retentions and protection structure time
for a given agent creating a framework
that shapes their perception and
anticipation
different agents or systems will exhibit
varying qualities and quantities of
retention and protection which resembles
something like Mike Levin's concept of
cognitive light comes so given the
presence of retention we can anticipate
a potential Horizon
not merely as an arbitrary expectation
students are thus the point at which
agents beliefs about the world are
updated to match their current
observations
which leads to a more accurate
understanding of the environment and
allows for more effective goal-directed
Behavior
Primal impressions are the Fulfillment
of a protention which is the time-bound
Nexus of perception and existence
is it is resolved sorry it is the result
probability that redefines the local
radiant
it's in Primal impression that reality
collapses
the Primal impression is thus mode
modeled as the essential Bayesian
cognitive moment
it is the juxtaposition of Prior beliefs
or retentions
with ongoing sensory information in an
unfolding future oriented present
retention
so now we have a description of temporal
thickness from the nominology which is
compatible with generative modeling in
active reference agents
for hustle this flow of conscious
experience is primarily made up of
Sensations that dwell up in a raw
uninterpreted form that we called
earlier highlighting data
so this data is the now phase of a
temporal object it is formatted
according to the eidetic or cognitive
laws of consciousness
this is specifically relative to Inner
time
you can understand how temporal temporal
flow structures how agents are able to
make choices act to self-evidence
connect the passive structure with the
active component of decision making or
goal Pursuit
individuals have drives and teleology
insofar as they have preferences
these preferences are protented goals
reach towards by what we would call
potentially the Fiat
where in the Fiat constitute the willed
act towards a desire
so the Fulfillment of retention by Fiat
drives the agent towards the teleology
across a trail set
in a retentional extension
more information is a matter so the
longer your retention more information
can be caught in a moment
as individuals of mass enough
information they can then find a
structure to the information which
becomes a map rather than a territory
and it's computationally more efficient
than the sum of all the information
amongst
this new state of information may lead
individuals closer to a shared goal the
information of mass turns into an
emergent whole of the retention which
grabs focus at the present moment
because it seems to bring signals to the
model that the potential role is closer
in its competition is simpler to retain
so sharing of retentions and protections
among group members any social context
can facilitate coordination and the
achievement of a shared goal
by aligning their beliefs about the past
or retentions and expectations about the
future or pretensions group members can
better predict each other's actions and
intentions
this allows them to work together more
effectively
in some cases group members may have
retentions and protections that align
naturally due to Common experiences or
understanding
even without active communication
however group members often actively
communicate their retentions and
protentions aligning their beliefs and
expectations through dialogue and
interaction
thereby
enhancing their ability to predict each
other's actions and interactions
retentions and protections may also
emerge jointly within the group not
confined to any individual agents umvelt
forming a collective understanding that
transcends individual perspectives
this complex interplay of individual and
Collective Dynamics can be explored
further in hierarchical generative
models encompassing resonant cognitive
models communication and even joint
emergence
the structure of time Consciousness
encapsulated in retention and protection
thus plays a significant role in the
emergence of shared potentials
as agents retain and process similar
elements from their environment they can
co-compute share protections by mapping
each other's cognitive Pathways and
building upon one another's trails
this process is formalized by Bayesian
updating
um
the relationship between the topology of
protensions and the expectation gradient
as well as the role of retention in
mapping past knowledge on the current
beliefs plays a role in development of
shared narratives and goals
we can use this to get a deeper insight
into the processes that drive the
emergence of collective Behavior and the
development of shared understanding
among agents
there's no better way to do it than
using active inference by extending
generative models of individual agents
to account for the beliefs and goals of
other agents
this is the kin2 theory of mind it
enables them to anticipate and adapt to
the actions of their peers by offloading
to the group
so
we discussed her little bit earlier
shared goals
potential goals are future oriented
objectives that individuals or groups
strive to achieve
they're not just mere desires but
they're actively pursued through the act
of will that we called earlier Fiat
the Fulfillment of a protention drives
the agent towards a teleology that trail
set we discussed
of a prediction entails less surprised
and therefore the agent's self-evidences
by seeking to accurately predict their
surroundings
agents select a series of actions or
policies which generate transitions
between states that produce expected
observations so through the choice of
policy an individual can reach their
protented goal by minimizing the
expected free energy that a given policy
affords them this seems pretty Central
and simple in terms of active inference
so further protections are represented
by the policies of longer time depth
in a hierarchical model this corresponds
to a policy tied to a higher level
action in a slower time scale
the choice of policies driven by the
expected free energy of that higher
order policy or the entire multi-scale
generative model is based on the agent's
preferences allowing an agent to conduct
gold directed behaviors across temporal
scales
so this is where we can cash out
um Jeff yoshimi's Trail sets where
agents assimilate actions into the
anticipated continuity of objects in
their surrounding world
this is the simulation
ensures a smoother understanding of the
environment and helps agents adapt
effectively near protensions act as the
near present contextual proximity and
the far pretensions rely on passive
synthesis of deontic cues which are
sedimented retentions in the environment
the preferences of the agents aligned by
policies correspond to attracting sets
which in the socio-cognitive setting can
be instantiated as narratives having
shared narrative is a necessary aspect
of any exchange between artifacts people
institutions that have some kind of
attracting set
generalized synchrony which we will
discuss a little bit later as well
so a team working on a project has a
potential goal to complete the project
successfully
the shared narrative might be the
project plan that guides their actions
it's like everyone in the team has a
shared story about what they're trying
to achieve and how they're going to do
it
the relationship between current states
and future observations is captured
within the B Matrix transitions
this Matrix represents the probability
of transitioning to a new state based on
the current state so the B Matrix
transition
and the a matrix is utilized to
determine which new observations is most
likely to occur given the current state
and potential transitions
in the Australian framework the
expectation gradient structure plays a
crucial role in defining the depth and
fulfillment of pretensions
the structure represents the varying
degrees of certainty and confidence
agents have in their predictions about
future States
the topology thus is inter and the
arrangement is interrelation sorry or
there is an interrelation between the
protentions or the arrangements of
future expectations which is
proportional to the expectation gradient
the higher the gradient the more
detailed and accurate the pretensions
are likely to be
the potential Horizon represents the
static states of the expected futures of
the temporal object while the
continuation Horizon is The Amalgamated
Trail of the temporal object
potential and continuation Horizons are
carried in protentions while the
imminent Horizon consists of the Primal
impressions
so agents can coordinate through
co-construction where agents or
individuals interact and collaborate to
build this shared understanding and
shared goals
this process is deeply interconnected
within a complex web where agents
typically coexist with other agents or
subjects
forming the collective often referred to
as multi-aging groups swarm ensembles or
sandwich
by aligning their beliefs to the signal
found within their Niche they can better
adapt to the environment and develop a
shared understanding of their
surroundings
sharing information with other agents is
beneficial as it allows them to trust
one another and pull their resources
this collaborative approach is
preferable to a conflict-driven scenario
in which every other agent is perceived
as a potential source of risk and
surprising
by sharing information agents could
collectively construct a more accurate
representation of their environment
leading to more effective decision
making and action
through these interactions shared
narratives and goals can emerge from a
co-construction of the world and each
agent's generative model
so these narratives and goals are the
result of dynamic process that in fact
can be mathematically modeled through
the equations that we introduce in the
paper that is that this presentation is
based on but that I will present a
little bit later
they capture the process of mutual
learning where agents adapt their
generative model based on the
information gathered from their
interactions with others
agents may start off with slightly or
greatly Divergent generative model so in
order to minimize surprise there will be
a natural alignment within a group as
agents adapt to the evolving dynamics of
their environment and social contexts
for example again consider this team
working on the project
even if you have your own understanding
of the model or of the project you'll
interact and share information and learn
from each other and then adapt the model
over time you'll develop a shared
understanding of the project and a
shared goal for its completion
this is an instance of co-construction
it's like building a house together
where everyone contributes to the final
structure
the emergence of shared narratives and
the learning and recognition of them may
be made more efficient through certain
mechanisms such as language
in an experiment uh Illustrated uh in a
paper that um Carl was on
um two agents share the same sensorium
ask each other's questions I think it's
a paper on 20 questions and Emma homes
um with a shared narrative entailing a
Common Language
this illustrates The Marked efficiency
and the minimization of free energy
simply by having a shared language a
common ground
so shared protections are common future
anticipations or goals that emerge among
groups of individuals through
co-construction
it allows them to better anticipate each
other's actions and intentions and work
towards a common goal
it's strongly tied to the conscious
efforts of individuals to work towards
that goal
and to effectively create an
organizational structures where we're
engaged in a conversation in an exchange
assuming that this exchange is meant to
align our regenerative models
so think of for instance the football
team
again they have a shared pretension to
win the match they anticipate each
other's moves and adapt their strategies
based on the ongoing game
everyone in the team has a shared vision
of Victory and they're constantly
adjusting their actions to make it
happen
so individuals infer each other's mental
states by observing cues which they can
attribute to hidden causes they use
their own model of or models that they
have largely recognized about others
this process is known as generalized
synchrony entailing Mutual
predictability and can be interpreted as
a collective minimization of free energy
in a group setting individuals create
cues in the world the direct other
agents attentions towards the same
signals their models of the world align
by sharing similar goals and similar
environments and by reinforcing patterns
of sampling reality
so we could we could try to represent
this through polynomials
um and morphisms each agent's
interaction with the environment
corresponds to amorphism and the
collective interaction of all agents can
be represented as a polynomial
so
amorphism so if a polynomial p is
defined uh morphism between two
polynomials p and Q consists of a pair
of functions f and g such that F Maps P
of 1 to Q of one
and G Maps P of I to Q of the quantity
one this morphism must satisfy the
commutative of the requirements meaning
that the following diagram commutes
T of one a p of I maps to Q the quantity
I and po1 maps to Q of one
so we can see how we could create a
framework to further explore the
cooperative and competitive Dynamics
among agents for multiple agents indexed
by I with boundaries p and share
environment boundary Q their interaction
can represent can be represented by a
morphism of polynomials which allows us
to understand the shared protection in
multi-agent systems and provide the
foundation for further exploration of
Cooperative Dynamics
we allow each agent to predict not only
its own behavior but also the behavior
of its Companions and the environment's
response to their actions
so the Dynamics of shared predictions
are really useful here and can be
properly cashed out mathematically
so recursive cognition and prediction on
the shared environment of the agent's
actions and response to each other's
actions
we can use sheep theoretic and topless
theoretic approaches to understand
multi-agent systems a multi-agent system
is a system where multiple individuals
or entities interact so for example a
traffic system can be considered a
multi-agent system or different vehicles
or interact
but topos is a category that has both
spatial and logical structure allowing
for the expression of logical
propositions and deductions within it so
we can use these approaches to construct
a coherent understanding of the world
from the perspective of multiple agents
the internal Universe of Agents which
can be seen as mathematical objects
containing beliefs perceptions and
predictions of individual agents are
represented using topoi
these internal universes provide a
foundation for understanding and
representing the complex interactions
and shared understanding among multiple
agents in this Dynamic environment
we try to construct a consensus topos by
patching together the internal universes
or topoi of multiple agents and the idea
is to use the chief theoretic and topos
theoretic structures to build a shared
understanding
so we can thus derive the
synchronization of goal oriented actions
among agents over time and leverage
mathematical insights for category
Theory and generalized generative models
this connection is the mechanism through
which the group synchronizes over time
and ultimately achieves their objective
agents with the system might possess
varying levels of certainty in achieving
the objective some may choose to expand
less energy temporarily decelerating
their progress towards the desired
outcome this variation in certainty and
approach leads to the emergence of
different roles within a group with some
agents focusing on computational tasks
while other monitor outcomes are engaged
in different actions in themselves
the nested and distributed structure of
generative models in active inference
allows for the integration of both
short-term and long-term goals agents
with similar or compatible preferences
can coordinate their actions by aligning
their policies and working towards
common narratives
so this alignment reduces the overall
expected free energy of their joint
actions increasing the likelihood of
achieving shared goals and facilitating
and sharing of goals and expectations
among group members
they can learn which allows them to
learn essential role in shaping agents
preferences and strategies over time
agents can gather new experiences and
update their generative model they
refine their preferences and methods for
achieving goals they can influence the
formation and modification of shared
narratives by having different
perspective over different parts of a
goal
here the the concept of General Life
synchrony is manifested when all agents
have learned compatible or harmonized
aspects of the overall generative model
the synchronization is rooted in the
retentional and potential dynamics of
agents and can be more accurately
described using mathematical models
so in conclusion
which I just shed light on the concept
of shared potential goals and
multi-agent systems we've emphasized the
importance of understanding this concept
as it plays a crucial in the
coordination synchronization of Agents
actions and intentions
in the future continuously highlight the
role of cues in the environment and how
they can be simple like marks on the
road or more complex like symbols and
language
the cues become carriers of passive
synthesis fire protections and far
retention and become wasted minimize
free energy as they minimize the amount
of any individual has to compute
it also allows us to delve into the
concept of other evidencing in which the
environment is in effect the self and
others must learn to navigate in terms
navigate in terms of others and self
we've provided mathematical models to an
equation standardized dynamics of shared
protections more accurately in terms of
category Theory
we've explored the Dynamics of shared
retentions and retention in hierarchical
generative models which reflect the
complex interplay of individuals and
Collective Dynamics
we've encapsulated the structure of time
Consciousness and how that this allows
agents to co-compute sharep retentions
by mapping each other's cognitive
pathways
so our approach basically begins an
examination of Hospital temporal
phenomenology integrated with the
hierarchical active inference model
polynomial morphisms and home
polynomials this enables recursive
cognition and prediction of not only an
agent's actions but also the
environment's response to these actions
so I think this comes to the end Daniel
I think I'm literally at 30 minutes
thank you
impeccable thank you Mao
yeah great uh presentation awesome topic
so
thank you for joining and looking
forward to seeing how the work continues
to develop
all right
farewell now see you you must come soon
see you all right
okay
all right
the next session is going to be the
final session of
this symposium
it's been a really
Incredible Journey
and I think this final session is going
to be great as well
so
we have a whole panel here
and
people can use their cameras even though
I'm not if they want to
um
welcome everyone
all just introduce the facilitator Kurt
J mungle so Kurt is a a legend in the
active ecosystem and has done incredible
work with a variety of researchers and
curious individuals in the space so we
could think of no one better
to host this conversation
and
bring it all together so Kurt I'll pass
it to you
you'll keep an eye on the live chat
anyone can call it if they need any
supports otherwise thanks everybody for
joining and uh
we don't see you yet Kurt but yeah I it
would it be all right if I left and then
came right back for whatever reason my
camera is not working sounds good sounds
good okay I'll be right back in about 25
seconds
well welcome everyone
um
we will get started in just a second
[Music]
so odd I apologize for that okay well
you can hear my voice at least
yep
just give me a moment
address
boy okay
well
well we'll do what we can okay
so you all can't see me but
that's all right so we have this
All-Star panel here today which to me
means my invitation must have been a
mistake but I'll take it thank you to
the active inference Institute and I'll
go around this virtual Zoom table and
introduce everyone briefly
Carl friston is the welcome principal
research fellow and scientific director
at the welcome trust Center for
neuroimaging and professor of Neurology
and University College London he's also
the chief scientist at versus
Anna Lemke
is chief of the Stanford addiction
medical sorry medicine dual diagnosis
clinic at Stanford University her
popular books include drug dealer MD and
dopamine Nation
Raphael Kaufman is CTO of digital Gaia
and the onboard sorry and is on the
board of directors of the active insta
active inference Institute
Bert DeVries is a professor
at einhoven University of Technology
where he directs the bias slab research
team and also works with industry
is an associate professor in
computational Psychiatry of the faculty
of medicine at the University of
Montreal and the director
of the Precision Psychiatry and social
physiology laboratory in Chu Saint sorry
in the chu St Justine Research Center
he's also affiliated with Mila or Mila
which is Quebec's artificial
intelligence Institute and other art
science and Consciousness service
initiatives my name is Kurt jamungal and
I use them I use my background in
mathematical physics to analyze various
theories of everything that are proposed
these include both the theoretical
physics side of grand unification with
gravity and dualities other schemes as
well as attempting to understand what
constitutes Consciousness you can find
the podcast by typing in theories of
everything onto YouTube or whatever
podcast catcher you have
so my question to everyone the initial
question is what have you been working
on in the past few months and what
excites you about it
we'll start with
Bert you seem to be smiling
and your name sounds like mine
foreign
okay so
um all right so my name is and uh yeah I
lead a lab in uh in an electrical
engineering department
and uh so our lab is called by flat as
you as you mentioned so we are
interested in Bayesian inference in in
general but more specifically in doing
it as fast as possible that that has
lots of applications outside active
inference also in yeah for Signal
processing and other control systems but
definitely of course also for active
inference so have our work over the past
few months but even over the past few
years has been on developing a toolbox
to support or to get as far as we can go
with trying to do real-time basing
inference or real-time free energy
minimization and and trying it in
applications
um so that's
that's the work that I try to lead a
team of PhD students who do the real
work of course I walk around with a cup
of coffee but uh that's what they have
been working on
great and Professor Lemke please
yeah well what I've been working on in
the last
um I don't know a year or so is spending
a lot of time thinking about
how it is that a faith framework in
particular surrendered to a higher power
improves people's lives
and I've been really struggling to come
up with a way of talking about this that
is inclusive thinking about it talking
about it it gets to a kind of core piece
of it that I'm interested in which is
not so much whether or not God exists
and what the proof is or not of whether
God exists but really what what is it
that changes in people's lives when they
undergo a spiritual transformation when
they surrender to a higher power
why why do their lives get better when
they do get better
and um I'm really new to the active
inference World Daniel Friedman is the
one who's introduced me to these ideas
I'm really excited about the ways in
which the whole active inference model
might help me at least think about
what's going on there and um so so
that's what I'm that's what I'm working
on it's a little weird but uh that's
what I'm interested in
great professor friston
you're muted
yes that's going to be the title of my
next book Carl you're on mute
a retro from here
possibly the future
um I I generally work on what I'm told
to work on so I'm just been trying to
list what I've been working on
um in the past few months interestingly
um it actually starts with um Daniel
Friedman and his um fascination with um
along with Axel constant for
evolutionary explanations and speak to
him in the scale of three issues that
we've been hearing about
um in the prior session and so that's
what I was working on really a
scale-free approach to understanding
temporary nested processes as free
energy minimizing processes as a kind of
active inference and how that would lead
to a variational synthesis of evolution
and then I was told to work on belief
sharing by Mao and colleagues versus
um and um
worked on that in the context of
synthetic language and try to
um
establish a really simple proof of
principle that communication was an
emergent property of any free Ensemble
free energy minimizing system
[Music]
um and the just Open brackets is to make
the observation it struck me time and
time again uh during the session today
how important communication is
um you know whether we're talking about
birds passing messages or responding to
uh you know you've got a new posterior
or we're talking about the kind of
communication
um that Mal was talking about Well
everybody's been talking about it
doesn't seem to be a really uh and
indeed the guy the guy
um notion of over connectivity and too
much communication or the wrong kind of
communication
um it does strike me that's quite
Central uh to a lot to the both the
theme of the um the workshop
um and
um the specific presentations that we've
heard
um and then uh in the past few weeks
working on stuff I think that Bert would
be um more interested in which is
um fast and Frugal
um message passing schemes that
um enable the evaluation the expected
free energy not to suffer from uh the
limitations imposed by Deep tree
searches so
um possibly uh Ashwin has spoke about
this earlier on but um you're using
ideas from dynamic programming backwards
induction to try and
um take the pressure off the message
passing to get fast and efficient uh
evaluations of the expected free energy
in sort of um sort of single unit uh
sort of single agent uh active inference
what have I been doing this week
can't remember no that's what I've been
doing
great Raphael Kaufman please
just a moment
and can everyone else hear
okay
what about now yeah great yeah thanks uh
and it's contagious I think uh no so
I've also been drinking a lot of coffee
as I've been caring for my now nine
month old daughter
so uh congratulations thank you so aside
from Steve deprivation what I've been
doing is
um uh I told you guys about this in the
in the session earlier today but uh in a
nutshell been working on what we call
the the the guy protocol uh or the guy
Network which is this uh this
um open approach for for building a uh
common uh common engine you can think of
it as a common runtime and uh in a
common uh language for with the building
blocks of of shared decision making
um and
um in the context of on the Mad crisis
and getting to getting to a set of of
building blocks for decision making that
don't kill us all so that's that's kind
of it
Rafael how many how much coffee is a lot
of coffee
well it's espresso so I don't think it's
quite comparable to like American coffee
all right
and Guillaume Dumas please
yes sure can you hear me
yes
okay uh so in the context of action
inference uh I have mostly focused on uh
well the two big topic of my lab so uh
Precision Psychiatry and social
physiology so on the Precision
Psychiatry side uh
presented earlier in this Symposium uh
work on trying to model theory of mind
to being able to evaluate through
digital phenotyping the level of
sophistication of interaction in
patients with neurodevelopmental
disorders
and that connect with also our interest
in the social mind and how we can
connect our understanding of
how we deal with other people but with
also ourselves and so that connect with
other work at the Mila with the Deep
learning architecture with ir order
functioning humans uh where we're trying
to combine different theories of
Consciousness such as Global law
workspace and attention schema Theory
and in the context of attention schema
Theory there is this kind of recycling
of self and other mechanisms so that's
one
big work and on the other side I'm very
interested also in uh military agent
systems and so with the Natalie Castle
we're going to join us uh soon we've
been working on creativity and the
emergence of cultural norms in
meditation systems with the idea of
applying that to climate action and also
a new project that is starting here with
the an frf of a big Canadian project on
indigenous knowledge and how we can
think about new narrative around Ai and
typically a less solipsistic
individualistic way of dealing with AI
so that's the two main uh field of
research
can you explain what you mean by less
solipsistic lessons
oh geez Louise
the
the Californian view of AI because the
narrative is mainly driven by uh us and
California right now tends to circle
around optimization profits I mean even
open AI states that AGI is about
optimizing profitable human tasks they
put like a profitable in their
definitions
in the case of indigenous systems of
knowledge we are more talking about
Community
sustainability
and the view already only in the
application is less individualistic but
also in the cognitive science point of
view we we have like the the outcore
computationalism that would say the
brain is just like a computer in a very
restrictive sense and so AI like
typically the those Transformers that
are massively used right now
are kind of like bringing that in a very
silicon sense while we are an embodied
systems that are
constituted by our interaction with
others and so like in a way how we can
think about artificial intelligence in
this kind of more co-constitutive way
and through a Developmental and cultural
lens
mm-hmm
okay now speaking of the brand as a
computer we frequently frequently hear
in these circles the brain as a
predictive machine
so where does this the quote-unquote
brain as a predictive machine have its
limits
and also is that to be interpreted as
implying conscious experience is a
predictive machine as well okay and if
not why not so
I think Carl you'd be a great person to
start this off and then we'll go around
the table again
yeah I'm just mindful of Mao's
presentation the past half hour
um and a notion of temporal thickness
um and I'm sure that's got a lot to do
with the necessary conditions for the
kind of Consciousness and guessing
you're referring to you know that
freedom from the moment
um and if one reads prediction in its
sort of psychological or pretensive or
pretension um
um nature in terms of being able to
predict what will happen in the future I
think that the um
that's that that's going to be a sort of
uh a key bright line between things that
um do not possess
certain kind of um bentians and things
that do
um and that bright line just rests
basically upon
um well from perspective of active
infants having a generative model that
includes the consequences of your own
actions in the future so just by having
consequences you're now talking about
um the future and the cause the
consequences
um in the future now become random
variables therefore you have to infer
them which leads you directly to the
notion of planning as inference which
means that bright lie is just the
difference between things that plan and
do not plan
um and
um I would guess that that's where you
probably want to start in terms of
foregrounding the role of prediction
um as being
an aspect of self-organization and its
sort of reading under active inference
that characterizes just things from
non-conscious things namely the ability
to plan does that make sense
I have follow-up questions we'll get to
them at some point but for now Anna Do
you have do you have any comments on
that and and Bert as well afterward
um well you know I'm I'm new to this
field so I'm just familiarizing myself
even with the language but I I can
respond to of the question the brain is
a predictive machine in terms of
the work that I do clinically in the
kind of Psychopathology that I see when
I'm working with patients
um you know we I work primarily with
narrative the stories that they tell
about their lives and one of the
recurring themes I've seen through my
work is that when patients tell stories
in which they are perpetually the
victims of other people's actions of the
world they tend to then that tends to be
a predictive model for them so that they
will then go out into the world and
unconsciously create scenarios which
will perpetuate their victimhood and
that part of getting into Wellness is to
stop seeing themselves as entirely the
victim of other people or circumstance
instead begin to appreciate what they
contribute to their life problems so I
guess when I think of the limits of the
brain as a predictive machine I think in
some ways one of the big limits is that
it's a very powerful predictive machine
that actually allows us to subsequently
shape what actually happens to us and or
our perceptions of what happens to us
which then can perpetuate
a false narrative and I I'll just give
one small example from my own life I've
had um you know my conflicts with my
mother and one of my beefs about her is
that she's a very poor communicator and
that whenever I email her I either get a
cryptic response or no response at all
and it drives me crazy and about five
years ago she sent an email asked me
some questions I wrote her back and
responded and it was clear to me that
that required yet a response from her
which I never got and that then
perpetuated my narrative about her as a
very poor communicator and many other
negative things and then about three
months after I sent that email I found
the email in my draft inbox in my draft
box so I had never actually responded to
through his email I hadn't actually sent
the email and that was for me um just a
you know a personal uh wonderful example
of the ways in which we can our actions
can actually
um
be manipulated to support our models and
perpetuate falsehoods about the world
that we live in
right and I I have a quick question Bert
just for Anna before we get to you so
use the word narrative there how are you
defining the word narrative is it the
same as model is it a sequence of events
like what is the specific definition of
narrative
you know I never really thought about it
in those terms but when I talk about
narrative I'm talking about
um
the stories that people tell about their
lives because that's sort of my data
um and and also about models because
what I've discovered about
self-narrative is it's not just a way to
organize the past it also becomes a road
map for the future that's the language
that I use but I see it Maps very nicely
onto ural's language of modeling the
world
I see Professor DeVries please
um yeah it's it's clear that uh the
ability to predict is is the essence of
talented decision making
um yeah I have a different background
right I'm not a psychiatrist so I think
about these things in different really
the thing that that I think about when I
think about prediction is I I would
assume that it brain predicts far ahead
but things get less accurate right if I
predict that I want to go three quarters
around around about I don't care about
the centimeter where my car goes when
I'm around here I just want to get in in
the right lane
um and I would assume that the brain
doesn't take much it takes less
computations if you care about things
less precisely but that's very hard in a
computer we have this is what uh kind of
kills Us in uh in in I think in our
current uh way of implementing active
inference when we want to predict a deep
hat we don't care about the accuracy but
we don't know how to do it much cheaper
when things are less accurate and so
that's still a that's a problem that we
that need to be working on
um it might be in
it might be a key to building or to
scaling up active Entrance Agency if we
can actually
compute messages that we want to know
that we don't care about if they are
less precise that we also spend much
less computational there
thank you now Professor Kaufman
uh I am not a professor but I'll answer
anyway
um can you just call me Rafa uh yeah so
uh there's uh so many really interesting
Avenues here and it's not often that I
get the the the pleasure of discussing
this kind of stuff with
this uh kind of diverse crowd but I do I
mean I've been interested in uh in these
questions uh for for a pretty long time
and I I think what comes to mind is like
how
how active inference has a lens uh for
instance it enables us to to to to
get another sense of what non-dualist
views on Consciousness uh or saying when
they when they uh get us experientially
to to notice the difference between what
we actually perceive and what
between the different various different
uh uh processes or things that are going
on in our in our head and our tendency
to like want them all together into the
same okay this is this is my this is my
experience that that I'm immersed in
um so noticing being able to to to uh
notice the difference between the the
the the the the process of perceiving an
act and and acting and that's what it's
automated and the narrative where the
various narratives that are going on uh
uh in parallel to my head whether I'm
aware of them or not and uh and our
ability to to to just put kind of
seemingly arbitrary manner levels on top
of it to to try to make sense of it all
into to force uh for static experience
of having multiple Americans and
multiple framings going on at the same
time makes uh make sense of that
experience you know in a
um
in a way that aligns with our physical
positions about about how things are so
um I I think that's super interesting
and also I also I like that uh like this
this view of Consciousness as being kind
of uh defined by having a narrative or
an internal model that's about self or
that at least uh it's about self and
that leads us as Carl said to the
blindness inference uh that's actually
like super deflationary in a way that
that people are not uh not used to
thinking about it and uh and so it's an
exciting it's opening the doors all the
sort of exciting interdisciplinary
conversations we had on the basis of at
least I feel like better uh less talking
past each other than we've ever had so
I'm excited about that
Aaron how is it that you're using the
word deflationary there Carl I know but
I asked you about that when we had our
podcast together but Raphael a similar
question so you said deflationary view
when we have narratives of self do you
mean it leads us to something that
Consciousness is much more than
sorry much yeah yeah I mean it's uh not
necessarily much less than in the in the
uh subjective sense but it's much much
less than in the in the scientific sense
so uh one example of like one not saying
exactly that but but maybe something
close to what uh Daniel Bennett calls
heterophenology which is basically the
the statement that the the sum of what
one can say scientifically about
Consciousness is is
um is equal to what can be can be uh
what can be studied and uh and modeled
and theorized and communicated and learn
and uh agreed upon on the basis of
objective data about what people
including you but they're also other
people say uh about their experience
which and of course like what can be
measured up neural correlates and
whatever which is not the same as are
not necessarily the same as our
experience so our direct what we think
is our direct experience of being
conscious content right so one way to
look at it is that uh uh is that the
science of Consciousness doesn't
necessarily have to put the privacy on
on people the purpose people think they
have qualia
uh that that we thought and that tends
to this deflationary right it's
um yeah you have to explain why people
believe they have quality or not white
people have quality because it's not
it's not necessarily a scientific truth
that people have quality right
Professor Dumas
uh yeah so well on the limits of Brands
break you mentioned well which we should
be always careful to not move from uh
one uh
map territory fallacy to another ones
for sure so we need to be uh Skeptics
and avoid to refine the methods and well
the this world Symposium show our this
metaphor is super useful and and
fruitful but I can see like two main uh
limits or at least things where we
should be careful so uh following what
uh Professor Lemke said like in
Psychiatry I think the the looping
effects and the way people picture
themselves uh can be uh very
unpredictable and so the the way uh we
think about the brain as a predictive
machine I think prediction for patients
would have different signification of
what we mean by predictive machines in
the context of factory inference and in
general also like uh the I I can see
that certain uh psychologists or
anthropologists would have a big Appeal
on a sudden for uh active inference and
prenergic principles but taking the the
words uh as uh directly what they think
the word mean where it needs to be we
need to be careful the way to
communicate it and typically Following
also what Professor debris said about uh
predict prediction as being super
important for decision making I think
like
we should be careful about the the
weirdness of uh cognitive science and
how it doesn't necessarily expand to uh
non-western educated industrialized
country where maybe the cultural value
is not about optimization of your
decision making or your profit and so
that's the first thing where I think we
should be careful it's more like a
matter of how to communicate the theory
in that case not necessarily a limit of
the theory itself the the second one is
uh
that the equivalence or not
with other Frameworks so like uh
I can see uh we are the Mao uh talking
about category Theory and I'm very
curious about right now among the
different Frameworks that are out there
how can we Define what is equivalent or
not with actually inference to be able
to to see those limits uh maybe we are
leaving what happened with quantum
mechanics in the in the early uh 20th
century with different interpretation
with different tools to model quantum
mechanics and air with artificial
intelligence and cognitive Neuroscience
we have also all those Frameworks and I
think the limitation would be then to
not take this interpretation as the only
one but uh try to have a crosstalk and a
differential diagnosis of which one is
the best for explaining what
okay now my role is the moderator but I
would like you all to to speak to one
another so I'm going to ask a question
that will serve us well you each will
speak on it but as the other person is
speaking as sorry as the other people
are speaking just think okay is there a
question that I have or is there a
comment that I have so the question is
what are some of the recent advancements
or breakthroughs in your respective
fields that you find particularly
promising
and well recent let's say
2020 until now
so we'll start off with Raphael you're
smiling and you look like a champion oh
I was thinking what is my field right
because
uh we're very much in the in the
um in the last mile of applying the the
wonderful stuff that y'all come up with
and uh and uh making it uh useful on the
ground but so I'm I'm extraordinarily
excited about research like what uh what
Bert is doing and uh uh I feel like
as uh as you almost saying we're also
starting to see some some convergence on
uh on different
um different ways to get to to the same
uh at least the same shape of answers
and in some cases even to the same
um the same uh results so one example of
this is uh work that uh
um Chris Chris Fields Carl and others
have been doing on uh on the quantum uh
uh
basically explaining Quantum information
Theory uh and uh and how it relates to
to to the free energy principle looking
at the free energy Principle as the as
the classical limit of of quantum
information Theory and I don't pretend
to to understand all of it but as
somebody who has who is coming from a
quantum physics background uh just uh uh
being alive to see this this kind of
conversions happening which as I mean as
as uh as Kion said you know we've been
at this at this business of like both
classical what's what the hell is going
on for over a century now and it's nice
to to be at a time where again we're
we're starting to talk less about each
other
and that's that's from a periodical
perspective from a practical perspective
I think just uh just finding that we
have all the building blocks to to
uh create
uh fast interpretable
um
um reliable and aligned
um decision making systems which
includes uh AI systems autonomous
systems that have all those
characteristics and that it turns out
that all the things that the
reinforcement learning and uh and the
neural networks people thought were very
hard or impossible are sort of in the
realm of what we can do uh looking at
things from an active inference lens and
vice versa a lot of things that that
that
active influence models have
Incorporated so far so it turns out if
you if you toss in a neural network
approximator here
um and um you know some borrow some
other you know massively parallel
computation techniques uh it also
becomes feasible so it's it's converging
yeah for me it's
what's remarkable is that there's so
many domains of of what we thought was
exclusively human or would be
exclusively human for decades that in
just the past couple years
robots or computers seem to be
just as good if not exceeding us
and I don't know if that's promising or
worrisome but anyhow Carl please if you
don't mind answering the question and
then we'll go Anna then Bert and then
Dumas
well actually just reflecting upon your
um
one of your observations I think it's
very difficult to identify one thing uh
you know in a sense
um
what is impressive is the diversity of
advances and applications
um and I just say that because that's
what I was thinking you know over the
past six hours is listening to your
amazing presentation after the
presentation and just you know noting
how diverse yeah and yet there's this
Common Thread this common commitment uh
basically say to your curiosity and and
using the the tools that naturalize that
kind of sense making curious behavior
and communication
um that inherit from sort of either
maths or category Theory or as rough
notes now Quantum information Theory but
just to pick up on a couple of things
which arrive into this conversation so
the work with Chris Fields um you know
it sounds
um lovely and exciting to bring quantum
mechanics into
um active inference but that's not the
move that I think Chris has um really
wanting to Champion the move I think is
something that we've all been addressing
in one way or another which is
um leveraging the scale-free aspects of
these this principled
approach to self-organization and
hopefully self-organization to some kind
of generalized synchrony
um so that that's where the quantum
information Theory gets into the game it
is scale free and indeed he will go
further and say it's completely
background for free and everything is
constructed it's just uh so I think that
that's a lovely move
um because once you've gone skill free
you then start to ask deep questions
about how you coupled one scale to
another scale and in a sense ecosystems
is just that how do the your the
denizens of an ecosystem
um how things that constitute how is it
co-constructed what is the structure of
it these are all questions about how one
scale links to another skill so I think
there have been lots of advances in that
direction in many many different fronts
um and you can read that either in terms
of coupling difference of spatial or
um yeah spatial scales
um but probably more importantly sort of
temporal scales and you see that yeah
wherever you look
um you'll just come back to what do you
mean by a narrative it is exactly I
think as I said it it it's just a a plan
is this a story but notice the story has
a temporal aspect to it you know I have
narratives about being a good person
being a good father being a good
scientist I also have narratives about
you know I want my cup of coffee or I
have to go look after that if I don't
but Ralph has to go look after the child
um so yeah we've all got narratives at
very very different time scales and
course if you're um you know just come
back to Bert's example of you know I'm
an autonomous vehicle and I'm sentient
and we're five years into the future and
I have to drive around the roundabout
yeah what Temple scale and what kind of
Temple course graining to define the
narrative in narratives would be
appropriate for that kind of situation
um and um
the you know the the ensuing planning so
um so to my uh so a short answer to your
question I think there have been many
many advances
um they have um I think what they've had
in common is basically transcending
either different domains but in
particular different scales of
application I also agree um with the
notion well another I think important
and pragmatic Advance
um is something that Bert mentioned
which is democratization of this
technology and I think Ralph also into
that you know this is the time you start
using this for the for the common good
um
so I think you know things like um RX
infer and pi mdp and I didn't know about
the the Gaia project uh but it sounds as
though there's been great advances there
as well so this kind of democratization
I think is really important this sort of
socialization everybody can play and
start to sort of um not to talk past
each other I think that that's a that's
a very important uh a very important
advance
and did you say the word scale and
variance or scale Independence
that's a scaling variant um I actually
said scale free now I shouldn't have
done that
um I meant
um I I said scale scale free so the the
idea that you can apply exactly the same
mechanics and literally for example say
from birth perspective the same kind of
message passing at different space time
scales or
um at different levels in a hierarchical
model so I've actually got a question
for bird
um in terms of reactive message passing
because
reactive means that you don't have to
um prescribe the scheduling but you in
in addressing the problems or the issues
that are entailed by
um having to specify the scheduling of
talking or of message passing
um you your
um you're bound to deal with time and in
a scale invariant context or nested with
nested scales for example you have to
deal with the temp uh the separation of
temporal scales so I I think there's
going to be a very important generic
question which technically but will have
been thinking about furiously for the
past few years and I think implicitly
we're all going to have to be addressing
soon which is the um how do you put that
the timing of your messages when you
make a move or when you listen to a
patient or
um
when you actually pass a message in on a
photograph
um how does how are you gonna how are we
going to be able to put the separation
of time scales
into the architecture in a way that
speaks to this uh the scaling variance
you know the gear project for example
how do you integrate
um live feed from traffic flow
um sensors with fluctuations in the
climate you know these kinds of this
kind of data comes a very very different
uh Temple scales and yet has to be
assimilated and modeled
um you know
in a way that is also I think has to pay
take you know due courtesy to that
separation of temporal scales
Bert could you please recapitulate the
question for the audience and then begin
to answer it
okay
um
yeah the issue is if you if I mean
active for instance agents are nested
agents and the higher levels
supposed to operate on a larger temporal
scale
but they should they're also working at
a lower resolution right if you if you
look far ahead you don't care as much
about Precision not that the centimeter
level when I go around to around about I
don't care the centimeter where I land
but if I'm but for the next few
milliseconds I do care because it may
mean the difference between getting in
the ditch or not
so
um I don't want to send so the higher
level I want to look very deep ahead but
I don't want to send every milliseconds
a message to go to to look let's say
um a minute ahead because
so I need to space it out a lot but then
I may miss things
um so preferably you would just send
inaccurate messages but that only works
if you actually have a method
to Also let's say use less computational
power to compute a less accurate message
and we're not good at that yet
um there I think I mean what we are
thinking about is there's a new field or
a new field but there's a
a field called probabilistic numerics
where
um we are used in in math to just
compute everything very precisely or as
precise as possible
and and and do not care about how much
computation we spend on it
um so in probabilistic numerics
um I I hope we can leverage this for uh
for message computations
um I would like to spend let's say
proportionally less
computational power on on the accuracy
of a message One Way possibly would be
to consider a message a latent variable
that has an uncertainty by itself
but
I I don't have a a totally clear answer
for for Carl because we haven't solved
that either
um but there
there is a problem in let's say what we
do on our I mean our computers
were so completely different from
computers that from let's say from the
um from the from the brain
that uh yeah we're spending
you're spending just too many
computations on messages that in the end
are very very inaccurate and that's a
problem in what we do on our computers
currently
um
yeah so I don't know
how we go I mean what you want to do
this on the higher level if you you want
to look maybe uh
um 10 times farther ahead and spend
about the same amount of computation on
the lower level that's sort of the uh
our goal
and uh but but we don't have an answer
for that either at the moment
and and Anna so please feel free to
comment on or ask a question to anyone
yeah well I mean I you know I don't I
don't have uh anything to contribute
unfortunately to how computers work but
I can tell you that this idea of
temporal scales is something that we
Face often in our work with patients
um for example addicted patients are
very focused on short-term rewards and
it's it's a fact in fact their ability
to control how they feel in the moment
that is partially what drives the
addiction so when when I try to adopt
url's language of minimizing surprise or
minimizing free entropy
that's one of the things that people are
trying to do on a short-term time scale
when they become addicted so I have a
young woman who's addicted to nitrous
oxide which has a very fast onset of
intoxication over the order of seconds
and a very fast offset and she says that
that's exactly what she likes about it
because she's controlling it second by
second
so when we work with patients to get
them out of that short temporal Horizon
we actually rely more and more on action
and having them change something in
their lives namely abstain from their
drug of choice for long enough to kind
of completely reset their brains and to
allow them to see this longer temporal
because when they're chasing this short
control they're actually not able to see
themselves in the longer narrative Arc
of their lives so that's that was that's
what comes to mind for me I don't think
it's going to be helpful to people who
are trying to build computers but that's
that's the kinds of interventions that I
make with humans
I have a question about that so you
mentioned control in the short term and
you've also mentioned that you study the
positive effects of having a higher
power in your life or or Surrender okay
I kind of gave the punch line Away by
saying surrendering to the higher power
where I was going was okay what's the
association between seeing yourself in
the largest time frame and a higher
power and then also is there something
that is akin to giving up control
when you yeah look farther and farther
into the future such a great yeah that's
right at the heart of what I'm very
interested in because it's a real
Paradox right it's this kind of locus of
control within ourselves that really in
modern culture we we think is a great
thing but when that's taken to an
extreme and one example of that is
addictive behaviors it's very bad for
people and for communities and so what
can be what can pull people out of that
is this kind of surrender to a to a
higher power giving up that locus of
control locating that locus of control
outside themselves not not necessarily
like in a theistic sense
um one of the things you know that they
talk about an alcoholic synonymous for
example is
um you know you don't have to believe in
God it just doesn't it's just not you
you're not you know you're not driving
it and so I would be very curious from
the perspective of ural's understanding
of active inference and the free energy
principle and how the brain works why is
it that um sort of embracing our
inability to control what happens in our
lives can actually be the very source of
healing especially embedded in this
really kind of over controlled yeah I
would even go so far as to say
endemically narcissistic culture like
I'm really curious I I don't want to
take the conversation you know in a
direction yeah please please that's a
fantastic question so if anyone has a
comment on that please
well I have some thought
uh and I think this applies
um supplies both at the personal level
and at the at the global level and I
think it has to do with the the my quote
from earlier uh brought by Edward
fulbrough that uh if you're falling from
a plane yes maybe an altimeter and some
instruments uh might be useful but what
you really need is a parachute right so
we have this
um uh we have this uh presupposition
that that are whatever like framing we
have we have operating in our day-to-day
is going to be okay this this is the
right Framing and it's gonna it tends to
be the this uh this rational scientific
uh framing of of okay very very linear
uh consequence for for most stuff and it
turns out that even like if you inspect
or or day-to-day Behavior you know
bigger more complicated models are not
necessarily better which is where we get
uh the success of heuristics under a
bounded computation boundary rationality
uh and uh if you scale it up to to uh
eight billion humans interacted in a in
a resources Planet you know a world of
possibilities but also of challenges
then you just you have to we have to
like drastically lower our our uh our
bar for
yes how much control we have but also
even like how much was where does uh
information gathering which diminishing
returns where does modeling reach uh
diminishing returns uh there is a whole
literature on uh in the business World
about the expected value of information
how much you should actually invest but
also in science is also uh known as uh
optimal experiment design where
basically you know acknowledging that uh
that you have a limited budget in terms
of how much you can act and how much you
can probe and how much you can how much
time you can spend thinking about stuff
and uh I think what we're doing when we
feel like burned out or or exhausted
from from overthinking uh or in Italy
feeling that that okay we've gone too
high and we need uh we need to to uh
give ourselves a vacation give ourselves
some uh some uh some free time here I
think that doing this on a principle in
a principled way we're just not not just
like taking the heuristics and the
signals that are that we inherit from
from Evolution but actually being able
to figure out uh collaboratively and uh
and with with some rigor okay this is uh
we don't need to know exactly how much
how many degrees the world is going to
warm uh by 2000 2100 in order to know
that maybe it's a good idea to to start
doing something about the amount of of
carbon in the atmosphere or whatever
right uh and so I think this leads to
this this this no knowledge this idea of
a real knowledge economy and of things
like abstraction as a service how can
you actually
um how can you actually build in
um build in this this kind of like
sophisticated and uh and
um sophisticated translation layers that
take some of this burden from from
ourselves as individuals and even as
organizations right uh and just put it
out in the world as as value-added
Services which is what they are
if you have any statements or questions
or retorts then please feel free uh yeah
thanks uh now I was still uh also uh
thinking about the recent breakthrough
post 2020 in action inference uh to to
me like they were like theoretical uh
progress that were very interesting uh
we heard already about the the formalism
maturity at the mathematical level
between military scale and scale free
aspect
um I I really liked or so the the
development of a more multi-agent
perspective of active insurance it's
very interesting like uh especially like
for instance the
seeing military agent systems we just
heard about like even society as well
like as many as one system or many as
many subsystems and how we can uh use
maybe those formalisms to also deal with
policy making that's very interesting
venue and uh the emergence of norms
culture and ideas are so on because
um one thing that I'm still struggling
with in in the case of active inference
models is like how to get outside the
checkerboard uh you you can put a lot in
the in the model a priori and uh how you
make the model creating new stuff that
is not backed inside at the first and I
on that like one very uh interesting
breakthrough was the application of
active inference to morphogenesis I
really like the the work that has been
done on that and on the technical
aspects I think the the two main Focus
that I love are all the Deep active
inference and how to scale up uh
actually in front because it's a strong
limitation for the adoption of the the
formalism uh if it's not scale enough
compared to other framework like deep
learning and then
um the the link with empirical data I
really like for instance the work of
Ryan Smith and how to connect with uh
electrophysiology and clinical data and
I think it's also something very
important to Anchor
uh the theory in in the real world and
have like a fancifiability and empirical
validation of those models
and what are some of the applications of
active inference to morphogenesis
so well I'm not the expert Erica would
be the the best to answer that but uh I
was referring to the the work with
Michael Levin and our mother can uh help
to create a sort of embryogenesis uh
so maybe Carl you can explain better
than me
please yeah I don't have a reputation
for explaining things very clearly
but yeah that's absolutely right
um it was just at work with Michael Evan
and colleagues
um uh showing that um you can get quite
expressive and bimetic out in formation
and movement of different cells into an
organization
um often described in terms of
morphogenesis
um simply by
communicating your beliefs
um so I'm coming back to this sort of
cross-cutting theme of communication so
if you just broadcast
your beliefs and you're a little fell
and you have and there are a little
ensemblance of cells and they all have
the shared charity model that includes
if I was in this position I would sense
that now they all have exactly the same
generative model the same predictions
the same expectations
um and they're all
um broadcasting their beliefs about
where they are and the free energy
minimizing solution is just when they're
all in a place that they except that
they
um receive signals that they would
expect to to
um receive when they're in this place
and of course if that is the same for
everybody there's only one Arrangement
where each cell Finds Its place so
basically it's just knowing your place
is is an immersion property of making
the world mutually predictable through
communication so
you know a deflationary account of
morphogenesis
um but the game I thought you know one
of your units as Precision Psychiatry so
I thought you're going to talk about
Precision so I'm going to do a geom now
I'm going to he he talked about
morphogenesis I'm going to talk about
Precision now
I think there's there's a that's a
really nice way just to pick up on
themes which uh everybody's just
mentioned and in particular the
pathology of precision uh and by
Precision you can reposition uh you know
in the sense that Bert was talking about
in terms of do you use an unsigned
integer or a double you know how much
can I coarse grain to my numeric
representation or you can use it in
terms of course grading in the sense of
the renormalization group you know it's
just chunking things in hours or years
as opposed to milliseconds and minutes
or you can look at it in terms of a
statistician
describing the reliability or the
inverse variance of a signal because we
have to estimate that
um when I say we I mean uh your agents
and statisticians and and act
accordingly and certainly
um in the active in the work of Ryan
Smith uh on addiction much of the sort
of mathematical explanation for these
addictive locked in OCD like a phenomena
rests upon a failure to get that course
grading that Precision estimation right
um
the reason I I I wonder whether it be
just worthwhile revisiting
um
um addiction and psychopathology of its
only pathology of Behavior Uh from the
point of view of getting Precision wrong
and certainly assigning too much
Precision to low level processing which
is what Bert wants to avoid doing
um it distracts me that that kind of
story also has mileage in terms of why
we are in a state of paralysis when it
comes to climate change because I also
notice gear that you talked about
climate action I've never heard that
before but that seems to me to be the
important thing why isn't there any
climate action and Anna you know what
it'll be like you going to the clinic
and finding some of the Parkinson's
disease why isn't this person moving you
know
and interestingly the the computational
explanation for Parkinson's Disease is
assigning too much Precision to the
evidence that you're not moving before
you move so you know if you don't if you
can't ignore the fact that nothing is
changing or your pride beliefs your
predictions that I'm going to stand up
are going to initiate walking
don't get a look at because they are
immediately canceled because they've
assigned too much Precision to the lower
level processing and I'm just wondering
whether that that's something that kind
of pathology is exactly what the the you
know what what Ralph Ralph is trying to
reverse by having you know models that
hand recommendations at hand that
provide a more coarse grained view of
things the deeper view
um
Anna would you like to comment on that
yeah well I just I love I love this idea
of the pathology of precision because I
think it it manifests in so many
different ways
um you know not just among my patient
population but I think it's almost like
a like a cultural sickness in a way
um you know the ways in which we we seem
like obsessed with certain types of data
and we're missing the big picture so I'm
gonna I'm gonna think more about that
I'm gonna read more about it I really
appreciate the discussions interesting
for me
and Adam when you're referring to the
Pathology of precision do you mean so in
a more conscious sense that we're over
evaluating something that we don't need
to whereas Carl you're referring to it
in an unconscious sense like the brain
is
putting too much Precision on something
because in Parkinson's it's it's not
like you consciously are putting
Precision in a place
well I think you could look at it sort
of like in both cases when I think about
addiction
um you know people aren't doing it
consciously it's that they really do
um see this as adaptive and healthy and
also even on some levels they can't do
otherwise
and they're not able to see the true
impact of their drug use on their lives
they're genuinely not able to see the
negative consequences I mean that's
that's what contributes to getting
caught in that vortex
but I mean you could also see it as part
of
what's happened culturally like for
example like the whole Wellness
industrial complex the way that we now
count ourselves
um you know through all these different
devices and if we could just count our
breathing and count our heart rate and
take supplements you know then we would
somehow reach some levitating state of
precise wellness and I don't know I mean
you know just kind of this is all this
is all kind of new new ideas for me
that's interesting so you believe that
we can be inundated with Health Data and
that that's detrimental to us
oh absolutely I see that all the time
uh-huh so for me I used to have uh okay
maybe I'll take this out of the well
this is going out live
okay let me be
let me figure out how to say this
diplomatic diplomatically I used to have
a device that would measure my heart
rate let's say that and and my sleep and
instead of improving my sleep it led to
me becoming obsessed with it and then
noticing oh I didn't sleep well I must
not be feeling good today as well
because apparently there's a high
connection between How You Sleep Quality
exactly it plus added to that the other
layer that I should be able to control
it right so with all of this data and
information I should be able to I don't
know reduce free entropy or whatever how
to reduce surprise as you guys talk
about
um you know and I think that's obviously
that only goes so far and then can
actually contribute to our misery
because where why aren't we all you know
levitating like the Buddha or whatever
um you know when we have all these tools
and we can pay attention to all this
data so
I see this also with people who have
productivity tools so and not only that
but mechanical keyboards let's say
some the reason why I don't have a
mechanical keyboard even though I think
I'd love it is because I know that why
the heck do I care about the clicking
sound of a keyboard but if I got one
then I'd be like well what's the
difference between clicking sound a
versus clicking sound B versus clicking
sound C and I become obsessed with the
trappings of productivity that is
sharpening so-called sharpening the ax
rather than cutting down the tree
there's this phrase that is apocryphal
and it said it's attributed to I think
yeah
Lincoln
which is that he'd spend 80 of his time
or half the time sharpening the knife
than cutting the tree and when you just
if you just think and then this is just
echoed in productivity circles but it
just it can't be the case why would you
spend so much time sharpening your ex
like look at anyone who cuts down a tree
with an X most of the time they're not
doing that
anyhow
so if anyone has any comments on on what
was just said please
can can I uh just talk about what I find
an exciting in my Fields about access
sure sure yes
um I read it was a long time ago but
there was a paper
um and it it's about that it says well
active inference is not really a
scientific Loop because it's biased and
um and I read that and the the
sound of the paper was kind of sort of
just so it's not good
but I think you know active entrance is
is it's maybe not a science book it's an
engineering Loop because there's bias
and we need buyers in engineering we
need to make stuff we need to build
stuff we need to have a biased so it's
an engineering design cycle I see that
everywhere around me
um and active inference could be
um a complete breakthrough in in
engineering right
um the fields around me are signal
processing I myself in a signal
processing uh
the department or group and everybody
builds algorithms
for us I mean an active interest agents
it's influence of States then the floor
below me they build Control Systems well
it's influence over actions
then other people are working on machine
learning it's influence over parameters
active infants could be and you'll like
this curve it's a very deflationary view
on uh on engineering because everything
is just inference and so rather than
building
algorithms everywhere if we become
really good at implementing
minimization we will we will be able to
build a great engineering design cycles
and and we'll be engineering better
machines for us or yeah
you know for medical procedures or for
other things that are important so it
has a tremendous uh application
potential in engineering
um in in engineering I think in most
many fields
people have sort of drifted in different
directions control theorists have I mean
they do almost the same thing as signal
processing people but they speak a
different language now and you know so
uh and everybody and and Signal
processing people
it's a completely different group from
the machine learning people but it's all
information processing and this brings
it uh is filled can bring it together
uh so I think it's the
if but the thing is that in order to
to make it successful in engineering we
need to build an application that uh
well that impresses right that it's not
like a tic-tac-toe thing that it really
needs to impress people it's to be
better than
you know there's some other control
systems but once we do that I think
there's tremendous uh application
potential because there haven't been
enormous breakthroughs in Signal
processing and control the last big
breakthrough
I think it was common filtering and this
was 1960s and and I mean it's it's kind
of uh it's kind of funny that the
essence of what we do in active interest
is also carbon filtering so
um that's uh yeah I think there's
tremendous opportunities for for what we
do here for uh for engineering
so that's why that's why it's exciting
to me
and do you mind expanding on what you
said about acting and therapists should
be helping their patients with that
oh uh sure just so I mean one of my
critiques of uh you know mental health
treatment today is that there's not
enough
um
there's not enough encouragement of
patients to actually go and act
differently in the world as a way of
gathering data instead of it often ends
up being kind of this
World building between therapists and
patients not not necessarily ultimately
adaptive in the world so I was really
just kind of responding to what rap was
saying that we need to act in the world
I think that's
more true now
um in you know modern Rich Nations than
ever before because we are so incredibly
sedentary and interactive of course
we're interacting with a virtual world
and that's
you know good and bad but I mean I think
we need to be actually acting in the
world
um
and so there's there's different forms
of therapy as you know there's talk
therapy and then there's also cognitive
behavioral therapy or Psychotherapy and
talk therapy but but cognitive
behavioral therapy as far as I
understand focuses on on the actions is
that incorrect or
[Music]
um
I mean for you know again treating
addiction like you're you're not going
to really get that far with cognitive
behavioral therapy or anything that's
focused on just emotions and cognitions
people have to go out and actually
um try stop using their stopping their
substance or their addictive behaviors
and gather data from that experience and
then come back and process it
mm-hmm
so Anna in your field and this question
will go to everyone but in your field
and what you study where is the largest
gap that you would like to see closed
well I mean we're facing a huge Mental
Health crisis now we have more and more
young people coming in with depression
anxiety suicidality addictions of all
sorts and these are not necessarily
people who are struggling by virtue of
trauma or socioeconomic disparity these
are people who have really privileged
lives in many instances so it's uh it's
really a puzzle you know what what is
going on for people and I think a big
part of it is
the fact that people are not having
embodied experiences they're not having
experiences in the world
um and and also the experiences that
they are having are
you know these kinds of very quick fixes
and
um fast Pleasures so
are you noticing I think you know the
the co-created sort of models through
healthier communication that allow
people to feel part of a community and
also to have like truthful co-created
narratives trying to use the language
here
um
I think that's really important
so for example one of the things
mentioned once he's excited about one of
the things I'm excited about in the
field of addiction medicine is mutual
support and the proliferation of things
like Alcoholics Anonymous but also other
mutual help groups a lot of them
existing now online and the way that
people are together creating healthier
narratives enacted together to
counteract a lot of the unhealthy
narratives that I think are driving a
lot of decision making today
I wanted to know is there a correlation
between the rise in mental health or
sorry mental illness or mental health
issues whatever we want to call it and
at a certain trait of people like is it
affecting every is it affecting the
population
the same so the whole population has
raised 20 in terms of how many mental
health issues they have per year or is
it affecting people who deal with
abstractions more and more so for
instance we're talking over zoom and
some people study abstractions just like
us and then there's some people who
whose work it is to to do something
physical like running or or swim like is
it affecting everyone equally or are you
noticing that there's some broad trend
well the broad trends that are out there
are just correlational but the more time
that people will spend in the virtual
world the more likely they are to suffer
from depression anxiety and other mental
health problems
um you know people haven't really been
able to narrow that down to specific
content but they have been able to save
just the sheer amount of time that
spending that you're spending online
increases your risk for certain mental
health you know poor mental health
outcomes
[Music]
um
okay now Carl if well again if anyone
has any comments or questions please
just raise your physical hand I can see
that and okay Ralph Raphael sorry oh I
was just gonna say that uh I think
another uh notable trend is that and I
just saw somebody see this on YouTube
yet just yesterday that uh young people
or disproportionately affected by things
like climate grief because they're the
ones that are going to be alive to deal
with it
um and uh I think that applies more
generally that I know Peter Sandy
already like 30 years or something ago
uh wrote about the inescapable network
of neutrality the reality that that uh
that what we're what we do affects each
other right and we built we we took
advantage of this huge resource buffer
that's called uh the biosphere and uh
and uh and and Earth to to pretend that
it didn't for
um for quite a long time and you know
got got a lot of mileage out of it but
it's uh now we're at a point where we
know that there's there's a uh a whole
generation of people that are coming to
grip so the fact that
um I'm gonna stop myself from seeing a
swear word but oh my God we need to uh
we actually need to change everything
about
everything about everything that we do
and and we need to do it fast and uh and
by the way that it's not just uh what we
do in uh
it's not just what we do out there it's
also what we do inside how we get ready
for for how to show up for Life
internally right so no wonder that that
impacts of my my myself I've dealt with
anxiety and uh and uh and a lot of of
other things we've had conversations
about what what are we doing bringing a
daughter into this world and all these
kinds of things I think it's it's only
natural that that it's it's coming to a
head in this way right now
you know when you have your hand up and
I can't see you
yes
um yeah it's connect with the what has
just been said
um so and your initial question about
the the gaps that needs to be closed I
think like uh the scale free model of
health and mental health particularly
would be great like uh we are in silos
in biomedical research and uh the fact
that someone is
uh having depression can come from uh
interacting genes as much as interacting
people and uh also is related to climate
change and so on so how we can have a
new health systems that doesn't deal
with those silos and integrate those
different skills to me it's like really
a big challenge but a challenge that
Quran models and work that we can see
going that direction and I'm very
enthusiastic about that
Bert
um
yeah the um
well I in in my field in engineering
active influence is not understood
because almost all papers are written by
neuroscientists and they're hard to read
so I was really happy to hear today
but I think it's sanjeeb Nam Joshi who
is writing an engineering book on active
inference so that will I think it will
really help
um that together with the availability
of good toolboxes for implementing
active inference should make a lot of
Engineers uh much more enthusiastic
about active influence because that's uh
it's not something that is
and it's not understood at the moment in
engineering circles so I hope that the
book will be good because I'm
enthusiastic about that
and Carl
where where are some
gaps in the in your research that you'd
like to see addressed
um
a little empty space out there yet to be
um explored
um but in terms of
um
in in terms of what seems to be emerging
from um the session and specifically the
past few
um answers it it does seem to be um
important to have
um this very generic just to take births
um sort of line that this is just one
deflationary simple and probably the
right way to understand stuff and to
make recommendations or to
um describe uh people's actions possibly
to themselves in a therapeutic uh
context and and as such it should be
push button technology and it should be
democratized and socialized and
um I I think that's the challenge
practically
um and what one may ask why would you
want to do that
um for me that there are two
um clear imperatives
um one is
um very abstract and it's not really my
uh um within my comfort zone and the
other one is in my cumbersome another
one that's outside my comfort zone as
um is um this notion of
um
interactivity and Hyper connectivity in
them and and The Meta crisis that we we
heard about
um and um and our game also refer to
this in terms of what he was trying he
was trying to distinguish between a
Californian notion of optimality and
another kind another way forward
um and to me it's it's it's you know a
stark contrast with growth is good
versus sustainability and of course the
maths of the free energy principle is
just about sustainability it's just a
description of the physics of systems
random dynamical systems that
self-organized to some non-equilibrium
steady state and that is what we are
um so you know for me there's something
deeply if you like apt about the free
energy principle and its coronal risk
such as active inference in application
to ecosystems and lived ecosystems and
realized ecosystems so if that if those
basic principles can be brought back
um into globalization uh into the you
know into the market into fintech into
um social media into politics into your
climate action I think that would be a
good thing
um I'm just mindful of you know this
struck me in a number of the
presentations today
um you remember before Bert was saying
if you look at the brain which is a
really lovely example of a
self-organizing system to a
non-equilibrium steady state
um then it's empty and what did he mean
by that it didn't mean you were
empty-headed what he meant was it's
incredibly sparsely connected
now that tells you immediately that a
pathology of connectivity is hyper
connective to overconnectivity which
immediately
um well it made me very alert to
um the presentation of the meta crisis
that one of the first three things that
was and underwrote them the the metacris
or you know the current crisis were
conduct ending with is a destruction of
that sparse Delica connectivity that
defines thingness and defines ensembles
of things technically in terms of Markov
blankets so if we want a world in which
lots of different things can coexist in
some kind of generalized synchrony in a
sustainable way
new deep sparse connectivity and the
pathology the thing that will destroy
that is over connectivity
um so it seems to be very important that
we get that into uh into play in terms
of uh machine learning
um artificial intelligence politics
fintech climate change and the only way
it's going to get there is is
epistemically by uh equipping people to
actually
um build their own little models and ask
their own questions you can't tell
people this they've got to learn and
they're going to learn it for themselves
uh just very quickly because I'm sure
yeah we've only got a couple of minutes
left um the the the
um the other agenda which I'm more
familiar with is exactly Anderson and
guillaume's agenda which is uh making
this work in the context of uh
um of Neurology and Psychiatry
um so if you can democratize
um and socialize this way of describing
things so that people can now build
models of their particular patient in
the other use of precision Psychiatry
um that are suspended games unit was
called after
um so to personalized medicine that is
really personalized in the sense that it
yo you actually have your digital twin
of the of your behavior and then you've
got that you know you optimize your
digital twin to become a model of your
patient and then you can start to do
experiments on that on that model
behavioral interventions or even share
that model very much in the spirit of
CBT with the patient and say look this
is you this is what would happen if you
went out and did this and this is what
would happen if you went out and did
that
um you know that that to to my mind and
indeed that was the initial motivation
for much of this work was actually to
build
um observation models of psychiatric
conditions to work out both the
um the the pharmacological and
physiological basis on the disruption of
the overly the pathology of precision
and message passing on the factor graphs
that are our brain even though they are
very empty and on the one hand but also
get that behavior that that key thing
that Anna was talking about the active
engagement with the lived world uh into
into that model and hence active
inference and just to conclude you know
um that that that activity that sort of
physical engagement that embodiment that
sort of um four ease and everything else
um I think it's really coming to a head
now in terms of people's um you know
after the large language model after the
church EPT moment people the bounce back
uh has been What's missing
you know what's not there and of course
what is not there is agency and embodied
engagement with the world
um and that's why I think that's the
whole there's still a lot of work to be
done you know in bringing artificial
intelligence red as active inference to
in a way that matters to people who you
know your the people who can make a
difference which is basically everybody
but specifically politicians and doctors
and the engineers and the like
so you all now have 30 seconds to 60
seconds to speak directly to the
audience what is the message that you
what closing message do you have you're
speaking directly to someone who's
listening you're a curious person
they're interested in active inference
they also want to lead Better Lives
hopefully and and and do something
propitious so what message do you have
for them
Anna we'll start with you
gosh
um I'm just gonna say what pops into my
mind right now is that one of the things
I have learned from my patients who are
trying to get into recovery from severe
addictions is something that they call
the set aside prayer where they set
aside all of the Notions that they have
about how the world works and try to be
completely open and receptive to
information coming into their minds and
I think that's just a wonderful
um
a wonderful frame or concept for all of
us uh living in the world to
periodically just take a moment and take
these models and just say you know
everything I think I know about the
world I'm going to temporarily suspend
it and I'm just going to be open and
when that happens we can be present and
learn in a way that it's not possible
when we're just trying to reinforce our
models
great fantastic and Bert and then we'll
go Carl and then Rapha and then
Guillaume
um well I I just enjoyed today very much
I thought there was a
there was a little material boost for
people from let's say psychology
Neuroscience but also from for engineers
so if you haven't watched some of the
talks go go go look through the schedule
because some of the talks were really
good I think so I really enjoyed that
um and then yeah what should I tell
people um go work out do do a lot of
sports it's good for you
[Music]
oh
yeah sorry I was going to make a joke
but I can't because
[Music]
um so I'm going to use my 32nd uh just
to thank uh Daniel and his team for for
this um you know so if you want
something to do
um you should go and watch the live
streams
um and
um get involved with this ecosystem I
haven't seen that paper be presented
before but I was really impressed with
you know with the sort of the active
Institute and its openness and it's your
welcoming
um
um attitude and vision like the
Smithsonian
um so if you want to pursue these ideas
get involved and if you uh haven't got
time just make sure you attend next
year's active inference Institute a
celebration but thank you Daniel
Raphael
yeah so I'll second what uh what Carl
said and follow along with uh it's it's
an invitation not just uh to participate
in the in the active defense Institute
but also an invitations participate in
uh building this uh this Gaia tractor
this uh this new way of of doing things
that acknowledges the value of growth uh
and also the value of sustainability
joins it all together in this thing
called regeneration
and uh it really is uh it really is a
collective effort it's a collective
learning effort so
um so and this also by the way also
applies to to the the panelists as well
and I think uh obviously what uh board
and Carl are doing it has immediate uh
things having that have to do with with
uh what we're after but one of the main
things that we discussed that we keep
discussing is also like this uh the
inter intersubjectivity and the The
Importance of Being able to operate well
as humans together and that connects
directly to cognitive science Psychiatry
on
and uh and yeah so everybody that wants
to to to be engaged and and be a part of
building a better world should be
thinking about how do I how what am I
doing with my as an individual or as a
as a employee organization or a
researcher or as a leader uh or the
family member what am I doing how does
it contribute to to this uh this new
this new non-steady non non equilibrium
set of state so yeah that's that's kind
of it I probably blew through the 60
seconds but here it is
well uh I would thanks also all of you
for the discussion and the organizer for
what they are doing indeed like the
the work of the actual Insurance
Institute is very uh lovable and
interesting from open science
perspective they are really uh embodying
that so big kudos to them and uh well uh
where the fridge was saying like to do
sport is good for you I'm not very good
at sports but uh some say that science
is a team sport so at least uh I have a
good team perspective when doing science
and being kind to each other would be
the best advice to to everyone
well thank you I also would like to you
get you get yours too somebody else has
to come in from outside the Markov
blanket though
right well I wanted to just thank you
Daniel thank you Daniel and and Raphael
and well and also Carl and Anna and Bert
and Yom this was a tremendous amount of
fun and well I hope I get to speak to
you all individually and for I as usual
I have way more questions than we were
able to get to
thank you all
thanks guys thank you thanks everyone
farewell panelists you're all welcome
back anytime
um thanks everybody for watching or
re-watching
right now we're about to head over to
the Discord and hang out and talk a
little more if you want to and then stay
involved get involved so until next time
bye bye-bye bye-bye